<document xml:lang="fao" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="news"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>19057</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>K 037-2025.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="nno">Nr. 37 24. mars 2025</p>
<p><em type="bold">Kunngerð um broyting í kunngerð um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina </em>(Avmarkandi tiltøk fyri ávís skip, áseta nærri upplýsingarkrøv í sambandi við undantaksumsóknir og revsireglur í hesum sambandi, at broyta skjal 2 og 5 til kunngerðina, o.a.) <em type="bold">§ 1 </em></p>
<p>Í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um av-markandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina verða gjørdar hesar broytingar: <em type="bold">1. </em>Í § 13, stk. 2, nr. 2 verður <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">“meklaratænastum.”</span>broytt til: <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">“meklaratænastum,”</span>. <em type="bold">2. </em>Í § 13 verður sum stk. 5 sett:“ <em type="italic">Stk. 5. </em>Forboðið sambært stk. 1, viðvíkjandisølu, veitan, flytan ella útflytan av vørum undir CN 3920 10 28, CN 3920 20 00 og CN 3925 10, umframt forboðið fyri at veita tænastur ella stuðul eftir stk. 2, nr. 1 og 2 í hesum sambandi, kemur í gildi 26. februar 2026.” <em type="bold">3. </em>§ 14, stk. 2, nr. 1 verður orðað soleiðis:<span type="quote">“1) Beinleiðis ella óbeinleiðis at keypa ellainnflyta jarnvørur og stálvørur, sum nevndar í skjali 3, umframt vørur, sum nevndar eru í skjali 5, til Føroya, um hesar vørur:”</span> <em type="bold">4. </em>Í § 14 verður sum stk. 3 sett:“ <em type="italic">Stk. 3. </em>Forboðið sambært stk. 2, nr. 1, við-víkjandi keypi ella innflutningi til Føroya av vørum undir CN 7601, umframt forboðið fyri at veita stuðul ella tænastur eftir § 2, stk. 2 í hesum sambandi, kemur í gildi 26. februar 2026.” <em type="bold">5. </em>Aftan á § 15 verður í kapittul 4 sett:“ <em type="italic">Forboð fyri innflutningi, útflutningi, sølu,veitan av tænastum, o.a. fyri ávís skip </em><em type="bold">§ 15 a. </em>Fyri skip, sum eru nevnd í skjali 6 A,er tað bannað beinleiðis ella óbeinleiðis at: 1)geva nevndu skipum atgongd til havnir ella akkerspláss í føroyskum sjóumveldi, ella at nevndu skip fáa slíka atgongd,2)innflyta, keypa ella á annan hátt at flyta nevndu skip til Føroya,3)selja, útvega, leiga, heruppií at chartra, ella at útflyta nevndu skip,4)reka ella at manna nevndu skip,5)flaggskráseta nevndu skip,6)veita fígging ella fíggjarligan stuðul, heruppií trygging, umframt miðlanartænastur, heruppií skipsmekling, til nevndu skip,7)veita tekniskan stuðul ella aðrar tænastur, heruppií viðvíkjandi bunkring, útgerð, skifti av manning, lasting ella lossing, fendarahjálp ella sleipingartænastur til nevndu skip, og8)luttaka í skip-til-skip umskiping ella aðrari flyting av farmi, ella at keypa tænastur frá nevndu skipum. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 2. </em>Skjal 6 A fevnir um skip, sum eru fevnd av artikli 3s, nr. 2, litra a-g, í fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 833/2014, sum nærri tilskilað í fylgiskjali XLII til nevndu fyriskipan. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 3. </em>Stk. 1 er ikki galdandi um eitt skip, sum er nevnt í skjali 6 A, hevur tørv á hjálp og leitar í neyðhavn, ella av neyð má leggja inn í føroyska havn við atliti at trygd á sjónum ella fyri at bjarga lívi á sjónum, við atliti til menniskjalig endamál ella fyri at fyribyrgja ella verja seg móti einari hending, sum sannlíkt vil bera við sær álvarsom og munandi árin fyri heilsustøðuna hjá menniskjum ella umhvørvinum, ella sum avleiðing av einari náttúruvanlukku, ella til tess at kunna viðurkenna ella fremja ein rættarúrskurð ella ein gerðarrættarúrskurð, sum er sagdur í Føroyum ella í einum ES-landi, ella við atliti til at tryggja rannsókn av lógarbrotum.” <em type="bold">6. </em>Í § 20 verða sum stk. 2-4 sett:“ <em type="italic">Stk. 2. </em>Umsókn um undantak eftir stk. 1, skalinnihalda upplýsingar um navn, bústað, skrásetingarnummar og samskiftisupplýsingar hjá útflytara, keypara, endabrúkara umframt møguligum umboðsfólkum, sum luttaka í transaktiónini. Fyri løgfrøðiligar persónar uttan skrásetingarnummar, skal felagsskráin, har løg- </p>
<p>Givið út 25. mars 2025frøðiligi persónurin er skrásettur, og skrásetingarnummarið gevast upp, umframt upplýsingar um møguligt skattaeyðmerkingarnummar í heimlandinum.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 3. </em>Tilskilast skal í umsóknini hvørt keyp-arin og endabrúkarin eru ein og sami persónur, og í hvørjum landi vøran endaliga skal nýtast í. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 4. </em>Hvør vøra, sum biðið verður um undantak fyri, skal eyðmerkjast annaðhvørt eftir Combined Nomenclature (CN) ella samsvarandi toll- og vøruskránni. Harumframt skal útflytarin upplýsa um bíleggingarnummarið ella sáttmálanummarið ella líknandi og, um keypari og endabrúkari ikki eru ein og sami persónur, í hvørjum landi ella umborð á hvørjum skipi, vøran endaliga skal nýtast í.” <em type="bold">7. </em>Í § 22, stk. 1 verður aftan á 1. pkt. sum nýtt pkt. sett: <span type="quote">“Á sama hátt verður tann revsaður, sum í sambandi við eina umsókn um undantak eftir § 20, tilætlað ella av grovum ósketni letur myndug-leikanum ósannar ella villleiðandi upplýsingar eftir § 20, stk. 2-4.”</span> <em type="bold">8. </em>Skjal 2 í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 1. <em type="bold">9. </em>Skjal 5 í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 2. <em type="bold">10. </em>Skjal 3 verður sett sum skjal 6 A í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina. <em type="bold">§ 2 </em></p>
<p>Henda kunngerð kemur í gildi dagin eftir, at hon er kunngjørd.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Uttanríkis- og vinnumálaráðið, 24. mars 2025</p>
<p><em type="bold">Sirið Stenberg (sign.) </em>landsstýriskvinna / Herálvur Joensen (sign.) 2 </p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 1 </em>“ <em type="bold">Skjal 2 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Listi við vørum, sum loyvt er at útflyta til Russlands samsvarandi § 13 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">CN Code </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Description </em>02 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Meat and edible meat offal 03</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Fish and crustaceans, molluscs and other aquatic invertebrates 04</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dairy produce; birds’ eggs; natural honey; edible products of animal origin; not elsewhere specified or included 05</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products of animal origin, not elsewhere specified or included ex 06</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Live trees and other plants; bulbs, roots and the like; cut flowers and ornamental foliage, excluding CN 0601 (Bulbs, tubers, tuberous roots, corms, crowns and rhizomes, dormant, in growth or in flower, chicory plants and roots other than roots of heading 1212:), 0602 30 (Rhododendrons and azaleas, grafted or not), 0602 40 (Roses, grafted or not), 0602 90 (Other live plants (including their roots), cuttings and slips; mushroom spawn – Other), and 0604 20 (Foliage, branches and other parts of plants, without flowers or flower buds, and grasses, mosses and lichens, being goods of a kind suitable for bouquets or for ornamental purposes, fresh, dried, dyed, bleached, impregnated or otherwise prepared – Fresh). ex 07</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Edible vegetables and certain roots and tubers, excluding CN 0709 56 00 (Truffles), 0710 80 69 (Other), 0711 59 00 (Other), 0712 39 00 (Other). 08</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Edible fruit and nuts; peel of citrus fruit and melons 09</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coffee, tea, maté and spices 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cereals 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products of the milling industry; malt; starches; inulin, wheat gluten 12</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oil seeds and oleaginous fruits; miscellaneous grains, seeds and fruit; industrial or medicinal plants; straw and fodder 13</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lac; grums; resins and other vegetable saps and extracts 14</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vegetable plaiting materials; vegetable products not elsewhere specified or included 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Animal or vegetable fats and oils and their cleavage products; prepared edible fats; animal or vegetable waxes ex 16</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of meat, of fish or of crustaceans, molluscs or other aquatic invertebrates, excluding CN 1604 31 00 (Caviar) and 1604 32 00 (Caviar substitutes) 17</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sugars and sugar confectionery 18</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cocoa and cocoa preparations 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of cereals, flour, starch or milk; pastrycooks’ products ex 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of vegetables, fruit, nuts or other parts of plants, excluding 2001 90 97 (Other) and 2003 90 10 (Truffles) ex 21</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Miscellaneous edible preparations, excluding CN 2103 90 90 (Other), 2104 10 00 (Soups and broths and preparations therefor), 2104 20 00 (Homogenised composite food preparations), and 2106 00 00 (Food preparations not elsewhere specified or included) ex 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Beverages, spirits and vinegar, excluding CN 2203 00 00 (Beer made from malt), 2204 10 11 (Champagne), 2204 10 91 (Asti spurmante), 2204 10 93 (Other), 2204 10 94 (With a protected geographical indication (PGI)), 2204 10 96 (Other varietal wines), 32204 10 98 (Other), 2204 21 00 (In containers holding 2 litres or less), 2204 29 00 (Other), 2205 00 00 (Vermouth and other wine of fresh grapes flavoured with plants or aromatic substances), 2206 00 00 (Other fermented beverages (for example, cider, perry, mead, saké); mixtures of fermented beverages and mixtures of fermented beverages with non-alcoholic beverages, not elsewhere specified or included), 2207 10 00 (Undenatured ethyl alcohol of an alcoholic strength by volume of 80 % vol or higher), and 2208 00 00 (Undenatured ethyl alcohol of an alcoholic strength by volume of less than 80 % vol; spirits, liqueurs and other spirituous beverages) 23</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Residues and waste from the food industries; prepared animal fodder ex 24</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tobacco and manufactured tobacco substitutes, excluding CN 2402 10 00 (Cigars, cheroots and cigarillos, containing tobacco) and 2402 90 00 (Other) 2505</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural sands of all kinds, whether or not coloured, other than metal-bearing sands of Chapter 26 2707</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oils and other products of the distillation of high temperature coal tar; similar products in which the weight of the aromatic constituents exceeds that of the non-aromatic constituents, excluding 2707 30 (Xylol (xylenes)) 2710 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medium oils and preparations, of petroleum or bituminous minerals, not containing biodiesel, n.e.s. 2711</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Petroleum gases and other gaseous hydrocarbons 2716</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Electrical energy 2853</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Phosphides, whether or not chemically defined, excluding ferrophosphorus; other inorganic compounds (including distilled or conductivity water and water of similar purity); liquid air (whether or not rare gases have been removed); compressed air; amalgams, other than amalgams of precious metals 2932</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Heterocyclic compounds with oxygen hetero-atom(s) only 3005</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wadding, gauze, bandages and the like, e.g. dressings, adhesive plasters, poultices, impregnated or covered with pharmaceutical substances or put up for retail sale for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes 3006</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pharmaceutical preparations and products of subheadings 3006 10 10 to 3006 93 00 3215 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ink, whether or not concentrated or solid (excl. printing ink) 3303</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Perfumes and toilet waters (Perfumes, toilet waters and cosmetics, including beauty and makeup products, value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 3304 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Beauty or make-up preparations and preparations for the care of the skin (other than medicaments), including sunscreen or suntan preparations; manicure or pedicure preparations (Perfumes, toilet waters and cosmetics, including beauty and make-up products, value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 3305 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations for use on the hair (Perfumes, toilet waters and cosmetics, including beauty and make-up products, value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 3307 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pre-shave, shaving or aftershave preparations, personal deodorants, bath preparations, depilatories and other perfumery, cosmetic or toilet preparations, not elsewhere specified or included; prepared room deodorisers, whether or not perfumed or having disinfectant properties (Perfumes, toilet waters and cosmetics, including beauty and make-up products, value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 3401</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for use as soap, in the form of bars, cakes, moulded pieces or shapes, whether or not containing soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for washing the skin, in the form of liquid or cream and put up for retail sale, whether or not containing soap; paper, wadding, felt and nonwovens, impregnated, coated or covered with soap or detergent 43402</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Organic surface-active agents (other than soap); surface-active preparations, washing preparations (including auxiliary washing preparations) and cleaning preparations, whether or not containing soap, other than those of heading 3401 3503</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gelatin (including gelatin in rectangular (including square) sheets, whether or not surfaceworked or coloured) and gelatin derivatives; isinglass; other glues of animal origin, excluding casein glues of heading 3501 3506 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products suitable for use as glues or adhesives, put up for retail sale as glues or adhesives, not exceeding a net weight of 1 kg 3506 91</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Adhesives based on polymers of headings 3901 to 3913 or on rubber (excl. put up for retail sale with a net weight of &lt;= 1 kg) 3801</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artificial graphite; colloidal or semi-colloidal graphite; preparations based on graphite or other carbon in the form of pastes, blocks, plates or other semi-manufactures, excluding CN 3801 20 (colloidal or semicolloidal graphite) 3822</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Diagnostic or laboratory reagents on a backing, prepared diagnostic or laboratory reagents whether or not on a backing, other than those of heading 3002 or 3006; certified reference materials 3901</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of ethylene, in primary forms, excluding CN 3901 40 (ethylene-alpha-olefin copolymers, having a specific gravity of &lt; 0,94, in primary forms) and 3208 (solutions of products of headings 3901 to 3913 in volatile organic solvents, containing &gt; 50 % solvent by weight (excl. solutions of collodion)) 3907 30</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Epoxide resins, in primary forms 3919</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Self-adhesive plates, sheets, film, foil, tape, strip and other flat shapes, of plastics, whether or not in rolls 3923</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles for the conveyance or packing of goods, of plastics; stoppers, lids, caps and other closures, of plastics 3924</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tableware, kitchenware, other household articles and hygienic or toilet articles, of plastics 3926</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of plastics and articles of other materials of heading 3901 to 3914, n.e.s. 4001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural rubber, balata, gutta-percha, guayule, chicle and similar natural gums, in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip 4003</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Reclaimed rubber in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip 4004</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Waste, parings and scrap of rubber (other than hard rubber) and powders and granules obtained therefrom 4006</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other forms (for example, rods, tubes and profile shapes) and articles (for example, discs and rings), of unvulcanised rubber, excluding CN 4006 10 (‘camelback’ strips of unvulcanised rubber, for retreading rubber tyres) 4009</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber other than hard rubber, with or without their fittings (for example, joints, elbows, flanges), excluding CN 4009 12 (tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber), not reinforced or otherwise) and 4009 41 (tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber), reinforced or otherwise combined with materials other than metal or textile materials, without fittings) 4011</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, excluding CN 4011 20 (New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, of a kind used for buses and lorries) and 4011 80 (New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, of a kind used on construction, mining or industrial handling vehicles and machines) 4015 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gloves, mittens and mitts, of a kind used for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes, of vulcanised rubber 4015 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gloves, mittens and mitts, of vulcanised rubber (excl. of a kind used for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes) (Articles and equipment for sports, including skiing, golf, diving and water sports <em type="italic">, </em>value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 4015 90 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of apparel and clothing accessories, for all purposes, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber and footwear and headgear and parts thereof, and gloves, mittens and mitts) (Articles 5and equipment for sports, including skiing, golf, diving and water sports <em type="italic">, </em>value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 4016 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other articles of vulcanised rubber other than hard rubber, excluding 4016 93 (gaskets, washers and other seals, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber and those of cellular rubber)) 4202</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Trunks, suitcases, vanity cases, executive-cases, briefcases, school satchels, spectacle cases, binocular cases, camera cases, musical instrument cases, gun cases, holsters and similar containers; travelling-bags, insulated food or beverage bags, toilet bags, rucksacks, handbags, shopping-bags, wallets, purses, map-cases, cigarette-cases, tobacco-pouches, tool bags, sports bags, bottle-cases, jewellery boxes, powder-boxes, cutlery cases and similar containers, of leather or of composition leather, of sheeting of plastics, of textile materials, of vulcanised fibre or of paperboard, or wholly or mainly covered with such materials or with paper. (Leather, saddlery and travel goods, handbags and similar articles, value not exceeding EUR 300 per item) 4203 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of apparel and clothing accessories, of leather or composition leather (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 4415 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Packing cases, boxes, crates, drums and similar packings, of wood; cable-drums of wood; pallets, box pallets and other load boards, of wood; pallet collars of wood (excl. containers specially designed and equipped for one or more modes of transport) 4802 56</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Packing cases, boxes, crates, drums and similar packings, of wood; cable-drums of wood; pallets, box pallets and other load boards, of wood; pallet collars of wood (excl. containers specially designed and equipped for one or more modes of transport) 4802 62</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Uncoated paper and paperboard, of a kind used for writing, printing or other graphic purposes, and non-perforated punchcards and punch-tape paper, in square or rectangular sheets with one side &lt;= 435 mm and the other side &lt;= 297 mm in the unfolded state, of which &gt; 10% by weight of the total fibre content consists of fibres obtained by a mechanical or chemi-mechanical process, n.e.s. 4818</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Toilet paper and similar paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres, of a kind used for household or sanitary purposes, in rolls of a width &lt;= 36 cm, or cut to size or shape; handkerchiefs, cleansing tissues, towels, tablecloths, serviettes, bedsheets and similar household, sanitary or hospital articles, articles of apparel and clothing accessories, of paper pulp, paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres 4819</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cartons, boxes, cases, bags and other packing containers, of paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres; box files, letter trays, and similar articles, of paper or paperboard of a kind used in offices, shops or the like, excluding 4819 20 (folding cartons, boxes and cases, of non-corrugated paper or paperboard) 4820</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registers, account books, notebooks, order books, receipt books, letter pads, memorandum pads, diaries and similar articles, exercise books, blotting pads, binders, folders, file covers, manifold business forms, interleaved carbon sets and other articles of stationery, of paper or paperboard; albums for samples or for collections and book covers, of paper and paperboard 4821</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Paper or paperboard labels of all kinds, whether or not printed 5602</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Felt, whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or laminated, n.e.s. 5603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nonwovens, whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or laminated, n.e.s. 5607</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Twine, cordage, ropes and cables, whether or not plaited or braided and whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or sheathed with rubber or plastics, excluding CN 5607 41 (binder or baler twine, of polyethylene or polypropylene) 5608</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Knotted netting of twine, cordage or rope, by the piece or metre; made-up fishing nets and other made-up nets, of textile materials (excl. hairnets, nets for sporting purposes, incl. landing nets, butterfly nets and the like) 5702 91</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carpets and other textile floor coverings, woven, not tufted or flocked, whether or not made up, incl. Kelem, Schumacks, Karamanie and similar hand-woven rugs of wool or fine animal hair (Carpets, rugs and tapestries, hand-made or not, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 5902 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tyre cord fabric of high-tenacity yarn of nylon or other polyamides, polyesters or viscose rayon, whether or not dipped or impregnated with rubber or plastic 65909</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Textile hosepiping and similar textile tubing, whether or not impregnated or coated, with or without lining, armour or accessories of other materials 5911 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Textile products and articles, for technical purposes, specified in Note 7 to chapter 59, n.e.s. 6101</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks (including ski jackets), windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles, knitted or crocheted, other than those of heading 6103 (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6102 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Women’s or girls’ overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks (including ski jackets), windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles, knitted or crocheted, other than those of heading 6104 (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), if value does <em type="italic">not </em>exceed EUR 300 per item) 6103 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (excl. wind-jackets and similar articles, separate waistcoats, tracksuits, ski suits and swimwear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6107 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' underpants, briefs, nightshirts, pyjamas, bathrobes, dressing gowns and similar articles, knitted or crocheted (excl. vests and singlets) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6109 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">T-shirts, singlets and other vests, knitted or crocheted (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6111 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Babies' garments and clothing accessories, knitted or crocheted (excl. hats) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6115 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pantyhose, tights, stockings, socks and other hosiery, incl. graduated compression hosiery [e.g., stockings for varicose veins] and footwear without applied soles, knitted or crocheted (excl. for babies) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6116 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gloves, mittens and mitts, knitted or crocheted (excl. for babies) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6201 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks, incl. ski jackets, windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles (excl. knitted or crocheted, suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers and trousers) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6203 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (excl. knitted or crocheted, wind-jackets and similar articles, separate waistcoats, tracksuits, ski suits and swimwear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6204 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Women's or girls' suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, dresses, skirts, divided skirts, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (excl. knitted or crocheted, wind-jackets and similar articles, slips, petticoats and panties, tracksuits, ski suits and swimwear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6211 33 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' tracksuits and other garments, n.e.s. of man-made fibres (excl. knitted or crocheted) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6211 39 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men's or boys' tracksuits and other garments, n.e.s. of textile materials (excl. of cotton or manmade fibres, knitted or crocheted) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6302 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bedlinen, table linen, toilet linen and kitchen linen of all types of textile materials (excl. floorcloths, polishing cloths, dishcloths and dusters) 6305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sacks and bags, of a kind used for the packing of goods, of all types of textile materials 6306</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tarpaulins, awnings and sunblinds; tents; sails for boats, sailboards or landcraft; camping goods of all types of textile materials (excl. flat protective coverings of light woven fabrics; 7umbrella and play tents; rucksacks, napsacks and similar containers; sleeping bags, mattresses and pillows, incl. their fillings) 6307</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Made-up articles of textile materials, incl. dress patterns, n.e.s. 6310</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Used or new rags, scrap twine, cordage, rope and cables and worn-out articles thereof, of textile materials 6401 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Waterproof footwear with outer soles and uppers of rubber or of plastics, the uppers of which are neither fixed to the sole nor assembled by stitching, riveting, nailing, screwing, plugging or similar processes (excl. orthopaedic footwear, toy footwear, skating boots with ice skates attached, shin-guards and similar protective sportswear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6402 91 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Footwear covering the ankle, with outer soles and uppers of rubber or plastics (excl. waterproof footwear of heading 6401, sports footwear, orthopaedic footwear and toy footwear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6403 40 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Footwear, incorporating a protective metal toecap, with outer soles of rubber, plastics, leather or composition leather and uppers of leather (excl. sports footwear and orthopaedic footwear) (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6405 00 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Footwear with outer soles of rubber or plastics, with uppers other than rubber, plastics, leather or textile materials; footwear with outer soles of leather or composition leather, with uppers other than leather or textile materials; footwear with outer soles of wood, cork, twine, paperboard, furskin, woven fabrics, felt, nonwovens, linoleum, raffia, straw, loofah, etc and uppers of any type of material, n.e.s. (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6406 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts of footwear, incl. uppers whether or not attached to soles other than outer soles; removable in-soles, heel cushions and similar articles; gaiters, leggings and similar articles, and parts thereof (excl. articles of asbestos) 6505</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hats and other headgear, knitted or crocheted, or made up from lace, felt or other textile fabric, in the piece (but not in strips), whether or not lined or trimmed; hairnets of any material, whether or not lined or trimmed 6505 00 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of fur felt or of felt of wool and fur, made from the hat bodies, hoods or plateaux of heading 6501 00 00 (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6505 00 30 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Peaked caps (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6505 00 90 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other (Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material), value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 6506 10 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Headgear, whether or not lined or trimmed, n.e.s. 6804 21</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Millstones, grindstones, grinding wheels and the like, without frameworks, for sharpening, polishing, trueing or cutting, of agglomerated synthetic or natural diamond (excl. hand sharpening or polishing stones, and grinding wheels etc. specifically for dental drill engines) 6804 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Millstones, grindstones, grinding wheels and the like, without frameworks, for sharpening, polishing, trueing or cutting, of agglomerated abrasives or ceramics (excl. of agglomerated synthetic or natural diamond, hand sharpening or polishing stones, perfumed pumice stones, and grinding wheels etc. specifically for dental drill engines) 6805</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural or artificial abrasive powder or grain, on a base of textile material, paper, paperboard or other materials, whether or not cut to shape or sewn or otherwise made up 6903</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Retorts, crucibles, mufflers, nozzles, plugs, supports, cupels, tubes, pipes, sheaths, rods, slide gates and other refractory ceramic goods (excl. those of siliceous fossil meals or of similar siliceous earths, and refractory bricks, blocks, tiles and similar refractory ceramic constructional goods) 7019</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Glass fibres, incl. glass wool, and articles thereof (excl. mineral wools and articles thereof, optical fibres, fibre bundles or cable, electrical insulators or parts thereof, brushes of glass fibres, dolls' wigs) 87312</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stranded wire, ropes, cables, plaited bands, slings and the like, of iron or steel (excl. electrically insulated products and twisted fencing wire and barbed wire) 7315</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Chain and parts thereof, or iron or steel (excl. watch chains, necklace chains and the like, cutting and saw chain, skid chain, scraper chain for conveyors, toothed chain for textile machinery and the like, safety devices with chains for securing doors, measuring chains) 7317</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nails, tacks, drawing pins, corrugated nails, staples and similar articles of iron or steel, whether or not with heads of other material (excl. such articles with heads of copper and staples in strips) 7318 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Threaded screws and bolts, of iron or steel, whether or not with their nuts and washers (excl. coach screws and other wood screws, screw hooks and screw rings, self-tapping screws, lag screws, stoppers, plugs and the like, threaded) 7318 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Threaded articles, of iron or steel, n.e.s. 7318 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Washers of iron or steel (excl. spring washers and other lock washers) 7318 29</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Non-threaded articles, of iron or steel 7326</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of iron or steel, n.e.s. (excl. cast articles) 7403</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Copper, refined, and copper alloys, unwrought (excl. copper alloys of heading 7405) 7415 33</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Screws, bolts, nuts and similar articles, threaded, of copper (other than screw hooks, ring- and eyebolts, lag screws, plugs, bungs and the like, with screw thread) 8202 31</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Circular saw blades, incl. slitting or slotting saw blades, of base metal, with working parts of steel 8202 91</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Straight saw blades, of base metal, for working metal 8203</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Files, rasps, pliers, incl. cutting pliers, pincers and tweezers for non-medical use, metal-cutting shears, pipe-cutters, bolt croppers, perforating punches and similar hand tools, of base metal 8204</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hand-operated spanners and wrenches, incl. torque meter wrenches (excl. tap wrenches), of base metal; interchangeable spanner sockets, with or without handles, of base metal 8205</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hand tools, incl. glaziers' diamonds, of base metal, n.e.s.; blowlamps and the like; vices, clamps and the like (other than accessories for and parts of machine-tools or water-jet cutting machines); anvils; portable forges; hand-operated or pedal-operated grinding wheels with frameworks 8211</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Knives with cutting blades, serrated or not, incl. pruning knives, and blades therefor, of base metal (excl. straw knives, machetes, knives and cutting blades for machines or mechanical appliances, fish knives, butter knives, razors and razor blades and knives of heading 8214) 8305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Fittings for loose-leaf binders or files, letter clips, letter corners, paper clips, indexing tags and similar office articles, of base metal (excl. drawing pins and clasps for books or registers); staples in strips, e.g. for use in offices, upholstery and packaging, of base metal 8308</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Clasps, frames with clasps, buckles, buckle-clasps, hooks, eyes, eyelets and the like, of base metal, of a kind used for clothing, footwear, awnings, handbags, travel goods or other made-up articles, tubular or bifurcated rivets, of base metal; beads and spangles of base metal 8311</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wire, rods, tubes, plates, electrodes and similar products, of base metal or of metal carbides, coated or cored with flux material, of a kind used for soldering, brazing, welding or deposition of metal or of metal carbides; wire and rods, of agglomerated base metal powder, used for metal spraying 8414</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Air or vacuum pumps, air or other gas compressors and fans; ventilating or recycling hoods incorporating a fan, whether or not fitted with filters; gas-tight biological safety cabinets, whether or not fitted with filters, excluding 8414 10 (vacuum pumps), 8418 10 81 (cryogenic pumps in the LNG-process) and 8414 90 (Parts) 8414 51</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Table, floor, wall, window, ceiling or roof fans, with a self-contained electric motor of an output not exceeding 125 W (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8414 59 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 98414 60 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hoods having a maximum horizontal side not exceeding 120 cm (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8418 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Refrigerators, freezers and other refrigerating or freezing equipment, electric or other; heat pumps other than air conditioning machines of heading 84.15 and excluding 8418 69 00 (Process units for gas cooling in the LNG-process) 8418 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Combined refrigerator-freezers, fitted with separate external doors (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8418 21 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Compression-type (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8418 29 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8418 30 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Freezers of the chest type, not exceeding 800 litres capacity (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8418 40 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Freezers of the upright type, not exceeding 900 litres capacity (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8422 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dish washing machines; machinery for cleaning or drying bottles or other containers; machinery for filling, closing, sealing or labelling bottles, cans, boxes, bags or other containers; machinery for capsuling bottles, jars, tubes and similar containers; other packing or wrapping machinery (including heat-shrink wrapping machinery); machinery for aerating beverages, 8422 11 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of the household type (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8438 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery, not specified or included elsewhere in this chapter, for the industrial preparation or manufacture of food or drink (other than machinery for the extraction or preparation of animal or fixed vegetable fats or oils); parts thereof 8443 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Offset printing machinery, reel-fed 8443 12 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Offset printing machinery, sheet fed, office type (using sheets with one side not exceeding 22 cm and the other side not exceeding 36 cm in the unfolded state) (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8443 14 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Letterpress printing machinery, reel fed, excluding flexographic printing 8443 31 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machines which only perform one of the functions of printing, copying or facsimile transmission, capable of connecting to an automatic data processing machine or to a network (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8443 32 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other, capable of connecting to an automatic data-processing machine or to a network (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8443 39 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8443 99 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other. 8508 11 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vacuum cleaners, incl. dry cleaners and wet vacuum cleaners, with self-contained electric motor, power not exceeding 1 500 W and having a dust bag or other receptacle capacity not exceeding 20 l (Electronic items for domestic use, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 750 per item) 8516 10 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric instantaneous or storage water heaters and immersion heaters 8516 40</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric smoothing irons 8516 79</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric instantaneous or storage water heaters and immersion heaters 108522</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts and accessories suitable for use solely or principally with sound reproducing and recording apparatus and with video equipment for recording and reproducing pictures and sound 8708</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts and accessories of the motor vehicles of headings 8701 to 8705 for the transport of persons on earth, air or sea, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 50 000 each, teleferics, chairlifts, ski-draglines, traction mechanisms for funiculars, motorbikes, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 5 000 each, as well as their accessories and spare parts, excluding CN 8708 99 (Parts and accessories of the motor vehicles of headings 8701 to 8705 (tractors, motor vehicles for the transport of ten or more persons, motor cars and other motor vehicles principally designed for the transport of persons, motor vehicles for the transport of goods and special purpose motor vehicles), n.e.s.)) 8907 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rafts, tanks, coffer-dams, landing stages, buoys, beacons and other floating structures (excl. vessels of heading 8901 to 8906 and floating structures for breaking up) 9001 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lenses, prisms, mirrors and other optical elements, of any material, unmounted (excl. such elements of glass not optically worked, contact lenses and spectacle lenses) 9002 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lenses, prisms, mirrors and other optical elements, mounted, of any material, being parts of or fittings for instruments or apparatus (excl. objective lenses for cameras, projectors or photographic enlargers or reducers, such elements of glass not optically worked, and filters) 9017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Drawing, marking-out or mathematical calculating instruments, e.g. drafting machines, pantographs, protractors, drawing sets, slide rules, disc calculators; instruments for measuring length, for use in the hand, e.g. measuring rods and tapes, micrometres, callipers and other gauges, not elsewhere specified in chapter 90 9020 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other breathing appliances and gas masks, excluding protective masks having neither mechanical parts nor replaceable filters (Articles and equipment for sports, including skiing, golf, diving and water sports, value <em type="italic">not </em>exceeding EUR 300 per item) 9025 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hydrometers and similar floating instruments, thermometers, pyrometers, barometers, hygrometers and psychrometers, recording or not, and any combination of these instruments, excluding CN 9025 90 (Parts and accessories for hydrometers, areometers and similar floating instruments, thermometers, pyrometers, barometers, hygrometers and psychrometers, n.e.s.) 9405</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Luminaires and lighting fittings, incl. searchlights and spotlights, and parts thereof, n.e.s; illuminated signs, illuminated nameplates and the like having a permanently fixed light source, and parts thereof, n.e.s. 9603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Brooms, brushes, incl. brushes constituting parts of machines, appliances or vehicles, handoperated mechanical floor sweepers, not motorised, mops and leather dusters; prepared knots and tufts for broom or brush making; paint pads and rollers; squeegees of rubber or similar flexible materials 9608 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Felt-tipped and other porous-tipped pens and markers 9608 40</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Propelling or sliding pencils ” 11</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 2 </em>“ <em type="bold">Skjal 5 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Listi við vørum og tøkni, sum nevnt í § 14 samsvarandi fylgiskjali XXI til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 833/2014 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">CN code </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Name of the good </em>0306 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Crustaceans, whether in shell or not, live, fresh, chilled, frozen, dried, salted or in brine; smoked crustaceans, whether in shell or not, whether or not cooked before or during the smoking process; crustaceans, in shell, cooked by steaming or by boiling in water, whether or not chilled, frozen, dried, salted or in brine 1604 31 00</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Caviar 1604 32 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Caviar substitutes 2208</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Undenatured ethyl alcohol of an alcoholic strength by volume of less than 80 % vol; spirits, liqueurs and other spirituous beverages 2303</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Residues of starch manufacture and similar residues, beet-pulp, bagasse and other waste of sugar manufacture, brewing or distilling dregs and waste, whether or not in the form of pellets 2402</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cigars, cheroots, cigarillos and cigarettes, of tobacco or of tobacco substitutes 2523</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Portland cement, aluminous cement, slag cement, supersulphate cement and similar hydraulic cements, whether or not coloured or in the form of clinkers 2701</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coal; briquettes, ovoids and similar solid fuels manufactured from coal 2702</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lignite, whether or not agglomerated, excluding jet 2703</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Peat, including peat litter, whether or not agglomerated 2704</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coke and semi-coke of coal, of lignite or of peat, whether or not agglomerated; retort carbon 2705</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coal gas, water gas, producer gas and similar gases, other than petroleum gases and other gaseous hydrocarbons 2706</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tar distilled from coal, from lignite or from peat, and other mineral tars, whether or not dehydrated or partially distilled, including reconstituted tars 2707</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oils and other products of the distillation of high temperature coal tar; similar products in which the weight of the aromatic constituents exceeds that of the non-aromatic constituents 2708</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pitch and pitch coke, obtained from coal tar or from other mineral tars 2711 12</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Propane, liquefied 2711 13</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Butanes, liquefied 2711 14</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ethylene, propylene, butylene and butadiene, liquefied 2711 19</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Gaseous hydrocarbons, liquified, n.e.s. 2712</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Petroleum jelly, paraffin wax, micro- crystalline petroleum wax, slack wax, ozokerite, lignite wax, peat wax, other mineral waxes, and similar products obtained by synthesis or by other processes, whether or not coloured 2713</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Petroleum coke, petroleum bitumen and other residues of petroleum oil or of oil obtained from bituminous minerals 122714</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bitumen and asphalt, natural; bituminous or oil-shale and tar sands; asphaltites and asphaltic rocks 2715</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bituminous mastics, cut-backs and other bituminous mixtures based on natural asphalt, on natural bitumen, on petroleum bitumen, on mineral tar or on mineral tar pitch 2803</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carbon (carbon blacks and other forms of carbon not elsewhere specified or included) 2804 29 10</p>
<p>Helium 2845 40</p>
<p>Helium-3 2811</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Inorganic acids and inorganic oxygen compounds of non-metals (excl. hydrogen chloride (hydrochloric acid), chlorosulphuric acid, sulphuric acid, oleum, nitric acid, sulphonitric acids, diphosphorus pentaoxide, phosphoric acid, polyphosphoric acids, oxides of boron and boric acids) 2818</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artificial corundum, whether or not chemically defined; aluminium oxide; aluminium hydroxide ex 28 25</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hydrazine and hydroxylamine and their inorganic salts; other inorganic bases; other metal oxides, hydroxides and peroxides, except for CN codes 28252000 and 28253000 2834</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nitrites; nitrates ex 28 35</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Phosphinates (hypophosphites), phosphonates (phosphites) and phosphates; polyphosphates, whether or not chemically defined, except for CN code 28352600 2836</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carbonates; peroxocarbonates (percarbonates); commercial ammonium carbonate containing ammonium carbamate ex 29 01</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Acyclic hydrocarbons, except for CN code 29011000 2902</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cyclic hydrocarbons 2903</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Halogenated derivatives of hydrocarbons 2905</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Acyclic alcohols and their halogenated, sulphonated, nitrated or nitrosated derivatives 2907</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Phenols; phenol-alcohols 2909</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ethers, ether-alcohols, ether-phenols, ether-alcohol-phenols, alcohol peroxides, ether peroxides, acetal and hemiacetal peroxides, ketone peroxides (whether or not chemically defined), and their halogenated, sulphonated, nitrated or nitrosated derivatives 2914</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ketones and quinones, whether or not with other oxygen function, and their halogenated, sulphonated, nitrated or nitrosated derivatives 2915</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Saturated acyclic monocarboxylic acids and their anhydrides, halides, peroxides and peroxyacids; their halogenated, sulphonated, nitrated or nitrosated derivatives 2917</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polycarboxylic acids, their anhydrides, halides, peroxides and peroxyacids; their halogenated, sulphonated, nitrated or nitrosated derivatives 2922</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oxygen-function amino-compounds 2923</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Quaternary ammonium salts and hydroxides; lecithins and other phosphoaminolipids, whether or not chemically defined 2931</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Separate chemically defined organo-inorganic compounds (excl. organo-sulphur compounds and those of mercury) 2933</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Heterocyclic compounds with nitrogen hetero-atom[s] only 133104 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Potassium chloride 3105 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mineral or chemical fertilisers containing the three fertilising elements nitrogen, phosphorus and potassium 3105 60</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mineral or chemical fertilisers containing the two fertilising elements phosphorus and potassium ex 3105 90 20 Other fertilising containing photassium chloride ex 3105 90 80 Other fertilising containing photassium chloride 3301</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Essential oils, whether or not terpeneless, incl. concretes and absolutes; resinoids; extracted oleoresins; concentrates of essential oils in fats, fixed oils, waxes or the like, obtained by enfleurage or maceration; terpenic by-products of the deterpenation of essential oils; aqueous distillates and aqueous solutions of essential oils 3304</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Beauty or make-up preparations and preparations for the care of the skin, incl. sunscreen or suntan preparations (excl. medicaments); manicure or pedicure preparations 3305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations for use on the hair 3306</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations for oral or dental hygiene, incl. denture fixative pastes and powders; yarn used to clean between the teeth (dental floss), in individual retail packages 3307</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Shaving preparations, incl. pre-shave and aftershave products, personal deodorants, bath and shower preparations, depilatories and other perfumery, toilet or cosmetic preparations, n.e.s.; prepared room deodorisers, whether or not perfumed or having disinfectant properties 3401</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for use as soap, in the form of bars, cakes, moulded pieces or shapes, whether or not containing soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for washing the skin, in the form of liquid or cream and put up for retail sale, whether or not containing soap; paper, wadding, felt and nonwovens, impregnated, coated or covered with soap or detergent 3402</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Organic surface-active agents (excl. soap); surface-active preparations, washing preparations, incl. auxiliary washing preparations, and cleaning preparations, whether or not containing soap (excl. those of heading 3401) 3404</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artificial waxes and prepared waxes 3801</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artificial graphite; colloidal or semi-colloidal graphite; preparations based on graphite or other carbon in the form of pastes, blocks, plates or other semi-manufactures 3811</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Anti-knock preparations, oxidation inhibitors, gum inhibitors, viscosity improvers, anticorrosive preparations and other prepared additives, for mineral oils, incl. gasoline, or for other liquids used for the same purposes as mineral oils 3812</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Prepared rubber accelerators; compound plasticisers for rubber or plastics, not elsewhere specified or included; anti-oxidising preparations and other compound stabilisers for rubber or plastics 3817</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mixed alkylbenzenes and mixed alkylnaphthalenes produced by the alkylation of benzene and naphthalene (excl. mixed isomers of cyclic hydrocarbons) 3819</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hydraulic brake fluids and other prepared liquids for hydraulic transmission not containing petroleum oil or bituminous mineral oil, or containing &lt; 70 % petroleum oil or bituminous mineral oil by weight 3823</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industrial monocarboxylic fatty acids; acid oils from refining; industrial fatty alcohols 143824</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Prepared binders for foundry moulds or cores; chemical products and preparations for the chemical or allied industries, incl. mixtures of natural products, n.e.s. 3901</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of ethylene, in primary forms 3902</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of propylene or of other olefins, in primary forms 3903</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of styrene, in primary forms 3904</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of vinyl chloride or of other halogenated olefins, in primary forms 3907</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polyacetals, other polyethers and epoxide resins, in primary forms; polycarbonates, alkyd resins, polyallyl esters and other polyesters, in primary forms 3908</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polyamides, in primary forms 3916</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Monofilament of which any cross-sectional dimension &gt; 1 mm, rods, sticks and profile shapes, of plastics, whether or not surface-worked but not further worked 3917</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tubes, pipes and hoses, and fittings therefor, e.g. joints, elbows, flanges, of plastics 3919</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Self-adhesive plates, sheets, film, foil, tape, strip and other flat shapes, of plastics, whether or not in rolls (excl. floor, wall and ceiling coverings of heading 3918) 3920</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Plates, sheets, film, foil and strip, of non-cellular plastics, not reinforced, laminated, supported or similarly combined with other materials, without backing, unworked or merely surfaceworked or merely cut into squares or rectangles (excl. self-adhesive products, and floor, wall and ceiling coverings of heading 3918) 3921</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Plates, sheets, film, foil and strip, of plastics, reinforced, laminated, supported or similarly combined with other materials, or of cellular plastic, unworked or merely surface-worked or merely cut into squares or rectangles (excl. self-adhesive products, floor, wall and ceiling coverings of heading 3918) 3923</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles for the conveyance or packaging of goods, of plastics; stoppers, lids, caps and other closures, of plastics 3925</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Builders’ ware of plastics, n.e.s. 3926</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of plastics and articles of other materials of heading 3901 to 3914, n.e.s. 4002</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Synthetic rubber and factice derived from oils, in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip; mixtures of natural rubber, balata, gutta-percha, guayule, chicle or similar types of natural rubber with synthetic rubber or factice, in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip 4011</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">New pneumatic tyres, of rubber 4107</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Leather further prepared after tanning or crusting (incl. parchment-dressed leather), of bovine (incl. buffalo) or equine animals, without hair on, whether or not split (excl. chamois leather, patent leather and patent laminated leather, and metallised leather) 4202</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Trunks, suitcases, vanity cases, executive-cases, briefcases, school satchels, spectacle cases, binocular cases, camera cases, musical instrument cases, gun cases, holsters and similar containers; travelling-bags, insulated food or beverage bags, toilet bags, rucksacks, handbags, shopping-bags, wallets, purses, map-cases, cigarette-cases, tobacco-pouches, tool bags, sports bags, bottle-cases, jewellery boxes, powder-boxes, cutlery cases and similar containers, of leather or of composition leather, of sheeting of plastics, of textile materials, of vulcanised fibre or of paperboard, or wholly or mainly covered with such materials or with paper 4301</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Raw furskins, incl. heads, tails, paws and other pieces or cuttings suitable for use in furriery (excl. raw hides and skins of heading 4101, 4102 or 4103) 1544</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wood and articles of wood; wood charcoal 4703</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Chemical wood pulp, soda or sulphate (excl. dissolving grades) 4705</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wood pulp obtained by a combination of mechanical and chemical pulping processes 4801</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Newsprint as specified in note 4 to Chapter 48, in rolls of a width &gt; 28 cm or in square or rectangular sheets with one side &gt; 28 cm and the other side &gt; 15 cm in the unfolded state 4802</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Uncoated paper and paperboard, of a kind used for writing, printing or other graphic purposes, and non-perforated punchcards and punch-tape paper, in rolls or in square or rectangular sheets, of any size, and handmade paper and paperboard (excl. newsprint of heading 4801 and paper of heading 4803) 4803</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Toilet or facial tissue stock, towel or napkin stock and similar paper for household or sanitary purposes, cellulose wadding and webs of cellulose fibres, whether or not creped, crinkled, embossed, perforated, surface-coloured, surface-decorated or printed, in rolls of a width &gt; 36 cm or in square or rectangular sheets with one side &gt; 36 cm and the other side &gt; 15 cm in the unfolded state 4804</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Uncoated kraft paper and paperboard, in rolls of a width &gt; 36 cm or in square or rectangular sheets with one side &gt; 36 cm and the other side &gt; 15 cm in the unfolded state (excl. goods of heading 4802 or 4803) 4805</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other paper and paperboard, uncoated, in rolls of a width &gt; 36 cm or in square or rectangular sheets with one side &gt; 36 cm and the other side &gt; 15 cm in the unfolded state, not worked other than as specified in note 3 to this chapter, n.e.s. 4810</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Paper and paperboard, coated on one or both sides with kaolin (China clay) or other inorganic substances, with or without a binder, and with no other coating, whether or not surfacecoloured, surface-decorated or printed, in rolls or in square or rectangular sheets, of any size (excl. all other coated papers and paperboards) 4811</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding and webs of cellulose fibres, coated, impregnated, covered, surface-coloured, surface-decorated or printed, in rolls or in square or rectangular sheets, of any size (excl. goods of heading 4803, 4809 and 4810) 4818</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Toilet paper and similar paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres, of a kind used for household or sanitary purposes, in rolls of a width &lt;= 36 cm, or cut to size or shape; handkerchiefs, cleansing tissues, towels, tablecloths, serviettes, bedsheets and similar household, sanitary or hospital articles, articles of apparel and clothing accessories, of paper pulp, paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres 4819</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cartons, boxes, cases, bags and other packing containers, of paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres, n.e.s.; box files, letter trays, and similar articles, of paperboard of a kind used in offices, shops or the like 4823</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding and webs of cellulose fibres, in strips or rolls of a width &lt;= 36 cm, in rectangular or square sheets of which no side &gt; 36 cm in the unfolded state, or cut to shape other than rectangular or square, and articles of paper pulp, paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding or webs or cellulose fibres, n.e.s. 5402</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Synthetic filament yarn, incl. synthetic monofilaments of &lt; 67 decitex (excl. sewing thread and yarn put up for retail sale) 5601</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wadding of textile materials and articles thereof; textile fibres with a length of &lt;= 5 mm ‘flock’, textile dust and mill neps (excl. wadding and articles thereof impregnated or coated with pharmaceutical substances or put up for retail sale for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes, and products impregnated, coated or covered with perfumes, cosmetics, soaps etc.) 5603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nonwovens, whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or laminated, n.e.s. 166204</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Women’s or girls’ suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, dresses, skirts, divided skirts, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (excl. knitted or crocheted, wind-jackets and similar articles, slips, petticoats and panties, tracksuits, ski suits and swimwear) 6305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sacks and bags, of a kind used for the packing of goods, of all types of textile materials 6403</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Footwear with outer soles of rubber, plastics, leather or composition leather and uppers of leather (excl. orthopaedic footwear, skating boots with ice or roller skates attached, and toy footwear) 6806</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Slag-wool, rock-wool and similar mineral wools; exfoliated vermiculite, expanded clays, foamed slag and similar expanded mineral materials; mixtures and articles of heat-insulating, sound-insulating or sound absorbing mineral materials (excl. articles of light concrete, asbestos, asbestos-cement, cellulose fibre-cement or the like, mixtures and other articles of or based on asbestos, and ceramic products) 6807</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of asphalt or of similar materials, e.g. petroleum bitumen or coal tar pitch 6808</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Panels, boards, tiles, blocks and similar articles of vegetable fibre, of straw or of shavings, chips, particles, sawdust or other waste of wood, agglomerated with cement, plaster or other mineral binders (excl. articles of asbestos-cement, cellulose fibre-cement or the like) 6810</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of cement, of concrete or of artificial stone, whether or not reinforced 6814</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Worked mica and articles of mica, incl. agglomerated or reconstituted mica, whether or not on a support of paper, paperboard or other materials (excl. electrical insulators, insulating fittings, resistors and capacitors, protective goggles of mica and their glasses, and mica in the form of christmas tree decorations) 6815</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of stone or of other mineral substances, incl. carbon fibres, articles of carbon fibres and articles of peat, n.e.s. 6902</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Refractory bricks, blocks, tiles and similar refractory ceramic constructional goods (excl. those of siliceous fossil meals or similar siliceous earths) 6907</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ceramic flags and paving, hearth or wall tiles; ceramic mosaic cubes and the like, whether or not on a backing (excl. of siliceous fossil meals or similar siliceous earths, refractory goods, tiles specially adapted as table mats, ornamental articles and tiles specifically manufactured for stoves) 7005</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Float glass and surface ground or polished glass, in sheets, whether or not having an absorbent, reflecting or non-reflecting layer, but not otherwise worked 7007</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Safety glass, consisting of toughened (tempered) or laminated glass 7010</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carboys, bottles, flasks, jars, pots, phials, ampoules and other containers, of glass, of a kind used for the conveyance or packing of goods; preserving jars of glass; stoppers, lids and other closures, of glass 7019</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Glass fibres (including glass wool) and articles thereof (for example, yarn, rovings, woven fabrics) 7104</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Precious and semi-precious stones, synthetic or reconstructed, whether or not worked or graded but not strung, mounted or set; ungraded synthetic or reconstructed precious or semi-precious stones, temporarily strung for convenience of transport 7106</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Silver (including silver plated with gold or platinum), unwrought or in semi-manufactured forms, or in powder form 7112</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Waste and scrap of precious metal or of metal clad with precious metal; other waste and scrap containing precious metal or precious-metal compounds, of a kind used principally for the 17recovery of precious metal (excl. waste and scrap melted down into unworked blocks, ingots, or similar forms) 7115</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of precious metal or of metal clad with precious metal, n.e.s. 7201</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pig iron and spiegeleisen, in pigs, blocks or other primary forms 7202</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Ferro-alloys 7203</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ferrous products obtained by direct reduction of iron ore and other spongy ferrous products, in lumps, pellets or similar forms; iron having a minimum purity by weight of 99,94 %, in lumps, pellets or similar forms 7205</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Granules and powders of pig iron, spiegeleisen, iron or steel 7408</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Copper wire 7601</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Unwrought aluminium’. 7604</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aluminium bars, rods and profiles 7605</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Aluminium wire 7606</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aluminium plates, sheets and strip, of a thickness exceeding 0,2 mm 7607</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aluminium foil (whether or not printed or backed with paper, paperboard, plastics or similar backing materials), of a thickness (excluding any backing) not exceeding 0,2 mm 7608</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aluminium tubes and pipes 7801</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Unwrought lead 8207</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tools, interchangeable, for hand tools, whether or not power-operated, or for machine tools (e.g. for pressing, stamping, punching, tapping, threading, drilling, boring, broaching, milling, turning or screw driving), incl. dies for drawing or extruding metal, and rock-drilling or earthboring tools 8212</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Non-electric razors and razor blades of base metal, incl. razor blade blanks in strips 8302</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Base metal mountings, fittings and similar articles suitable for furniture, doors, staircases, windows, blinds, coachwork, saddlery, trunks, chests, caskets or the like; base metal hat-racks, hat-pegs, brackets and similar fixtures; castors with mountings of base metal; automatic door closers of base metal 8309</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stoppers, caps and lids, incl. crown corks, screw caps and pouring stoppers, capsules for bottles, threaded bungs, bung covers, seals and other packing accessories, of base metal 8407</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Spark-ignition reciprocating or rotary internal combustion piston engine 8408</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Compression-ignition internal combustion piston engine (diesel or semi-diesel engine) 8409</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts suitable for use solely or principally with internal combustion piston engine of heading 8407 or 8408</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Ex 84 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Turbojets, turbopropellers and other gas turbines with the exception of parts of turbojets or turbopropellers of CN code 8411 91 00 8412</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Engines and motors (excl. steam turbines, internal combustion piston engine, hydraulic turbines, water wheels, gas turbines and electric motors); parts thereof 8413</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pumps for liquids, whether or not fitted with a measuring device (excl. ceramic pumps and secretion aspirating pumps for medical use and medical pumps carried on or implanted in the body); liquid elevators (excl. pumps); parts thereof 188414</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Air or vacuum pumps (excl. gas compound elevators and pneumatic elevators and conveyors); air or other gas compressors and fans; ventilating or recycling hoods incorporating a fan, whether or not fitted with filters; parts thereof 8418</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Refrigerators, freezers and other refrigerating or freezing equipment, electric or other; heat pumps; parts thereof (excl. air conditioning machines of heading 8415) 8419</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery, plant or laboratory equipment whether or not electrically heated (excl. furnaces, ovens and other equipment of heading 8514 ), for the treatment of materials by a process involving a change of temperature such as heating, cooking, roasting, distilling, rectifying, sterilising, pasteurising, steaming, drying, evaporating, vaporising, condensing or cooling (excl. those used for domestic purposes); instantaneous or storage water heaters, non-electric; parts thereof 8421</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Centrifuges, incl. centrifugal dryers (excl. those for isotope separation); filtering or purifying machinery and apparatus, for liquids or gases; parts thereof (excl. artificial kidneys) 8422</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dishwashing machines; machinery for cleaning or drying bottles or other containers; machinery for filling, closing, sealing or labelling bottles, cans, boxes, bags or other containers; machinery for capsuling bottles, jars, tubes and similar containers; other packing or wrapping machinery, incl. heat-shrink wrapping machinery; machinery for aerating beverages; parts thereof 8424</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mechanical appliances, whether or not hand-operated, for projecting, dispersing or spraying liquids or powders, n.e.s.; fire extinguishers, charged or not (excl. fire-extinguishing bombs and grenades); spray guns and similar appliances (excl. electric machines and apparatus for hot spraying of metals or sintered metal carbides of heading 8515); steam or sand blasting machines and similar jet projecting machines; parts thereof, n.e.s. 8426</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ships’ derricks; cranes, incl. cable cranes (excl. wheel-mounted cranes and vehicle cranes for railways); mobile lifting frames, straddle carriers and works trucks fitted with a crane 8431</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts suitable for use solely or principally with the machinery of headings 8425 to 8430 8450</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Household or laundry-type washing machines, incl. machines which both wash and dry; parts thereof 8455</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Metal-rolling mills and rolls therefor; parts of metal-rolling mills 8466</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts and accessories suitable for use solely or principally with the machines of headings 8456 to 8465, incl. work or tool holders, self-opening dieheads, dividing heads and other special attachments for the machines, n.e.s.; tool holders for any type of tool for working in the hand 8467</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tools for working in the hand, pneumatic, hydraulic or with self-contained electric or nonelectric motor; parts thereof 8471</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Automatic data-processing machines and units thereof; magnetic or optical readers, machines for transcribing data onto data media in coded form and machines for processing such data, n.e.s. 8474</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery for sorting, screening, separating, washing, crushing, grinding, mixing or kneading earth, stone, ores or other mineral substances, in solid, incl. powder or paste, form; machinery for agglomerating, shaping or moulding solid mineral fuels, ceramic paste, unhardened cements, plastering materials or other mineral products in powder or paste form; machines for forming foundry moulds of sand; parts thereof 8477</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery for working rubber or plastics or for the manufacture of products from these materials, not specified or included elsewhere in this chapter, parts thereof 8479</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machines and mechanical appliances having individual functions, not specified or included elsewhere in this chapter; parts thereof 198480</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moulding boxes for metal foundry; mould bases; moulding patterns; moulds for metal (other than ingot moulds), metal carbides, glass, mineral materials, rubber or plastics (excl. moulds of graphite or other carbons, ceramic or glass moulds and linotype moulds or matrices) 8481</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Taps, cocks, valves and similar appliances for pipes, boiler shells, tanks, vats or the like, incl. pressure-reducing valves and thermostatically controlled valves; parts thereof 8482</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ball or roller bearings (excl. steel balls of heading 7326); parts thereof 8483</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Transmission shafts, incl. camshafts and crankshafts, and cranks; bearing housings and plain shaft bearings for machines; gears and gearing; ball or roller screws, gear boxes and other speed changers, incl. torque converters; flywheels and pulleys, incl. pulley blocks, clutches and shaft couplings, incl. universal joints; parts thereof 8487</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery parts, n.e.s. in Chapter 84 (excl. parts containing electrical connectors, insulators, coils, contacts or other electrical features) 8501</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric motors and generators (excl. generating sets) 8502</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric generating sets and rotary converters 8503</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts suitable for use solely or principally with electric motors and generators, electric generating sets and rotary converters, n.e.s. 8504</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electrical transformers, static converters, e.g. rectifiers, and inductors; parts thereof 8511</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electrical ignition or starting equipment of a kind used for spark-ignition or compressionignition internal combustion engines, e.g. ignition magnetos, magneto-dynamos, ignition coils, sparking plugs, glow plugs and starter motors; generators, e.g. dynamos and alternators, and cut-outs of a kind used in conjunction with such engines; parts thereof 8516</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric instantaneous or storage water heaters and immersion heaters; electric space-heating apparatus and soil-heating apparatus; electro-thermic hairdressing apparatus, e.g. hairdryers, hair curlers and curling tong heaters, and hand dryers; electric smoothing irons; other electrothermic appliances of a kind used for domestic purposes; electric heating resistors (other than those of heading 8545 ); parts thereof 8517</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Telephone sets, incl. telephones for cellular networks or for other wireless networks; other apparatus for the transmission or reception of voice, images or other data, incl. apparatus for communication in a wired or wireless network [such as a local or wide area network]; parts thereof (excl. than transmission or reception apparatus of heading 8443, 8525, 8527 or 8528) 8523</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Discs, tapes, solid-state non-volatile storage devices, ‘smart cards’ and other media for the recording of sound or of other phenomena, whether or not recorded, incl. matrices and masters for the production of discs (excl. products of Chapter 37) 8525</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Transmission apparatus for radio-broadcasting or television, whether or not incorporating reception apparatus or sound recording or reproducing apparatus; television cameras, digital cameras and video camera recorders 8526</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Radar apparatus, radio navigational aid apparatus and radio remote control apparatus 8531</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric sound or visual signalling apparatus, e.g. bells, sirens, indicator panels, burglar or fire alarms (excl. those for cycles, motor vehicles and traffic signalling); parts thereof 8535</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electrical apparatus for switching or protecting electrical circuits, or for making connections to or in electrical circuits, e.g., switches, fuses, lightning arresters, voltage limiters, surge suppressors, plugs and other connectors, junction boxes, for a voltage &gt; 1 000 V (excl. control desks, cabinets, panels etc. of heading 8537) 8536</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electrical apparatus for switching or protecting electrical circuits, or for making connections to or in electrical circuits, e.g., switches, relays, fuses, surge suppressors, plugs, sockets, lamp 20holders and junction boxes, for a voltage &lt;= 1 000 V (excl. control desks, cabinets, panels etc. of heading 8537) 8537</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Boards, panels, consoles, desks, cabinets and other bases, equipped with two or more apparatus of heading 8535 or 8536, for electric control or the distribution of electricity, incl. those incorporating instruments or apparatus of Chapter 90, and numerical control apparatus (excl. switching apparatus for line telephony or line telegraphy) 8538</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts suitable for use solely or principally with the apparatus of heading 8535, 8536 or 8537, n.e.s. 8539</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric filament or discharge lamps, incl. sealed beam lamp units and ultraviolet or infra-red lamps; arc lamps; light-emitting diode (LED) lamps; parts thereof 8541</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Diodes, transistors and similar semiconductor devices; photosensitive semiconductor devices, incl. photovoltaic cells whether or not assembled in modules or made up into panels (excl. photovoltaic generators); light emitting diodes (LED); mounted piezoelectric crystals; parts thereof 8542</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electronic integrated circuits; parts thereof 8543</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electrical machines and apparatus, having individual functions, n.e.s. in Chapter 85 and parts thereof 8544</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Insulated (incl. enamelled or anodised) wire, cable (incl. coaxial cable) and other insulated electric conductors, whether or not fitted with connectors; optical fibre cables, made up of individually sheathed fibres, whether or not assembled with electric conductors or fitted with connectors 8545</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carbon electrodes, carbon brushes, lamp carbons, battery carbons and other articles of graphite or other carbon, with or without metal, of a kind used for electrical purposes 8603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Self-propelled railway or tramway coaches, vans and trucks (excl. those of heading 8604) 8606</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Railway or tramway goods vans and wagons (excl. self-propelled and luggage vans and post office coaches) 8701</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tractors (other than tractors of heading 8709) 8703</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Motor cars and other motor vehicles principally designed for the transport of &lt; 10 persons, incl. station wagons and racing cars (excl. motor vehicles of heading 8702) 8704</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Motor vehicles for the transport of goods, incl. chassis with engine and cab 8716</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Trailers and semi-trailers; other vehicles, not mechanically propelled (excl. railway and tramway vehicles); parts thereof, n.e.s. 8802</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Powered aircraft (e.g. helicopters and aeroplanes); spacecraft, incl. satellites, and suborbital and spacecraft launch vehicles 8901</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cruise ships, excursion boats, ferry-boats, cargo ships, barges and similar vessels for the transport of persons or goods 8903</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yachts and other vessels for pleasure or sports; rowing boats and canoes 8904</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tugs and pusher craft 8905</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Light-vessels, fire-floats, dredgers, floating cranes, and other vessels the navigability of which is subsidiary to their main function; floating docks; floating or submersible drilling or production platforms 9001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Optical fibres and optical fibre bundles; optical fibre cables (excl. made up of individually sheathed fibres of heading 8544); sheets and plates of polarising material; lenses, incl. contact 21lenses, prisms, mirrors and other optical elements of any material, unmounted (excl. such elements of glass not optically worked) 9006</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Photographic cameras, photographic flashlight apparatus and flashbulbs (excl. discharge lamps of heading 8539) 9013</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Liquid crystal devices not constituting articles provided for more specifically in other heading; lasers (excl. laser diodes); other optical appliances and instruments not elsewhere specified in Chapter 90 9014</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Direction finding compasses; other navigational instruments and appliances (excl. radio navigational equipment) 9026</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Instruments and apparatus for measuring or checking the flow, level, pressure or other variables of liquids or gases, e.g. flow meters, level gauges, manometers, heat meters (excl. instruments and apparatus of heading 9014, 9015, 9028 or 9032) 9027</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Instruments and apparatus for physical or chemical analysis, e.g. polarimeters, refractometers, spectrometers, gas or smoke analysis apparatus; instruments and apparatus for measuring or checking viscosity, porosity, expansion, surface tension or the like; instruments and apparatus for measuring or checking quantities of heat, sound or light, incl. exposure meters; microtomes 9030</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oscilloscopes, spectrum analysers and other instruments and apparatus for measuring or checking electrical quantities (excl. meters of heading 9028); instruments and apparatus for measuring or detecting alpha, beta, gamma, x-ray, cosmic or other ionising radiations 9031</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Measuring or checking instruments, appliances and machines not elsewhere specified in Chapter 90; profile projectors 9032</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Regulating or controlling instruments and apparatus (excl. taps, cocks and valves of heading 8481) 9401</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Seats, whether or not convertible into beds, and parts thereof, n.e.s. (excl. medical, surgical, dental or veterinary of heading 9402) 9403</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other furniture and parts thereof 9404</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mattress supports (excl. spring interiors for seats); articles of bedding and similar furnishing, e.g. mattresses, quilts, eiderdowns, cushions, pouffes and pillows, fitted with springs or stuffed or internally filled with any material or of cellular rubber or plastics, whether or not covered (excl. pneumatic or water mattresses and pillows, blankets and covers) 9405</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lamps and lighting fittings, incl. searchlights and spotlights, and parts thereof, n.e.s.; illuminated signs, illuminated nameplates and the like having a permanently fixed light source, and parts thereof, n.e.s. 9406</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Prefabricated buildings, whether or not complete or already assembled ” 22</p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Skjal 3 </em>“ <em type="bold">Skjal 6 A </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Listi við skipum, sum eru fevnd av § 15a, samsvarandi fylgiskjali XLII til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 833/2014 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Vessel name </em></p>
<p xml:lang="deu"><em type="bold">IMO number </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Grounds for inclusion </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Date of application </em>1. </p>
<p xml:lang="est">Angara 9179842</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (a): transport goods and technology used in the defence and security sector, from or to Russia, for use in Russia or for Russia’s warfare in Ukraine. 25.6.2024 2.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Maria 8517839</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (a): transport goods and technology used in the defence and security sector, from or to Russia, for use in Russia or for Russia’s warfare in Ukraine. 25.6.2024 3.</p>
<p xml:lang="sms">Saam FSU 9915090</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 4.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Koryak FSU 9915105</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 5.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Jun Ma (formerly Kavya, Hana) 9353113</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 6.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">N Cerna (formerly Canis Power) 9289520</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 7.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Apar (formerly Feng Shou; Andromeda Star) 9402471</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 238.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Legacy (formerly NS Lotus) 9339337</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 9.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Saga (formerly NS Spirit) 9318553</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 10.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Serenade (formerly NS Stream) 9318541</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 11.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Success (formerly SCF Arum) 9333436</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 12.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Lady R 9161003</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (a): transport goods and technology used in the defence and security sector, from or to Russia, for use in Russia or for Russia’s warfare in Ukraine. 25.6.2024 13.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Maia-1 9358010</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (a): transport goods and technology used in the defence and security sector, from or to Russia, for use in Russia or for Russia’s warfare in Ukraine. 25.6.2024 14.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Audax 9763837</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 15.</p>
<p xml:lang="som">Pugnax 9763849</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.6.2024 16.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hunter Star 9830769</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of 25.6.2024 24the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Daksha (formerly Hebe) 9259185</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 18.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Enisey 9079169</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (d): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies which undermine or threaten the economic subsistence or food security of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian grain, or the preservation of cultural heritage of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian cultural goods. 25.6.2024 19.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Kelly Grace (formerly Vela Rain) 9331141</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 20.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ozanno (formerly Ocean AMZ) 9394935</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 21.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Delvina (formerly Galian 2) 9331153</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 22.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bodhi (formerly Robon) 9144782</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 2523.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Lunar Tide (formerly Beks Aqua) 9277735</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 24.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kemerovo 9312884</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.6.2024 25.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Krymsk 9270529</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.6.2024 26.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Krasnoyarsk 9312896</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.6.2024 27.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kaliningrad 9341067</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.6.2024 28.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dashan (formerly Mianzimu) 9299666</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 29.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Pioneer 9256602</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 30.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Alissa 9273052</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 17.12.2024 26transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 31.</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Marabella Sun 9323376</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 32.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Christophe de Margerie 9737187</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 33.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Altair 9413547</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 34.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Peta Lumina 9296391</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 35.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">San Damian 9274331</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (d): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies which undermine or threaten the economic subsistence or food security of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian grain, or the preservation of cultural heritage of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian cultural goods. 17.12.2024 36.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">San Cosmas 9274343</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (d): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies which undermine or threaten the economic subsistence or food security of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian grain, or the preservation of cultural 17.12.2024 27heritage of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian cultural goods. 37.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">San Severus 9385233</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (d): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies which undermine or threaten the economic subsistence or food security of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian grain, or the preservation of cultural heritage of Ukraine, such as the transport of stolen Ukrainian cultural goods. 17.12.2024 38.</p>
<p xml:lang="som">Galaxy 9826902</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 39.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Rigel 9511533</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 40.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cassiopeia 9341081</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 41.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Constellation 9306794</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 42.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Andromeda 9292204</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 43.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Callisto 9299692</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 17.12.2024 28transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 44.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alliance 9413561</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 45.</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Phoenix 9333424</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 46.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Leo 9412347</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 47.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Zenith 9610781</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 48.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Turbo Voyager 9299898</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 17.12.2024 29transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 49.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Sirius 9422445</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 50.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Saturn 9421972</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 51.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Life 9265756</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 52.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Krishna 1 9271585</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while 17.12.2024 30practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 53.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Vladimir Vinogradov 9842188</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 54.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Meridian (formerly Moskovsky Prospect) 9511521</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 55.</p>
<p xml:lang="ita">Bolero 9412335</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 56.</p>
<p xml:lang="som">Vega 9316127</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 57.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ocean Embrace (formely Tyagaraja) 9327372</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 58.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Yi Meng Shan (formerly Attica) 9436941</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping 17.12.2024 31practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 59.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">La Perouse 9849887</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 60.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Echo (formerly Elbrus) 9276030</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 61.</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Georgy Maslov 9610793</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 62.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Premier 9577082</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 63.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Pathfinder 9577094</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 64.</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Sierra 9522324</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 65.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Trust 9382798</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 3266.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Jaguar (formely Zaliv Amerika) 9354301</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 67.</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">Zaliv Amurskiy 9354313</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 17.12.2024 68.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Amber 6 9235713</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 69.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Areia (formerly Emily S) 9321847</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 70.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Fjord Seal 9513139</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 71.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Heidi A 9321976</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 72.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Line 9291250</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 3373.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Okeansky Prospect 9866380</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 74.</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Capella 9341079</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 75.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Siri 9281683</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 17.12.2024 76.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">North Way 9953535</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 77.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">North Sky 9953523</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 78.</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">North Air 9953509</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 79.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">North Mountain 9953511</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 17.12.2024 80.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Yuri Senkevich 9301419</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, 25.2.2025 34are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons 81.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Belgorod 9412359</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons 25.2.2025 82.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Bratsk 9411020</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons 25.2.2025 83.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Nikolay Zadornov 9901037</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons 25.2.2025 84.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Victor Konetsky 9301421</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 85.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Viktor Titov 9301407</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 3586.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Pavel Chernysh 9301380</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 87.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Captain Kostichev 9301392</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 88.</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Mermar 9231212</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 89.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Surrey Quays 9350654</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the 25.2.2025 36exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 90.</p>
<p xml:lang="yid">Nichole 9332822</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 91.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Crius 9251274</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 92.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Great Jacombo 9319703</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 93.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Chen Lu 9404948</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 37</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 94.</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Bull 9292503</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 95.</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Huihai Pacific 9346732</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 96.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Kudos Stars 9288710</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 97.</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Udaya 9288746</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 98.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Merope 9281891</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 99.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">PRS Ocean 9276561</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International 25.2.2025 38</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 100.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Stratos Aurora 9288708</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 101.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mercury 9321706</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 102.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Neer 1 (formerly Kapal Cantik) 9224283</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 103.</p>
<p xml:lang="som">Kiwala 9332810</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 104.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Andaman Skies 9288693</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 105.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Voyager 9843560</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 106.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Kareliya 9306782</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): 25.2.2025 39are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 107.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Kazan 9258002</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 108.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kotlas 9299719</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 109.</p>
<p xml:lang="pol">Ligovsky Prospect 9256066</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 110.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">NS Leader 9339301</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 111.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Prosperity (formerly NS Pride) 9322956</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 112.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Sapphire (formerly NS Silver) 9309576</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 113.</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Pacific 9329667</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on 25.2.2025 40behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 114.</p>
<p xml:lang="tur">Primorye 9421960</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 115.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Shturman Albanov 9752084</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 116.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Symphony 9309588</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 117.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Asher 9258868</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 118.</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Carl 9288851</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 119.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Deliver 9194983</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 25.2.2025 41transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 120.</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Facca 9271951</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 121.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Lang Ya 9332781</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 122.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Minerva M 9282479</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of 25.2.2025 42the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 123.</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Moti 9281011</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 124.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ocean Faye 9321689</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 125.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Serena (formerly Pontus I) 9255660</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 126.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sea Fidelity 9285835</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 43</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 127.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Swiftsea Rider 9318539</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 128.</p>
<p xml:lang="ita">Aquatica 9299769</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 129.</p>
<p xml:lang="rmu">Ederra 9258026</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 130.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Eventin 9308065</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 131.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Pravasi 9409467</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 132.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Sauri 9266475</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 25.2.2025 44transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 133.</p>
<p xml:lang="rmu">Temiro 9209972</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 134.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">East Energy 9216298</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 135.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Zaliv Vostok 9360130</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 136.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Zaliv Aniva 9418494</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 137.</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">Lokosao 9286657</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 138.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Madhav 9353096</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 45139.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Atlas 9413573</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 140.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Metagas Everest 9243148</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 141.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">T Cereal (formerly Rolin) 9286073</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 142.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Viktor Bakaev 9610810</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (c): are operated in such a way as to contribute or support actions or policies for the exploitation, development or expansion of the energy sector in Russia, including energy infrastructure. 25.2.2025 143.</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Fiora 9282493</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 144.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Noble 9333400</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 145.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Unity 9388792</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 146.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Sikar 9419137</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): 25.2.2025 46transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 147.</p>
<p xml:lang="olo">Anatoly Kolodkin 9610808</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025 148.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Wilma II 9247431</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 149.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Lorena Grand 9288899</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 150.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Corum 9544281</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 151.</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Xiwang 9317949</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 152.</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Azure Celeste 9288722</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (b): transport crude oil or petroleum products, as listed in Annex XXV, that originate in Russia or are exported from Russia while practicing irregular and high-risk shipping practices as set out in the International Maritime Organisation General Assembly resolution A.1192(33) 25.2.2025 47153.</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Aria 9397559</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Article 3s(2), point (g): are owned, chartered or operated by natural or legal persons, entities or bodies listed in Annex I to Regulation (EU) No 269/2014, are otherwise used in the name of, on behalf of, in relation with or for the benefit of such persons. 25.2.2025’. ” 48</p>
</body></document>
