<document xml:lang="fao" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="news"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>18290</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual/><origFileName>K 226-2025.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision$; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header>
<body>
<p xml:lang="fra">Nr. 226 30. desembur 2025</p>
<p><em type="bold">Kunngerð um broyting í kunngerð um avmarkandi tiltøk </em>(Avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við destabiliserandi virksemi, tiltøk móti ávísum skipum, o.a.) <em type="bold">§ 1 </em></p>
<p>Í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um av-markandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukra-ina, sum broytt við kunngerð nr. 37 frá 24. mars 2025, verða gjørdar hesar broytingar: <em type="bold">1. </em>Heitið á kunngerðini verður orðað soleiðis:“ </p>
<p><em type="bold">Kunngerð um ávís avmarkandi tiltøk </em>” <em type="bold">2. </em>Inngangurin til kunngerðina verður orðaður so-leiðis:“Við heimild í § 3, stk. 1 og 3, § 4, stk. 1 og 4, § 5, § 5 a, § 6, stk. 2, § 9 og § 10, stk. 2 í løgtingslóg nr. 90 frá 17. mai 2022 um ávís avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti </p>
<p>Ukraina, sum broytt við løgtingslóg nr. 193 frá 4. desember 2025, verða gjørdar hesar broyt-ingar:” <em type="bold">3. </em>Í § 7, stk. 2, § 9, stk. 5 og § 20, stk. 1 verður<span type="quote">“Landsstýrismaðurin”</span> broytt til: <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">“Landsstýris-fólkið”</span> og í § 13, stk. 4 verður <span type="quote">“landsstýris-maðurin”</span> broytt til: <span type="quote" xml:lang="isl">“landsstýrisfólkið”</span> <em type="bold">4. </em>Aftan á § 3, men áðrenn yvirskriftina yvir § 4,verður sett:“ <em type="bold">3 a. </em>Allir ognarlutir, sum eru ogn, í varð-veitslu ella undir ræði hjá likamligum ella løgfrøðiligum persónum ella eindum, nevndir í skjali 1 A ella 1 B, skulu frystast. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 2. </em>Eingin ognarlutur skal vera til fyri-muns fyri ella latast likamligum ella løgfrøði-ligum persónum ella eindum, nevndir í skjali 1 </p>
<p>A ella 1 B, at ráða yvir, hvørki beinleiðis ella óbeinleiðis.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 3. </em>Stk. 1 og 2 eru ikki galdandi fyri fiski-skap í altjóða sjógvi, sum er heimilaður í fiski-veiðuavtaluni millum Føroyar og Russland. </p>
<p>Undantakið er ikki galdandi fyri føroyskar lik-amligar ella løgfrøðiligar persónar ella eindir.” <em type="bold">5. </em>Aftan á § 13, men áðrenn yvirskriftina yvir §14, verður sett:“ <em type="italic">Forboð fyri útflutningi o.a. av marglætisvørum </em><em type="bold">§ 13 a. </em>Tað er bannað beinleiðis ella óbein-leiðis at selja, veita, flyta ella útflyta marglætis-vørur, nevndar í skjali 2 A, sama um vørurnar hava uppruna í Føroyum ella aðrastaðni, um-framt eisini einhvørjar tænastur, ið eru knýttar at vørum nevndar í skjali 2 A til likamligar ella løgfrøðiligar persónar ella eindir í Russlandi, til nýtslu í Russlandi ella setan umborð á skipi undir russiskum flaggi. Forboðið í 1. pkt. er galdandi fyri marglætisvørur, nevndar í skjali 2 </p>
<p>A, um virðið er omanfyri 300 evrur fyri hvørja vøru, um ikki annað er ásett í skjalinum.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 2. </em>Tað er bannað: 1) Beinleiðis ella óbeinleiðis at veita tøkni-ligan stuðul, meklaratænastur, viðlíkahaldella aðrar tænastur til likamligar ella løg-frøðiligar persónar ella eindir í Russlandi,ella til nýtslu í Russlandi, knýttar til aðrarvørur enn tær vørur, sum sambært stk. 1eru loyvdar at útflyta til Russlands.2) Beinleiðis ella óbeinleiðis at veita fíggingella fíggjarligan stuðul, knýtt at sølu,veiting, flyting ella útflutning av øðrumvørum enn tær, sum nevndar eru sambærtstk. 1, ella í sambandi við veiting av at-knýttum tøkniligum stuðli, meklaratænast-um, viðlíkahald, ella øðrum tænastum, tillikamligar ella løgfrøðiligar persónar ellaeindir í Russlandi ella til nýtslu í Russ-landi. </p>
<p><em type="italic">Stk. 3. </em>Forboðið í stk. 1 og 2 er ikki galdandi fyri vørur undir CN 7113 00 og CN 7114 00 00, sum eru persónlig ogn hjá likamligum per-sónum, sum ferðast úr Føroyum, og sum ikki eru ætlaðar til sølu.” <em type="bold">6. </em>Skjal 1 í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við </p>
<p>Givið út 30. desember 2025atgerðir móti Ukraina, verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 1. <em type="bold">7. </em>Skjal 2 verður sett sum skjal 1 A í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina. <em type="bold">8. </em>Skjal 3 verður sett sum skjal 1 B í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina. <em type="bold">9. </em>Skjal 2 í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina, verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 4. <em type="bold">10. </em>Skjal 5 verður sett sum skjal 2 A í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina. (luksusvørur) <em type="bold">11. </em>Skjal 6 A í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina, verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 6. (skipalistin) <em type="bold">12. </em>Skjal 15 í kunngerð nr. 108 frá 18. november 2024 um avmarkandi tiltøk í sambandi við atgerðir móti Ukraina, verður orðað sum ásett í skjali 7. <em type="bold">§ 2 </em></p>
<p>Henda kunngerð kemur í gildi 1. januar 2026.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Uttanríkis- og mentamálaráðið, 30. desembur 2025</p>
<p><em type="bold">Sirið Stenberg (sign.) </em>landsstýriskvinna / Herálvur Joensen (sign.) 2 </p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 1 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 1 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Listi við likamligum og løgfrøðiligum persónum, samsvarandi fylgiskjali I til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 269/2014 </em></p>
<p>Samanskrivaði listin hjá Evropasamveldinum við likamligum og løgfrøðiligum persónum, sum eru fevnd av avmarkandi tiltøkunum sambært § 3, samsvarandi fylgiskjali I til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 269/2014, sæst á heimasíðuni hjá Uttanríkis- og mentamálaráðnum, www.ummr.fo” 3</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 2 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Skjal 1 A </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Listi við likamligum og løgfrøðiligum persónum, samsvarandi fylgiskjali I til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 2024/2642 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl">A. Likamligir persónar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Name </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Identifying information Statement of Reasons </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Date of listing </em>1. </p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Artem Sergeevich</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">KUREEV (Russian: Артём</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Сергеевич КУРЕЕВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Officer of the 5th Service of the Federal Security</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Service, Editor-in-chief of the ‘African Initative’,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Founder of ‘Rusafro’</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 24.10.1980</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: USSR (now</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport number: 4002209800</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax Identification</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Number (INN): 782500167259</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artem Sergeevich Kureev is a Russian Federal Security Service officer involved in malign activities, namely coordinated disinformation campaigns, both in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe and Africa. He conducts influence campaigns in Europe, including by organising the dissemination of articles in Russian and their English translations on proxy websites and making payments for the publication of pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian articles, with the aim of spreading Russian disinformation in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe. He founded two media outlets in Africa and conducted deliberate disinformation campaigns aiming at undermining</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Western health projects in Africa by spreading conspiracy theories such as the alleged use of Africa for biological warfare experiments and illicit trials of various drugs by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Western pharmaceutical companies.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Artem Sergeevich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kureev is implementing actions or policies by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union or in third countries by planning and directing the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 16.12.20242.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Nikolai Aleksandrovich</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">TUPIKIN (russisk: Николай</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Александрович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ТУПИКИН)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Executive director of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Structura National</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Technologies a.k.a. GK</p>
<p xml:lang="rmy-rlo">Struktura</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: USSR (now</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nikolai Aleksandrovich Tupikin is the head and founder of Structura</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">National Technologies (GK</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Struktura). The company has been involved in the so-called ‘Doppelganger’ campaign, a</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian-led digital disinformation campaign aimed at manipulating information and spreading disinformation in support of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian war of aggression against</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine and targeting the Union’s</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States, the United States and Ukraine. He works in close 16.12.2024 4</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax Identification</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Number (INN): 773402066160 coordination with the Presidential</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Administration of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation. He has also been one of the key figures in Russia’s disinformation campaign across</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Latin America aiming at undermining support for Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Therefore, Nikolai Aleksandrovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tupikin is implementing actions or policies by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union or in third countries by planning and directing the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. He is also associated with Sofia</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Avraamovna Zakharova, department head in the Office of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">President of the Russian Federation for the Development of Information and Communication Technologies and Communications Infrastructure. 3.</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Sofia Avraamovna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">ZAKHAROVA (Russian: София</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">Авраамовна</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ЗАХАРОВА)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Department head in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Office of the President of the Russian Federation for the Development of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Information and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Communication</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Technologies and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Communications</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Infrastructure</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: USSR (now</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sofia Avraamovna Zakharova is the department head in the Office of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">President of the Russian Federation for the Development of Information and Communication Technologies and Communications Infrastructure.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">She has been involved in the so-called ‘Doppelganger’ campaign aimed at manipulating information and spreading disinformation in support of the Russian war of aggression against Ukraine and targeting the Union’s Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States, the United States and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine. She has been working directly with Ilya Gambashidze and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nikolai Tupikin, heads of Social</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Design Agency and GK Struktura, respectively, on this operation. She has also been one of the team leaders and active members of the so-called ‘Team I’ lead by Ilya</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gambashidze, which stands behind the Kremlin’s campaign for disinformation in the West, interfering in the elections of different countries, and is preparing projects to discredit the Russian opposition.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Sofia Avraamovna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Zakharova is implementing actions or policies by the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union or in third 16.12.2024 5countries by planning and directing the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 4.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Andrey Vladimirovich</p>
<p xml:lang="mns">AVERYANOV (Russian: Андрей</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Владимирович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">АВЕРЬЯНОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Commander of GRU unit 29155</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Major General</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 29.9.1967</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: USSR (now</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax Identification</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Number (INN): 773378888007</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Andrey Vladimirovich Averyanov is a high-ranking military official of the Main Directorate of the General</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Staff of the Armed Forces of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation (GRU). After the death of Yevgeny Prigozhin and the restructuring of the Wagner</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Group, the command of Russian military operations in Africa was restructured and placed under the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Africa Corps under the umbrella of the Russian Ministry of Defence, and Averyanov was placed in charge of the operations. In many</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">African countries, Russian forces provide security to military juntas that have overthrown legitimate democratic governments, gravely worsening the stability, security and democracy of the countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In addition, Russian forces in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Africa exploit the natural resources there to finance their operations. In the beginning of 2024, Russian forces took control of the Intahaka gold mine in Mali.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Andrey Vladimirovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Averyanov is implementing actions or policies by the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in third countries by undermining the democratic political process in the African countries where</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian forces operate and by exploiting an armed conflict, instability or insecurity, including through the illicit exploitation or trade of natural resources and wildlife in a third country. 16.12.2024 5.</p>
<p>Tinatin Givievna</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">KANDELAKI a.k.a.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tina KANDELAKI (Russian: Тинатин</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Гивиевна</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">КАНДЕЛАКИ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Journalist, public figure, celebrity, TV presenter and producer, Deputy</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">General Director of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gazprom Media Holding</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 10.11.1975</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">POB: Tbilisi, Georgian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">SSR (now Georgia)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Georgian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tinatin Givievna Kandelaki is a Russian journalist employed by the state-owned company Gazprom</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Media, and a public figure who has been using her popularity and influence in the public sphere to voice Russian propaganda and to justify the ongoing Russian war of aggression against Ukraine. She was among those who performed during the Luzhniki stadium concert of 18 March 2022 that marked the 8th anniversary of the illegal annexation of Crimea and 16.12.2024 6served as a symbol of support for the ongoing war in Ukraine. After 2014, she fully supported the illegal annexation of Crimea. Moreover, she is a Deputy General Director of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gazprom Media Holding, a holding of several media outlets that spread anti-Ukrainian propaganda and justify Russian aggression against</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Several TV channels owned and governed by Gazprom Media</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Holding have replaced Ukrainian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">TV outlets on local TV frequencies previously seized forcefully by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russians after the Russian invasion of Crimea and have thus actively participated in the process of the illegal annexation of Crimea.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Tinatin Givievna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kandelaki is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union or in one or several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States, in an international organisation, or in a third country, or which undermine or threaten the sovereignty or independence of one or several of its Member States, or of a third country, by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 6.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Vladimir Vladimirovich</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">SERGIYENKO (Russian: Владимир</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Владимирович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">СЕРГИЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Former assistant of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member of Bundestag</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Eugen Schmidt</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 23.5.1971</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Lviv, Ukrainian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">SSR (now Ukraine)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian /</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vladimir Vladimirovich Sergiyenko is a former parliamentary assistant of the Member of the German</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bundestag, Eugen Schmidt. In parallel, Sergiyenko actively colluded with Russian intelligence officers seeking to leverage his privileged parliamentary and political access to the detriment of the democratic political process and constitutional order of the Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Germany.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Vladimir Vladimirovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sergiyenko implemented and supported actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law and security in the Federal Republic of Germany by engaging in, 16.12.2024 7directly or indirectly, the obstruction or undermining of the democratic political process. 7.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Denis Alexandrovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">SMOLYANINOV (Russian: Денис</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Александрович</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">СМОЛЯНИНОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">GRU colonel</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 26.8.1976</p>
<p xml:lang="tur">POB: Chelyabinsk,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport number: 672904784466</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Denis Alexandrovich Smolyaninov is a GRU colonel who specialises in psychological operations. He is in charge of the Ukrainian direction of the GRU. Lists of mercenaries to be sent to the Donbass passed through the Ukrainian direction. He also supervised two private military companies (PMCs) associated with the Ministry of Defense:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Longifolia, a military company of crime bosses from the 1990s, through which contacts were established with Western PMCs, and Convoy, the military security company. Shortly before the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian invasion of Ukraine, he deployed an agent network in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine. He uses Telegram channels to spread disinformation, including in Ukraine. Through social media he recruits agents for sabotage activities in the Union and other activities aimed at creating tensions between NATO countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The GRU is responsible for actively preparing explosions, arson and damage to infrastructure on Union territory, with the goal of slowing down the supply of weapons to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine and of creating discord and the appearance of dissatisfaction with support for Ukraine in Europe.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Denis Alexandrovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Smolyaninov is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in third countries by planning and directing acts of violence, and by facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 16.12.2024 8.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Vladimir/ Volodymyr</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">LIPCHENKO (Russian: Володимир</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">ЛИПЧЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU officer</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 28.9.1974</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">POB: Mykolaiv,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian SSR (now</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport number: 4015400649</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vladimir Lipchenko is a GRU officer responsible for hybrid attacks in Europe under his pseudonym ‘Wlodek Lyakh’. He is part of a special department led by</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">GRU Colonel Denis Alexandrovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Smolyaninov, set up to conduct sabotage activities in Western countries. He recruited a person to set fire to the Museum of the 16.12.2024 8</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Occupation in Riga by throwing</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Molotov cocktails.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Vladimir Lipchenko is responsible for or implementing actions by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union by planning and directing acts of violence. 9.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yuriy SIZOV (Russian: Юрий</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">СИЗОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU military officer</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 17.2.1988</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">POB: St. Petersburg,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport number: 784805190577</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yuriy Sizov is a GRU military officer. He serves in military unit</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">No 92154. He personally gave instructions to recruit agents to target a hypermarket in Kyiv and recorded a video tutorial on installing an explosive device in one of the stores of the same chain in the Moscow region. He was also responsible for orchestrating sabotage in Ukraine in the Lviv region in February 2024. He supervised and gave orders to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian intelligence agents involved in the planned sabotage activity.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Yuriy Sizov is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union by planning and directing acts of violence. 16.12.2024 10. Visa Nokhayevich</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">MIZAEV (Виса Нохаевич</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">МИЗАЕВ) a.k.a.</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">Vishan Nochaevic</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">MIZAYEV;</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Vysa Nokhaevich</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">MIZAEV;</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Visa Nokhaievych</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">MIZAIEV;</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Oleg SHISHKIN</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Entrepreneur</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 9.7.1963</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Grozny, USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport No 753870064 (Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">No PRE0018440 (Federation of Saint</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Christopher and Nevis)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax Identification</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Number (INN): 481101523410</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Visa Nokhayevich Mizaev is a Russian entrepreneur. He played a key role in a Russian intelligence operation against the German</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federal Intelligence Service (BND) in which he instigated his accomplices to procure highly classified information from the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">BND and to pass it to the Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Security Service of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation (FSB).</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Visa Nokhayevich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mizaev implements and supports actions by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten the security in the Federal Republic of Germany by attempting to destabilise the constitutional order. 16.12.2024 11. Olga Alekseevna</p>
<p xml:lang="mns">BELYAVTSEVA (Ольга Алексеевна</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">БЕЛЯВЦЕВА) a.k.a.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Entrepreneur</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 25.10.1969</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Lipetsk, USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Olga Alekseevna Belyavtseva is a Russian entrepreneur. She is the wife and business partner of Visa</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nokhayevich Mizaev. She is associated with Visa Nokhayevich 16.12.2024 9</p>
<p xml:lang="fin">Olha Oleksiyivna</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">BIELIAVTSEVA;</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Olga Alekseevna</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">BELJIAWZEWA;</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Olga Aleksevna</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">MIZAEV</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport No 768613166 (Russian Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax Identification</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Number (INN): 481100083621</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mizaev through the co-ownership of the two Russia-based Limited</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Liability Companies ‘OOO</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Agronom-sad’ and ‘OOO Biplast’.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">She founded those companies and was the single shareholder before transferring 30 % of the shares for each company after their marriage in 2018. Moreover, Belyavtseva and Mizaev had a similar ownership arrangement over the company Agronom-Sad Trading before Mizaev sold his shares to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Belyavtseva on 22 February 2023 in direct temporal connection with</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Visa Mizaev’s involvement in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian intelligence operation against the Federal Republic of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Germany, providing Mizaev with additional liquidity and concealing his asset base.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Olga Alekseevna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Belyavtseva supports natural or legal persons, entities or bodies engaged in implementing actions or policies by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten the security of the Federal Republic of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Germany. She is also associated with Visa Nokhayevich Mizaev. 12. Timofey</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Vyacheslavovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">BORDACHEV (Russian: Тимофей</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Вячеславович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">БОРДАЧЕВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Political scientist</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 28.1.1973</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">POB: St. Petersburg,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Timofey Vyacheslavovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bordachev is a Russian political scientist and international affairs specialist. He is the Programme</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Director of the Valdai Discussion</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Club, Academic Supervisor of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Centre for Comprehensive</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">European and International Studies at the National Research</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">University – Higher School of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Economics, as well as member of the Council for Foreign and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Defence Policy.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Through his activities, he substantially contributes to the ideological base and rationalisation of the Russian war of aggression against Ukraine and aggressive policies of the Kremlin, including by promoting the view that neither</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine as a state nor its government are legitimate.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Timofey</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vyacheslavovich Bordachev is responsible for or supporting actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or 16.12.2024 10threaten the sovereignty or independence of Ukraine by engaging in and supporting the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 13. Harouna DOUAMBA</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Businessman, director of the Groupe Panafricain pour le Commerce et l’investissement</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 8.1.1973</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Cocody, Ivory</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coast</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Ivorian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Harouna Douamba is an Ivorian businessman, and the head of a pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian, anti-Western disinformation network in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Central African Republic (CAR) and Burkina Faso.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In 2011, Douamba founded a non-governmental organisation called <em type="italic">Aimons Notre </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="italic">Afrique </em>(ANACOM) in the CAR. </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">That organisation received funding from Lobaye Invest, which has been associated with the Wagner</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Group. In 2022, Harouna Douamba established the <em type="italic">Groupe Panafricain pour le Commerce et l'Investissement </em>(GPCI) in Burkina </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Faso. GPCI has been involved in covert influence operations.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Harouna Douamba’s disinformation networks were dismantled by Meta in May 2021, and later in May 2023. Despite this, GPCI-related disinformation groups are still active and running structured and coordinated disinformation campaigns, with the use of a vast network of information chains.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Those campaigns target France in particular, including through accusations of conspiracy, terrorism, destabilisation operations or preparing coups against the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or its Member States.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Harouna Douamba is supporting and implementing actions or policies of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in a Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">State or in a third country by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 16.12.2024 14. Anatolii PRIZENKO</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Businessman</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 26.11.1974</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Moldovan SSR (now Republic of</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Moldova)</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Nationality: Moldovan</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Anatolii Prizenko is a businessman in the Republic of Moldova. In late</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">October 2023, he coordinated the dispatch of several citizens of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Moldova to France, where they painted the Star of 16.12.2024 11</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">David on the streets in exchange for financial compensation. That operation was widely reported by the media and had a significant destabilising effect in the context of the conflict between Israel and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hamas following the attacks on 7 October 2023. Images of that operation were first spread by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Recent Reliable News media network, which is associated with the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation and used by Russian actors to conduct disinformation campaigns.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Anatolii Prizenko publicly took responsibility for his role as the organiser of that operation.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">According to media reports, that destabilising operation was carried out for the benefit of the Russian military intelligence service, the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU, and aimed at fuelling tensions in French society.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Anatolii Prizenko is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability in a Member State and, therefore, in the Union by planning, directing, or engaging in, directly or indirectly, the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15. Alesia</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MILORADOVICH or</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Alesya</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MILORADOVICH or</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Olesya MILORADOVIC</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">Алеся</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">МИЛОРАДОВИЧ or</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Олеся</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">МИЛОРАДОВИЧ</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Government employee, ‘Foreign Affairs</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Facilitator’</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Associate of the project ‘Foreign journalists for</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Russia’ (‘Инностранные журналисты за</p>
<p xml:lang="yrk">Россию’)</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 10.3.1968</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Angarsk, USSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alesya Miloradovich is a collaborator of the Government of the Russian Federation in France, and calls herself a ‘foreign affairs facilitator’.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alesya Miloradovich organised a so-called ‘electoral observation’ mission in the Ukrainian territories illegally occupied by Russia, in the context of the referendum on the annexation of those regions to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia, and recruited French nationals who participated in the mission. She publicly admitted that she did this for the benefit of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Government.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">She was also a co-organiser of trips for French children to the Artek</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">International Children Center in illegally annexed Crimea, which were funded by the Government of the Russian Federation. She has also been involved in the Russian 16.12.2024 12propaganda project ‘Foreign journalists for Russia’ and has participated in spreading pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian views, including by claiming that French and Western societies support Russian actions against Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Alesya Miloradovich is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in a third country by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, or otherwise facilitating the obstruction or undermining of the democratic political process of a third country, including by attempting to destabilise its constitutional order. 16. Oleg Sergeevich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">EREMENKO (Russian: Олег</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Сергеевич</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">ЕРЕМЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Representative of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Officers of Russia, former GRU officer</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 18.5.1978</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">POB: Bischkek, Kyrgyz</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">SSR (now Kyrgyzstan)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: Male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oleg Sergeevich Eremenko is a former GRU officer and an active member of various Russian influence groups. Notably, he is a member of ‘Officers of Russia’ an organisation used by the Russian military and security services to influence domestic politics by cultivating links to veterans amongst the Russian diaspora and to retired military and security personnel of former Soviet-allied armed forces, in which he serves as their main representative in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Germany. In that capacity, Oleg</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sergeevich Eremenko is associated with the EU designated entities</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rossotrudnitschestvo, which is the operator of the ‘Russian House’ in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Berlin, and the Wagner Group. In his role as an envoy of the Russian state security apparatus, Oleg</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sergeevich Eremenko is cultivating links to and supporting anti-democratic organisations within</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Germany. He is well connected with far-left anti-democratic groups and groups of former personnel of outlawed GDR security services and veterans of GDR military formations, such as Desant e.V., a pro-Russian association of former paratroopers.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Oleg Sergeevich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Eremenko is supporting actions or policies by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which 16.12.2024 13undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Federal Republic of Germany by undermining the democratic political process, including by attempting to destabilise its constitutional order. 17. Alik Yuryevich</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">KHUCHBAROV</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Alik Yuryevich</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">HUCHBAROV</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alik HUTŠBAROV (Russian: Алик</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Юрьевич ХУЧБАРОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: GRU operative</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 12.11.1992</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Estonian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax identification number: 601515903509</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alik Khuchbarov was reponsible for planning and preparing an operation in Estonia, which entailed damaging the property of public figures who have spoken out against the Russian war of aggression against Ukraine, as well as defacing monuments related to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">World War II. In doing so, he acted under the direction, in the interests and at the request of Russia’s military foreign intelligence agency (GRU) to hire perpetrators to carry out the attacks. In the attacks, vehicles of the Estonian Minister of the Interior as well as of the editor-in-chief of a Russian-language newspaper were targetted. The security services of Estonia prevented further attacks targeting more public figures. In addition, several war memorials in Estonia were defaced, with paint thrown on them and swastikas drawn on them.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The aim of the operation was to create fear, panic and tension in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Estonian society, and to intimidate persons critical of Russian actions and policies.As a collaborator in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU’s network, Alik Khuchbarov is responsible for implementing actions by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in a Member State through planning and directing acts of violence, including activities to silence, intimidate, coerce, or exact reprisals against persons critical of the actions or policies of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation. 20.5.2025 18. Ilya Sergeevich</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">BOCHAROV</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ilja BOTŠAROV (Russian: Илья</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Сергеевич БОЧАРОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: GRU operative</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 29.6.1991</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax identification number: 561410364291</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ilya Bocharov was reponsible for planning and preparing an operation in Estonia, which entailed damaging the property of public figures who have spoken out against the Russian war of aggression against Ukraine, as well as defacing monuments related to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">World War II. In doing so, he acted 20.5.2025 14under the direction, in the interests and at the request of Russia’s military foreign intelligence agency (GRU) to hire perpetrators to carry out the attacks. In the attacks, vehicles of the Estonian Minister of the Interior as well as of the editor-in-chief of a Russian-language newspaper were targetted. The security services of Estonia prevented further attacks targeting more public figures. In addition, several war memorials in Estonia were defaced, with paint thrown on them and swastikas drawn on them.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The aim of the operation was to create fear, panic and tension in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Estonian society, and to intimidate persons critical of Russian actions and policies.As a collaborator in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU’s network, Ilya Bocharov is responsible for implementing actions by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in a Member State through planning and directing acts of violence, including activities to silence, intimidate, coerce, or exact reprisals against persons critical of the actions or policies of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation. 19. Elena</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">KOLBASNIKOVA (Russian: Елена</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">КОЛБАСНИКОВА</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Ukrainian,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 20.3.1975</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">POB: Dnipro, Ukraine</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">SSR (now Ukraine)</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Elena Kolbasnikova is a Russian national who has close ties with, and is financially supported by,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rossotrudnitschestwo, a Russian state entity. Kolbasnikova formed political structures with the German anti-democratic extreme political right in support of Russia’s destabilisation of Ukraine. She was sentenced for hate speech in a court of final instance in Germany in regard to her undermining of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian sovereignty and denouncement of German public institutions. Criminal investigations are ongoing in regard to her support of separatists in the Donbas with military hardware, through fundraisers and the provision of aid to separatist groups. Moreover,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kolbasnikova promoted violent acts committed by her husband,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rostislav Teslyuk, against counter-demonstrators, and organised car rallies to intimidate Ukrainian minors seeking refuge in Germany. 20.5.2025 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">She thus supports actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of a Member State through activities aimed at undermining the democratic political process in Germany. She also supports actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine the security of a third country (Ukraine), through instigating or facilitating an armed conflict, by supporting separatist movements in</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Elena Kolbasnikova is associated with Rostislav Teslyuk, through joint efforts in destabilising activities. 20. Hüseyin DOGRU</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Kavacık</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Mahallesi, Fatih Sultan</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Mehmet Caddesi,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tonoglu Block No.: 3,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Beykoz, Istanbul,</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Türkiye</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Turkish</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hüseyin Doğru is the founder and representative of AFA Medya A.Ș. which is a media company based in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Istanbul. AFA Medya A.Ș. operates <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“RED”</span>, which comprises a number of media platforms, and which has close financial and organisational connections with Russian state propaganda entities and actors, and shares deep structural ties, including interlinkages between, and rotation of, individual personnel with Russian state media organisations.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RED has used its media platforms – often publishing under <span type="quote" xml:lang="ron">“redstreamnet”</span> or <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“thered.stream”</span> – to systematically spread false information on politically controversial subjects with the intent of creating ethnic, political and religious discord amongst its predominantly German target audience, including by disseminating the narratives of radical Islamic terrorist groups such as Hamas.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">During a violent occupation of a German university by anti-Israel rioters, RED personnel coordinated with the occupiers to disseminate images of their vandalism – which included the use of Hamas symbols – through their online channels, thus providing them with an exclusive media platform, facilitating the violent nature of the protest. 20.5.2025 16</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Through AFA Medya, Hüseyin</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Doğru thus supports actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability and security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union and in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States, including by indirectly supporting and facilitating violent demonstrations and engaging in coordinated information manipulation. 21. Yulia Sergeevna</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">PROKHOROVA (Russian: Юлия</p>
<p xml:lang="yrk">Сергеевна</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ПРОХОРОВА)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 18.2.1992</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation, United Arab</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Emirates.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Formerly Landshut,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bavaria, Germany</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yulia Prokhorova is a Russian citizen. She resided in Germany until 2024. Yulia Prokhorova sustains a social media campaign in which she promoted the intentional wasting of energy in Germany, seeking to support Russia’s war of aggression. In parallel, she disseminates misinformation in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian state media about the energy supply, the rule of law, and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian refugees in Germany.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In addition, Yulia Prokhorova intimidated Ukrainian refugees in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe through public assaults and other forms of harassment, which she recorded and disseminated online.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yulia Prokhorova thus supports actions and policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union or in one Member State by engaging in the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference and indirectly supporting actions targeted at economic activities and services of public interest. 20.5.2025 22. Rostislav TESLYUK (Russian: Ростислав</p>
<p xml:lang="mrj">ТЕСЛЮК)</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Alias</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Max SCHLUND (Russian: Макс</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ШЛУНД)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 23.4.1982</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Moscow</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rostislav Teslyuk is a Russian national who has close ties with, and is financially supported by,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rossotrudnitschestwo, a Russian state entity. Rostislav Teslyuk formed political structures with the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">German anti-democratic extreme political right in support of Russia’s destabilisation of Ukraine. Criminal investigations in regard to his support of separatists in the Donbas with military hardware are ongoing.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rostislav Teslyuk committed violent acts against counter-demonstrators and organised car rallies to intimidate Ukrainian 20.5.2025 17minors seeking refuge in Germany, together with Elena Kolbasnikova.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">He thus supports actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of a Member State (Germany) through activities aimed at undermining the democratic political process in Germany. He is also responsible for actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation, which undermine the security of a third country (Ukraine) through instigating or facilitating an armed conflict, by his support for separatist movements in</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rostislav Teslyuk is associated with</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Elena Kolbasnikova, who is subject to restrictive measures, through joint efforts in destabilising activities. 23. Alina LIPP</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: war correspondent</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 17.9.1993</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">POB: Hamburg</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: German</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Alina Lipp runs the blog <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“Neues aus Russland”</span>, in which she systematically disseminates misinformation about Russia’s war of aggression against Ukraine, and delegitimises the Ukrainian government, especially with a view to manipulating German public sentiment as regards support for</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Furthermore, she is using her role as a war correspondent with the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian armed forces in eastern</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine to spread Russian war propaganda. She regularly appears in troop entertainment and propaganda shows on the Russian military TV channel Zvezda.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thus, Alina Lipp is engaging in and supporting actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten security and stability in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union and in a third country (Ukraine) through the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference, and through facilitating an armed conflict in a third country. 20.5.2025 24. Viktor Volodymyrovych</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MEDVEDCHUK (Ukrainian: Віктор</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Володимирович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">МЕДВЕДЧУК)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Politician, businessman, de facto media owner</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 7.8.1954</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Viktor Medvedchuk is a former</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian politician and businessman, who has been the leading proponent of a pro-Russian policy in Ukraine and who has promoted policies and actions 20.5.2025 18(Russian: Виктор</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Владимирович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">МЕДВЕДЧУК)</p>
<p xml:lang="swe">POB: Pochet,</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Krasnoyarskyi Krai,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian SFSR, USSR</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Moscow</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian Tax ID (Код</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">ДРФО): 1994214296 (void) intended to erode the credibility and legitimacy of the Government of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine. Viktor Medvedchuk has close personal ties to, and is associated with, the President of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation, Vladimir Putin.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Through his associates, including</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Artem Marchevskyi, Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk controlled Ukrainian media outlets and used them to disseminate pro-Russian propaganda in Ukraine and beyond.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">After the start of Russia’s war of aggression against Ukraine, Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk spread Russian propaganda narratives about the war, undermining Ukrainian sovereignty. To that end, in April 2023, Viktor Medvedchuk founded a political movement in Russia called <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“Another Ukraine”</span>.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">With his associates and associated entities, including Artem</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Marchevskyi and the Voice of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe media channel, and in close coordination with the Russian authorities, Viktor Medvedchuk has continued funding and carrying out influence operations targeting political parties and individual politicians in Europe. Those activities aimed to support the foreign policy interests of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation and to spread its influence, including ahead of the 2024 European Parliament elections. Those activities included providing financial resources to individual political actors in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe, including selected candidates in the European</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parliament elections, and for cooperation with journalists. Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk has directed and maintained control over the malign activities of Artem Marchevskyi and Voice of Europe, using Artem</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Marchevskyi’s de facto direction of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Voice of Europe.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Viktor Medvedchuk is responsible for, implementing, supporting, or benefitting from actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in the Union and in a third country, and which undermine the sovereignty or independence of several of its Member States and of 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, through planning, directing, engaging in and otherwise facilitating the obstruction or undermining of the democratic political process, including the 2024 European</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parliament elections, and through planning, directing and engaging in the use of information manipulation and interference. 25.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Artem Pavlovich MARCHEVSKYI Artem Pavlovich MARCHEVSKIJ Artem Pavlovich MARCHEVSKIY Artěm Pavlovič MARČEVSKIJ (Ukrainian: Артем Павлович МАРЧЕВСЬКИЙ) (Russian: Артем</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Павлович</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">МАРЧЕВСКИЙ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Politician, media producer, propagandist</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 5.7.1988</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Kyiv, Ukrainian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">SSR, USSR, (now</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ukraine)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Ukrainian,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Israeli</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Hovorčovická 1079, 250 65 Líbeznice,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Czech Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian Tax ID (Код</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ДРФО): 3232824038</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artem Marchevskyi is a former</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian politician closely associated with Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk, a former Ukrainian politician and businessperson with close connections to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation. By virtue of his position in the pro-Russian party <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“Opposition Platform – For Life”</span> and in a TV channel involved in pro-Russian propaganda, Artem</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Marchevskyi supported and provided assistance to Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk in the years 2018 to 2021. Artem Marchevskyi and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Viktor Medvedchuk continued to coordinate after they both left</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine following the Russian invasion in 2022, with Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk directing and controlling Artem Marchevskyi’s activities facilitating construction of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk’s influence network in the Union and its Member States.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artem Marchevskyi has played an instrumental role in disseminating concerted disinformation and biased narratives aimed at supporting the foreign policy interests of the Russian Federation and spreading its influence, including ahead of the 2024</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">European Parliament elections, by undermining the credibility and public image of Ukraine and its efforts to defend itself against</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia’s war of aggression. Artem</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Marchevskyi played a key role in the acquisition of the media brand <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“Voice of Europe”</span> and the incorporation of its activity in a company of the same name. As the concealed head of Voice of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe, Artem Marchevskyi has used the company to funnel financial resources designated for the remuneration of propagandists, and to build an influence network 20.5.2025 20connecting Medvedchuk and his associates with representatives of political parties in Europe.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Artem Marchevskyi is responsible for actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in the Union and in Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty or independence of several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States and of Ukraine, through engaging in and otherwise facilitating the obstruction or undermining of the democratic political process and through planning, directing and engaging in the use of information manipulation and interference. 26.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natallia SUDLIANKOVA A.k.a.: Natallia SUDLENKOVA Natalia SUDLENKOVA Natalia SUDLIANKOVÁ (ŠEVKOVÁ) Natalija SUDLIANKOVÁ (ŠEVKOVÁ) (Russian: Наталья СУДЛЕНКОВА (ШЕВКО)) Alias: Natalyia KORNELYUK (Russian: Наталья</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">КОРНЕЛЮК)</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Function: Journalist,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Media and PR</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Consultant, Coordinator</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 9.6.1964</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">POB: Belarus</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Belarusian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Borovanského 2381/22, 155 00 Prague,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Czech Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Identity documents:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Travel document:</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">U0002974, valid until 18.3.2031</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Residence Permit: 001631077, valid until 13.3.2034</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natallia Sudliankova is a journalist and a media and PR consultant who has been producing custom-made media products that included information manipulation and spreading misleading narratives aiming to support the foreign policy interests of the Russian Federation and aiming to undermine the public trust towards Czech national and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">European Union democratic values and processes. Sudliankova has been receiving assignments over a long period of time and has been financially rewarded.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">She plays a significant role in planning and directing coordinated information manipulation intended for the public in the Czech Republic and in other Member States, and cooperates with Russian state entities (Rosatom, Pravfond), entities representing the interests of the Russian Federation (Immortal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Regiment of Russia), and Alexey</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nikolayevich Shavrov, an officer of the Main Directorate of the General</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Staff of the Armed Forces of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation (GRU).</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Natallia Sudliankova is responsible for actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in the Union and in Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty or independence of several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States and of Ukraine, through planning, directing and 20.5.2025 21engaging in the use of information manipulation. 27. Iurie NECULITI (Russian: Юрие</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">НЕКУЛИТИ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: CEO of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industries</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 71-75 Shelton</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Street, Covent Garden,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">London, United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom; Chisinau,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Bender, Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Iurie Neculiti is CEO of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industries Solutions Ltd., a web hosting service registered as a maildrop company in the United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom. The company provides server hosting, with server locations all over the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stark enables various Russian state-sponsored and state-affiliated actors to conduct destabilising activities including coordinated information manipulation and interference and cyber-attacks against the Union and third countries by providing services intended to hide these activities from European law enforcement and security agencies.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, as CEO of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industries Solutions Ltd., Neculiti is supporting actions by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which threaten democracy and the rule of law, stability or security in the Union, in one of its Member States and a third country, by facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference and by facilitating actions targeted at the functioning of democratic institutions, economic activities or services of public interest.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Iurie Neculiti is associated with</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ivan Neculiti and Stark Industries. 20.5.2025 28.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Ivan NECULITI (Russian: Иван</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">НЕКУЛИТИ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Owner of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industries and PQ</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Hosting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 71-75 Shelton</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Street, Covent Garden,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">London, United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom; Chisinau,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Bender, Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ivan Neculiti is the owner of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Industries Solutions Ltd., a web hosting service registered as a maildrop company in the United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom. The company provides server hosting, with server locations all over the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stark enables various Russian state-sponsored and state-affiliated actors to conduct destabilising activities, including coordinated information manipulation and interference and cyber-attacks against Union and third countries, by providing services intended to hide these activities from European law enforcement and security agencies.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ivan Neculiti is associated with</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Iurie Neculiti and Stark Industries.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, as the owner of Stark</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Industries Solutions Ltd. Ivan</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Neculiti is supporting actions by the 20.5.2025 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which threaten democracy and the rule of law, stability or security in the Union, in one of its Member States and in a third country, by facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference and by facilitating actions targeted at the functioning of democratic institutions, economic activities or services of public interest. 29. Andrei KHARKOVSKY (Russian: Андрей</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ХАРКОВСКИЙ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Leading member of the Union of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cossack Warriors of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia and Abroad</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">POB: Tomsk Region,</p>
<p xml:lang="kal">Russia</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Germany</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Andrei Kharkovsky is a Russian citizen living in Germany. In</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Germany, Kharkovsky functions as a representative of the Union of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cossack Warriors of Russia and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Abroad, including by organising military-style gatherings for its members. The Union of Cossack</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Warriors of Russia and Abroad is an entity linked to the Government of the Russian Federation, and partaking in Russia’s war of aggression and acts of violence in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine in support of pro-Russian separatists under the premise of a <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“historical mission”</span> to reinstate</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian control over southern and eastern Ukraine. As a member of the Union of Cossack Warriors of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia and Abroad, Kharkovsky is engaging in acts of violence.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Andrei Kharkovsky is therefore supporting actions of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine the sovereignty and security of Ukraine by attempting to overthrow the constitutional order of Ukraine. 20.5.2025 30. Anatoli Yurevich</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ABRAMOV (Russian: Анатолий</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Юрьевич АБРАМОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Director of the</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">General Radio</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Frequency Centre branch in the Northwestern</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Federal District</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Anatoly Abramov is the director of the General Radio Frequency</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Centre’s Northwestern Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">District branch. Branch heads are appointed and dismissed by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Director of the GRFC in agreement with Roskomnadzor, and act on behalf of the GRFC.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">He oversees the use of radio frequencies and devices in the</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kaliningrad region.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Recently, GPS signal failures in several European countries have been linked to electronic warfare activities from Kaliningrad, including jamming and spoofing of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GPS signals, primarily affecting the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Baltic States. These activities have 20.5.2025 23disrupted civil aviation. The repression of GPS signals requires the permission of the GRFC.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Anatoly Abramov is responsible for, planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States, through engaging in actions which are targeted at the functioning of critical infrastructure. 31. Ruslan Vasilyevich</p>
<p xml:lang="mns">NESTERENKO (Russian: Руслан</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Васильевич</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">НЕСТЕРЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Acting General</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Director of the GRFC</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ruslan Nesterenko is the acting general director of the General</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Radio Frequency Centre (GRFC).</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">He oversees the use of radio frequencies and ensures compliance with legislation.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Recently, GPS signal failures in several European countries have been linked to electronic warfare activities from Kaliningrad, Russia, including jamming and spoofing of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GPS signals, primarily affecting the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Baltic States and disrupting civil aviation. The repression of GPS signals requires the permission of the GRFC.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Under Nesterenko’s direction, the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRFC is involved in planning and supporting information manipulation and interference that impacts Union Member States. As per the GRFC Charter, the general director represents the enterprise’s interests within Russia and beyond its borders.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Ruslan Nesterenko is responsible for, planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States through engaging in actions which are targeted at the functioning of critical infrastructure and through supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 20.5.2025 2432. Viktor Aleksandrovitch</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">LUKOVENKO (Russian: Виктор</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Александрович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ЛУКОВЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Alias</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Viktor VASILEV (Russian: Виктор</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ВАСИЛЬЕВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Head of the news agency “African</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Initiative”</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 6.4.1985</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Uzbek</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Viktor Lukovenko has been active on the African continent for several years, previously as a member of the Wagner Group and now as the head of the news agency “African</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Initiative”. He is involved in spreading Russian propaganda on the continent. He is linked to well known figures of Russian propaganda in Africa. Additionally,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Viktor Lukovenko was sent to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine in 2022 before the war, under the supervision of a GRU colonel, in order to recruit pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian sympathisers.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Viktor Lukovenko is therefore responsible for, implementing, and supporting actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States, by planning, directing, engaging in, directly and indirectly, supporting and facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 20.5.2025 33. Oleg Anatoliyovych</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">VOLOSHIN (Ukrainian: Олег</p>
<p xml:lang="kpv">Анатолійович</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">ВОЛОШИН) (Russian: Олег</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Анатольевич</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ВОЛОШИН)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 7.4.1981</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">POB: Nikolaev, USSR (now Ukraine)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Passport No.: ET870130</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">ID-No.: 1981040705733; 2968200719</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oleg Voloshin is a former</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian member of parliament and a member of the pro-Russian political party “Opposition</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Platform – For Life” (OPFL). He is part of the network behind <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“Voice of Europe”</span> and is active at Golos.eu and PolitWera, both platforms spreading disinformation and pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian narratives. He was involved in bribe payments made to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Western politicians.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oleg Voloshin has used his position as Ukrainian delegate to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parliamentary Assembly of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Council of Europe (2019-2023) to implement the strategy of Russian interference in Europe led by pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Russian oligarch Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk, who leads OPFL.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In particular, Voloshin has promoted Medvedchuk’s <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“peace plan”</span> for Ukraine, which is linked to the Russian narrative regarding</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia’s war of aggression. In order to win-over European elected representatives to his cause, he has organised conferences with French and German parliamentarians, arguing that the <span type="quote" xml:lang="nno">“Normandy format”</span> (France, Germany, 20.5.2025 25</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, Russia) has a so-called parliamentary dimension outside any official framework. The most recent event was organised by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Voloshin at the French Senate on 11 February 2022 (<span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“Peace process in Ukraine: how to break the deadlock”</span>), a few days before the invasion of Ukraine by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian army.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thus, Oleg Voloshin is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefitting from actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union and its Member States, including Germany, by planning, directing, engaging in, directly and indirectly, the obstruction and undermining of the democratic political process. 34. Justin Blaise TAGOUH (Russian: Жюстин Блез</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ТАГУ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: CEO of press group International</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Afrique Media (IAM), which includes the TV channel Afrique Média,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">IAM press review, and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Courrier Confidentiel</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 1959</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Justin Tagouh is CEO of the press group International Africa Media.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">This media group has direct links with the Russian authorities, and spreads Russian narrative and anti-western narrative in African countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Justin Tagouh is therefore responsible for, implementing, and supporting actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 20.5.2025 35. Mikhaïl Mikhaïlovich</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">PRUDNIKOV</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Alias <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“Micha”</span> (Russian: Михаил</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Михайлович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ПРУДНИКОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Member of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Africa Politology, entity responsible for disinformation and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian propaganda in the Central African</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="est">POB: Tambov Oblast</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mikhaïl Prudnikov is a Russian disinformation activist operating in the Central African Republic (CAR) who has close links with the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wagner galaxy and disinformation campaign holdings in CAR through various newspapers and networks.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In particular, he developed a narrative against western countries and participated in communication actions in order to undermine and threaten the Union’s image in the CAR. 20.5.2025 26</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Mikhaïl Prudnikov is therefore responsible for, implementing, and supporting actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 36. Sylvain AFOUA (Russian: Сильвен</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">АФУА)</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Alias</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Egountchi BEHANZIN (Russian: Эгунчи</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">БЕХАНЗИН)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Founder of the pan-African group “Ligue de défense noire</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Africaine” (LDNA); influencer/activist known by the pseudonym <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“Egountchi Behanzin”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 5.11.1988</p>
<p xml:lang="smn">POB: Madjikpeto, Togo</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: French,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Togolese</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Website: www.egountchibehanzin.com</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sylvain Afoua is a pro-Russian activist, founder of the “ <em type="italic">Ligue de défense noire Africaine </em>” (LDNA) (Black African Defence League), a group involved in hit actions on </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">French territory. The structure was dissolved by a French ministerial decree of 29 September 2021 for spreading an ideology calling for hatred, discrimination and violence.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sylvain Afoua spreads Russian narratives and misinformation on the war of aggression against</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, which he carries out in particular on the African continent.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">His message is transmitted via social networks and his association’s website. He is regularly invited to Russian fora and is, furthermore, financially linked to the Wagner Group.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sylvain Afoua is therefore responsible for, implementing, supporting and benefitting from actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 20.5.2025 37. Thomas RÖPER (Russian: Томас</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">РЁПЕР)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: war correspondent</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 26.11.1971</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">POB: Bremen</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: German</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thomas Röper is a German blogger. Through his network of online channels named “Anti-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Spiegel”, he systematically disseminates misinformation about</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia’s war of aggression against</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine and delegitimises the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian government, especially with a view to manipulating 20.5.2025 27</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">German public sentiment regarding support to Ukraine.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Furthermore, he legitimises</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia’s illegal annexation of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian territory by serving as an election <span type="quote" xml:lang="fra">“observer”</span> and participating in a campaign to promote Russia’s illegal referendum on the secession from</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine of the Russian-occupied territories. Moreover, he has served as a spokesperson for the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federationto disseminate Russian propaganda narratives, including at the UN Arria-forum.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Thomas Röper is therefore engaging in and supporting the use of information manipulation and interference and facilitates an armed conflict in a third country. 38. Nathalie YAMB</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 22.7.1969</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">POB: La Chaux-de-</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Fonds, Switzerland</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Swiss and</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Cameroonian</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Gender: female</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nathalie Yamb is a social media influencer. Since the Sochi summit she attended in 2019, Nathalie</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yamb has been an outspoken supporter of Russia, adopting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moscow’s language and targeting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">France and the West in particular, with a view to ousting them from the African continent. She has specific ties with AFRIC, an organisation linked to Russian private military companies.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Nathalie Yamb is supporting actions or policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union or in its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States by engaging in the use of information manipulation. 26.6.2025 39. Andrey Yuryevich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">ROMANCHENKO (Russian: Андрей</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Юрьевич</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">РОМАНЧЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: General</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Director of the Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian Television and</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Radio Broadcasting</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Network’ (RTRS)</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 16.10.1960</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Moscow, Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">SSR (now Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Tax ID (ИНН): 771515786260</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Andrey Yuryevich Romanchenko is the General Director of The Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Television and Radio Broadcasting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Network’ (RTRS), a Russian federal unitary for-profit enterprise of strategic significance, operating terrestrial radio and television broadcasting infrastructure in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia. Romanchenko, who was appointed as General Director by the Russian President, directs the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RTRS, which plays a direct role in implementing policies attributable to the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation by providing the 15.7.2025 28infrastructure and technical capabilities for the transmission of the so called ‘All-Russian mandatory publicly available television and radio channels’ such as Pervyi Kanal or Rossiya 24 which disseminate Russian state propaganda.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Under Romanchenko’s leadership,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RTRS has played a key role in effectively replacing legacy</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian broadcasting systems in occupied regions with a network that transmits content approved by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation intended to suppress dissent, to align the local population with Russian policies and to delegitimise Ukraine’s governance in the occupied territories. This directly undermines the ability of local populations to access diverse and independent information. The expansion of RTRS operations into the occupied territories is facilitated by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which grants RTRS the exclusive right to establish transmission infrastructure in the occupied territories. By overseeing and directing these operations,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Romanchenko actively facilitates the obstruction of access to diverse and independent information, thereby assuming responsibility for the use of information manipulation.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Romanchenko, as the head of RTRS, benefits from and implements policies attributable to the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty and independence of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 40. Vladimir NAIDENOV (Russian: Владимир</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">НАЙДЕНОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Director of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Department for</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coordination of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Communications</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Infrastructure</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Development in New</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Territories of the Federal</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian Television and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vladimir Naidenov is the Director of the Department for Coordination of Communications Infrastructure</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Development in New Territories at the Federal State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian Television and Radio</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Broadcasting Network’ (RTRS), a Russian federal unitary for-profit enterprise of strategic significance operating terrestrial radio and 15.7.2025 29</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Radio Broadcasting</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Network’ (RTRS)</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian television broadcasting infrastructure in Russia. Vladimir</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Naidenov, is subordinated to the</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">RTRS General Director Andrey</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yuryevich Romanchenko, who directs the RTRS and plays a direct role in implementing policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation. RTRS provides infrastructure and technical capabilities for the transmission of the so called ‘All-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian mandatory publicly available television and radio channels’ such as Pervyi Kanal or</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rossiya 24 which disseminate</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian state propaganda.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">In his position within the RTRS,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vladimir Naidenov has played a key role in effectively replacing legacy Ukrainian broadcasting systems in occupied regions with a network that transmits content approved by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation intended to suppress dissent, to align the local population with Russian policies and to delegitimise Ukraine’s governance in the occupied territories. This directly undermines the ability of local populations to access diverse and independent information. The expansion of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RTRS operations into the occupied regions is facilitated by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which grants RTRS the right to establish transmission infrastructure there.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Vladimir Naidenov, as the Director of the Department for</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coordination of Communications</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Infrastructure Development in New</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Territories at RTRS, facilitates the obstruction of access to diverse and independent information by coordinating the RTRS infrastructure development in the occupied Ukrainian territories and thus implements policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty and independence of Ukraine, through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference 3041. Dmitri BUIMISTRU</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: TV presenter, actor; blogger</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 26.11.1992</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Chișinău, Republic of Moldova</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Nationality: Moldovan</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dmitri Buimistru intentionally engages in coordinated information manipulation and interference by operating as a key propagandist on</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MD24, a Russia-based online TV channel created by Ilan Shor following license withdrawals from his previous stations for disseminating Russian disinformation. To that end,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Buimistru deliberately spreads demonstrably false claims – systematically debunked by independent fact-checkers – regarding NATO drawing Moldova into conflict, imminent revocation of constitutional neutrality, ‘Romanization’ of institutions, misrepresentation of the EU referendum’s constitutional implications, and fabricated trade statistics.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Furthermore, his participation in synchronised cross-platform disinformation campaigns is evidenced by the July 2023 Russian embassy surveillance equipment scandal, where his messaging was perfectly coordinated with other pro-Kremlin outlets, demonstrating centralised orchestration. In addition, Buimistru’s ‘SOSEDI’ project has been identified as a key tool in a broader external influence operation. His systematic promotion of other pro-Russian information sources and deployment of consistent messaging tactics specifically designed to undermine Moldova’s sovereignty, European integration, and democratic processes further confirms his deliberate engagement in coordinated information manipulation with a view to serving</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian destabilisation interests in</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Moldova.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Dmitri Buimistru is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions and policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability in a third country through engaging in, directly or indirectly, the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15.7.2025 42. Veaceslav VALICO</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Function: Activist</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Veaceslav Valico participated, alongside Anatolii Prizenko, 15.7.2025 31</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">DOB: 10.8.1977 POB: Chișinău, Republic of Moldova Nationality: Moldovan Gender: male a natural person listed by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union, in the Russian destabilisation operation concerning the painting of the Star of David on the streets of Paris following the 7 October 2023 Hamas attack on</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Israel in exchange for financial compensation and in order to create tensions in French society.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moreover, Veaceslav Valico is involved in the systematic dissemination of disinformation in the Republic of Moldova and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, as part of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation’s malign hybrid activities.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Furthermore, Veaceslav Valico is associated with Anatolii Prizenko, who is an individual listed by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union. Their association predates their collaboration in the Paris incident.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Veaceslav Valico is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions and policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten the stability in a Member State and therefore, in the Union, and in third countries, through planning, directing, and engaging in, directly or indirectly, the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 43. Simeon BOIKOV</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Pro-Russian blogger</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of birth: 15.2.1990</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of birth: Sydney,</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Australia</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Australian/Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Simeon Boikov is an Australian pro-Russian activist known by the pseudonym ‘Aussie Cossack’. He is recognised for disseminating pro-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kremlin narratives and misinformation, particularly regarding the COVID-19 pandemic and the Russian invasion of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine. Boikov has also been implicated in spreading disinformation related to the 2024</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">U.S. presidential election, notably by paying an American influencer to post a Storm-1516 fabricated video falsely depicting voter fraud in Georgia.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Simeon Boikov is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions and policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union or in third countries, by planning, directing, engaging in, 15.7.2025 32directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 44. Vitaly KULIKOV (Russian: Виталий</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">КУЛИКОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Function: Lieutenant</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Colonel in the Russian military, heading the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electronic Warfare (EW) center of the Baltic Fleet</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lieutenant Colonel Vitaly Kulikov is the commander of the Electronic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Warfare (EW) center of the Baltic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Fleet also known as the 841st</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Separate Electronic Warfare Center.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vitaly Kulikov oversees exercises of his EW troops in the Kaliningrad region.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GPS signal failures in several</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">European countries have been linked to electronic warfare activities from Kaliningrad, including jamming and ‘spoofing’ of GPS signals, primarily affecting the Baltic States. These activities have disrupted civil aviation.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The EW center of the Baltic Fleet, under Kulikov’s commands, has received jamming equipment and conducted exercises using advanced systems capable of disrupting communications over large areas, and is also involved in planning, supporting and executing coordinated information manipulation and interference that impacts Union Member States.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Vitaly Kulikov is responsible for planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference which directly affects Union</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States. 15.7.2025 45. Yuri Illarionovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">LASTOCHKIN (Russian: Юрий</p>
<p xml:lang="myv">Илларионович</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ЛАСТОЧКИН</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian: Юрій</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Iлларіонович</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">ЛАСТОЧКIН)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Official of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ministry of Defense of the Russian Federation;</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Military Leader;</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">General-</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Major/Lieutenant</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">General; Chief of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electronic Warfare</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Forces of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation/head of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Defense</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Ministry’s Radio-</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electronic Warfare (REB) force</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 18.8.1967</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">POB: Rzhavka, Mogilev region, Belarusian SSR (now Belarus)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lieutenant General Yuri Lastochkin is the chief of the Electronic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Warfare (EW) Forces of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation. Yuri</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lastochkin oversees actions and exercises of Russia’s EW troops, including those of the 841st</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Separate EW center in the</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Kaliningrad region.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Recently, GPS signal failures in several European countries have been linked to electronic warfare activities from Kaliningrad, including jamming and ‘spoofing’ of GPS signals, primarily affecting the Baltic States. These activities have disrupted civil aviation.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The 841st Separate EW center in the Kaliningrad region, under 15.7.2025 33</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lastochkin’s commands, has received jamming equipment and conducted exercises using advanced systems capable of disrupting communications over large areas; it is also involved in planning, supporting and executing coordinated information manipulation and interference that impacts Union Member States.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Y. I. Lastochkin is responsible for planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference which directly affects Union</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States. 46. Yevgeny Shevchenko (Russian: Евгений</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">ШЕВЧЕНКО)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Founder of</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TigerWeb</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tax identification number: 910202780107</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yevgeny Shevchenko is a web developer who has specialised in creating websites for many years.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">He is the founder of Tigerweb, the web-company that runs the informational manipulation set ‘Portal Kombat’ which disseminates pro-Russian content and targets several Western countries, including France, on several so-called ‘informational portals’. Therefore, he is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions and policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which threaten the stability and security in the Union, or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15.7.2025 47.</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Aleksey Nikolayevich SHAVROV (Russian: Алексей Николаевич ШАВРОВ) a.k.a. Andrey PETROV (Russian: Андрей</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ПЕТРОВ)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Function: Military</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Intelligence Officer of the Main Directorate of the General Staff of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Armed Forces of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation (GRU)</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">DOB: 12.12.1989</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nationality: Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Gender: male</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aleksey Shavrov is a GRU officer involved in Russian influence operations directed to destabilise the Union and its Member States.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aleksey Shavrov's malign activities include information manipulation and disinformation campaigns in the Czech Republic and other</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union Member States. Through his concealed associate, Natallia</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sudliankova, Aleksey Shavrov conducts influence campaigns, including by organising the dissemination of tailor-made articles in various European media outlets. Misleading or outright false narratives aim to support the foreign policy interests of the 15.7.2025 34</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation and to spread its influence. Moreover, the content is designed to further undermine public trust in the Union values and processes, democracy and Union cohesion. Articles also contain specific manipulative anti-NATO, anti-Ukraine and anti-NGO narratives. Aleksey Shavrov instructed Natallia Sudliankova to spread and disseminate those divisive messages through media to amplify their polarising content.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aleksey Shavrov provided financial rewards for accomplishing tasks and for publication of those custom-made pro-Russian media campaigns.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Aleksey Shavrov is implementing actions or policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union or in third countries by planning and directing the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference.</p>
<p>B. Løgfrøðiligir persónar, eindir og stovnar</p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Name </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Identifying information Statement of reasons </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Date of listing </em>1. </p>
<p xml:lang="deu">GRU Unit 29155</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">ФКУ ‘Войсковая</p>
<p xml:lang="mdf">Часть 29155</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration: 105077, Moscow 11th</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Parkovaya Street, 38A</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration No: 7719737879</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">OGRN: 1097746770395</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GRU Unit 29155 is a covert unit within the Russian military intelligence agency (GRU), known for its involvement in foreign assassinations and destabilisation activities across Europe. Through coups, assassinations, bombings, and cyberattacks against other countries around the world in connection with the war in Ukraine, it has sought to create chaos and destabilise European Union countries. By carrying out such actions, it seeks to help and benefit</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia. GRU Unit 29155 carried out cyberattacks and other attacks against critical infrastructure.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, it is responsible for, implementing, supporting or benefiting from actions or policies by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union or in one or several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States by planning, directing, 16.12.2024 35engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating acts of violence, as well as planning, directing, engaging in, supporting or otherwise facilitating any actions aimed at interfering with, damaging or destroying, including through sabotage or malicious cyber activities as part of hybrid activities, critical infrastructure. 2.</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Groupe Panafricain pour le Commerce et l’Investissement</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GPCI</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lomé, Togo</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">January 2022</p>
<p xml:lang="fra"><em type="italic">Groupe Panafricain pour le </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="italic">Commerce et l’Investissement </em>(GPCI) is a disinformation network carrying out pro-Russian covert influence operations, particularly in the </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Central African Republic and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Burkina Faso. GPCI was dismantled by Meta in May 2023.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Despite this, GPCI is still active and is running structured and coordinated disinformation campaigns with the use of a vast network of information chains.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Those campaigns target France in particular, including through accusations of conspiracy, terrorism, destabilisation operations or preparing coups against the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or its Member States. GPCI has been indirectly funded by the</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Wagner Group.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, GPCI is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions or policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, stability or security in the Union or in one or several of its Member States by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 16.12.2024 3.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">African Initiative</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of Registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moscow, Russia</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">September 2023</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">African Initiative is a news agency that operates on the African continent. It has been involved in spreading Russian propaganda and disinformation against the West, and has hired journalists and influencers for the purpose of spreading Russian propaganda. It has also organised press tours for</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">African journalists in the illegally occupied territories of Ukraine, during which pro-Russian 16.12.2024 36narratives about the war were spread. African Initiative has also organised events serving the interests of the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation, including by facilitating access to mineral resources.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, African Initiative is responsible for or supporting actions and policies by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability and security in the Union or in one or several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States or in a third country by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 4.</p>
<p xml:lang="smj">AFA Media aka RED</p>
<p xml:lang="hbs">AFA Medya Anonim</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Șirketi aka RED</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">AFA Медиа</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Kavacık</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Mahallesi, Fatih Sultan</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Mehmet Caddesi,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tonoglu Block No.: 3,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Beykoz, Istanbul,</p>
<p xml:lang="kmr">Türkiye</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: media company</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Istanbul</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 22.11.2022</p>
<p xml:lang="est">VAT Nr.: 0081804196</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number 423277-5</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Principle place of business: Türkiye</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Website: https://thered.stream/imprint/</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Founder: Hüseyin Dogru</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">AFA Medya A.Ș. is a media company based in Istanbul. AFA</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medya A.Ș. operates <span type="quote" xml:lang="deu">“RED”</span>, which comprises a number of media platforms, and which has close financial and organisational connections with Russian state propaganda entities and actors, and which shares deep structural ties including interlinkages between, and rotation of, individual personnel with Russian state media organisations.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RED has used its media platforms – often publishing under <span type="quote" xml:lang="ron">“redstreamnet”</span> or <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“thered.stream”</span> – to systematically spread false information on politically controversial subjects with the intent of creating ethnic, political and religious discord amongst its predominantly German target audience, including by disseminating the narratives of radical Islamic terrorist groups such as Hamas.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">During the violent occupation of a German university by anti-Israel rioters, Red personnel coordinated with the occupiers to disseminate their vandalism – which included the use of Hamas symbols – through RED’s online channels, thus providing them with an exclusive media platform.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">AFA Medya Anonim Șirketi thus supports actions by the Government of the Russian Federation that 20.5.2025 37undermine stability and security in the Union and in one or several of its Member States, including by indirectly supporting and facilitating violent demonstrations and engaging in information manipulation. 5.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Voice of Europe (Russian: Голос</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Европы)</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Address: Krakovská 583/9, 110 00 Prague,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Czech Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Website: www.voiceofeurope.com, www.voiceofeurope.eu</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: Limited</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Liability Company (s.r.o.)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="ita">Prague</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 14.3.2023</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">CZ05185327</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Principal place of business: Czech</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Republic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Voice of Europe is an online media outlet, engaged in a systematic international campaign of media manipulation and distortion of facts through its website and accounts on</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Facebook, YouTube, Telegram and</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">X. Voice of Europe disseminated concerted disinformation related to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine, the Union and its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States with the aim of supporting the foreign policy interests of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation. It systematically undermined the public image of Ukraine and its efforts to defend itself against</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia’s war of aggression, and the credibility of the assistance of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union and its Member States to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukraine’s defence, including ahead of the 2024 European Parliament elections.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Through its activities, Voice of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe is implementing and supporting actions or policies of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in the Union and in Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty or independence of several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States, through engaging in and otherwise facilitating the obstruction or undermining of the democratic political process, including the 2024 European</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parliament elections, and through engaging in the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Voice of Europe was secretly financed and directed by Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk, a pro-Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian politician and businessperson with close ties to the leadership of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation, through his associate</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Artem Marchevskyi. Voice of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Europe was used to funnel financial resources designated for the remuneration of propagandists and the building an influence network connecting Medvedchuk and his 20.5.2025 38associates with representatives of political parties in Europe.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Voice of Europe was involved in activities facilitating the construction of Viktor</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medvedchuk’s influence network in the Union and its Member States. 6.</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Norebo JSC</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Office 510, 43</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Schmidta Street, 183038</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Murmansk, Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: Joint</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Stock Company</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Murmansk</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 2.11.2007</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number: 1201000007889</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">TIN / KPP: 2901170107 / 519001001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Norebo JSC is a Russian fishing company. Vessels owned and operated by Norebo JSC show particular movement patterns that are inconsistent with regular economic practices and fishing activities. The movement patterns align with malign objectives, such as repeatedly being in the vicinity of or loitering near critical infrastructure and military sites.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The movement patterns have been linked, including by Member States and the authorities of third states, to the Russian state-sponsored surveillance campaign that employs inter alia, civilian fishing trawlers, to conduct espionage missions directed against civilian and military infrastructure in the North and Baltic Sea. Those activities can facilitate future sabotage operations. Shipping vessels owned and operated by Norebo JSC have also been equipped with technology that may be used for espionage.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">A Norebo JSC vessel has been banned from entering Dutch port facilities due to espionage.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Norebo JSC has also received several loans from Sberbank, a Russian state-owned bank.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moreover, in July 2022, Russia released its new <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“maritime doctrine”</span>, which emphasises the strategic importance of civilian ships and their crews for maritime readiness, including by preparing them for wartime, and allowing them to be used by the armed forces in peace time.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Norebo JSC thus implements and supports actions by the Government of the Russian Federation, which undermine or threaten the security in the Union, several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States and third countries by engaging in and supporting actions aimed at interfering with critical infrastructure, including submarine infrastructure. 20.5.2025 397.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Murman SeaFood (Russian: Мурман</p>
<p xml:lang="myv">СиФуд, Мурманские морепродукты)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: Ulitsa Karla</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Marksa, 28, Murmansk,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Murmansk Oblast,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation, 183025</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: limited liability company</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="vep">Murmansk</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Murman SeaFood (MSF) is a Russian fishing company.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Melkart-5 (Russian: Мелькарт-5), a vessel owned and operated by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MSF, has repeatedly shown untypical behaviour inconsistent with its regular economic practices and fishing activities, including its presence in close vicinity to an ongoing NATO military exercise, and regular presence close to</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Norwegian critical infrastructure and military sites. In particular</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Melkart-5 showed highly unusual navigation practices in the immediate vicinity of a subsea cable in the Norwegian North Sea, crossing the cable multiple times, immediately before the cable was severely damaged. In addition, crew of Melkart-5 violated Norwegian on-shoring regulations while being caught setting off to investigate a Norwegian bridge critical for military logistic purposes in a clandestine manner.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moreover, in July 2022, Russia released its new <span type="quote" xml:lang="eng">“maritime doctrine”</span>, which emphasises the strategic importance of civilian ships and their crews for maritime readiness, including by preparing them for wartime, and allowing them to be used by the armed forces in peace time.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">MSF thus implements and supports actions by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten the security in the Union, several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States and third countries by engaging in and supporting actions aimed at interfering with critical infrastructure, including submarine infrastructure. 20.5.2025 8.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federal State Unitary</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Enterprise “Main</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Radio Frequency</p>
<p xml:lang="ron">Centre”</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">General Radio</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Frequency Centre</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">GRFC</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Федеральное</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Государственное</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Унитарное</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Предприятие “Главный</p>
<p xml:lang="rus">Радиочастотный</p>
<p xml:lang="mns">Центр”</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 7,</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Derbenevskaya nab. 7 p.,</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Moscow 115114. 15 115114, город Москва,</p>
<p xml:lang="koi">Дербеневская наб, д. 7 стр. 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: Federal agency</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moscow, Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 30.3.2001</p>
<p xml:lang="ita">BIN: 1027739334479</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The General Radio Frequency</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Centre (GRFC) is responsible for ensuring the proper use of radio frequencies and devices for civil purposes, and monitors compliance with legislation. It is one of the main organisations which contribute to decisions about the use and supervision of the radio frequency sector.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Recently, GPS signal failures in several European countries have been linked to electronic warfare activities from Kaliningrad, 20.5.2025 40</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ФГУП <span type="quote" xml:lang="udm">“ГРЧЦ”</span></p>
<p xml:lang="eng">INN: 7706228218</p>
<p xml:lang="tur">KPP: 772501001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Principal place of business: Russia including jamming and spoofing of</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">GPS signals, primarily affecting the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Baltic States. These activities have disrupted civil aviation. The repression of GPS signals requires the permission of the GRFC.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The electronic warfare centre in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kaliningrad has received new jamming equipment and conducted exercises using advanced systems capable of disrupting communications over large areas.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, GRFC is responsible for, planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating actions or policies by the Government of the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation which undermine or threaten stability or security in the Union or in several of its Member States through engaging in actions which are targeted at the functioning of critical infrastructure and through supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 9.</p>
<p xml:lang="isl">Stark Industries</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Solutions Ltd.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 10.2.2022</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 71-75 Shelton</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Street, Covent Garden,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">London, United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom (maildrop address)</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number: 13906017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Website: https://stark-industries.solutions/</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Website: https://pq.hosting/</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stark Industries Solutions Ltd. is a web hosting service registered as a maildrop company in the United</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kingdom. Stark Industries</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Solutions Ltd. is owned and operated by the Moldavian nationals Ivan Neculiti and Iurie</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Neculiti, through the web hosting service PQ Hosting. The company provides server hosting, with server locations all over the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stark enables various Russian state-sponsored and state-affiliated actors to conduct destabilising activities, including coordinated information manipulation and interference and cyber-attacks against the Union and third countries, by providing services intended to hide those activities from European law enforcement and security agencies.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Stark Industries</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Solutions Ltd. is supporting actions by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which threaten democracy and the rule of law, stability or security in the Union, in one of its Member States and a third country, by facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference and by facilitating actions targeted at 20.5.2025 41the functioning of democratic institutions, economic activities or services of public interest.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stark is associated with Ivan</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Neculiti and Iurie Neculiti. 10.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federal State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian Television and Radio Broadcasting Network’ (RTRS); Федеральное государственное унитарное предприятие ‘Российская телевизионная и радиовещательная сеть’</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 13, Korolyov street, Moscow, Russia</p>
<p xml:lang="fkv">Website: https://moscow.rtrs.ru/</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration: 13,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Korolyov street,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Moscow, Russia</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 30.11.2001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number:</p>
<p xml:lang="mns">ИНН: 7717127211;</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">ОГРН: 1027739456084</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The Federal State-owned Enterprise ‘Russian Television and Radio</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Broadcasting Network’ (RTRS) operatеs Russia’s terrestrial broadcasting infrastructure. It is directly subordinated to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ministry of Digital Development,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Communications and Mass Media of the Russian Federation and operates under the authority of a general director appointed by the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian President. RTRS provides infrastructure and technical capabilities for the transmission of the so called ‘All-Russian mandatory publicly available television and radio channels’ such as Pervyi Kanal or Rossiya 24.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">RTRS plays a key role in effectively replacing legacy</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian broadcasting systems in occupied regions with a network that transmits content approved by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation intended to suppress dissent, to align the local population with Russian policies and to delegitimise Ukraine’s governance in the occupied territories. This directly undermines the ability of local populations to access diverse and independent information. The expansion of RTRS operations into the occupied regions is facilitated by the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which grants RTRS the right to establish transmission infrastructure there.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, RTRS is implementing and benefiting from policies attributable to the Government of the Russian Federation which undermine or threaten democracy and stability in Ukraine, and which undermine the sovereignty or independence of Ukraine, through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of information manipulation and interference. 15.7.2025 11. 841st Separate</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electronic Warfare</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Center of the Baltic</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Fleet</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Address: 238580,</p>
<p xml:lang="est">Kaliningrad oblast,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yantarny settlement,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Balebin street, 09643</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The 841st Separate Electronic</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Warfare Center is at the core of one of the strongest electronic warfare groups in Russia. The centre is 15.7.2025 42841-й центр радиоэлектронной борьбы 238580,</p>
<p xml:lang="myv">Калининградская обл., пгт.Янтарный, ул.Балебина, в/ч 09643</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Type of entity: Military unit</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration:</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kalininingrad region,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russian Federation</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Phone number: 8(40153)37-244</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Military unit 09643 responsible for using technology to disorganise any system of shortwave communication, conducting electronic warfare exercises (EW) to disrupt enemy navigation and radio communications as well as for the collection and analysis of intelligence information obtained by observing electromagnetic radiation in the short and ultrashort wave ranges.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Several European countries have experienced GPS signal failures, which have been attributed to electronic warfare activities by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Russia, specifically from</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kaliningrad. This includes deliberate jamming and ‘spoofing’ of GPS signals, primarily affecting the Baltic States. Interference and manipulation of GPS signals has led to obstacles for landing civil planes.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The 841st Separate EW Center in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Kaliningrad has received jamming equipment and conducted exercises using advanced systems capable of disrupting communications over large areas.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, 841st Separate EW</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Center, as part of Russia’s military forces enabling the misuse of radio frequency sector, is responsible for engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference which directly affects Union</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States. 12.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">BRICS Journalist</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Association</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Website: bricspress.live</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The BRICS Journalists Association (BJA) is a Russian NGO linked to the Foundation to Battle Injustice (R-FBI), created by Yevgeny</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Prigozhin, and headed by Oksana</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vovk (Mira Terada). The BJA has been used as a vehicle to disseminate pro-Russian narratives and disinformation under the guise of independent journalism, including fake content originating from the Storm-1516 Information</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Manipulation Set (IMS).</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, the BJA is responsible for, implementing, supporting and benefitting from actions and policies attributable to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or 15.7.2025 43threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union, or in one or several of its</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Member States or in a third country through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 13.</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Center for Geopolitical</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Expertise</p>
<p xml:lang="udm">Центр геополитических экспертиз, CGE</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Website: cge.evrazia.ru, cge.su</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration: Ul.</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Dinamovskaya D.1a,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Office 409, Moscow,</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">RUS, 109044</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 17.12.2002</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number: 1027739806940</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The Center for Geopolitical</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Expertise (CGE) is a Moscow-based think tank founded by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Aleksandr Dugin, and headed by</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Valery Korovin, accused of orchestrating disinformation campaigns aimed at targeting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ukrainian interests, discrediting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Western political figures, and influencing electoral processes in</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Western countries. CGE and its director, Valery Mikhaylovich</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Korovin, are reportedly involved in creating and disseminating false information by utilising artificial intelligence tools to produce deepfake videos, and supporting a network of hundreds of fake news websites. CGE is alleged to have worked closely with Russia’s military intelligence agency (GRU), receiving financial support to carry out these operations.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, the CGE is responsible for, implementing, supporting and benefitting from actions and policies attributable to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten the democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Union or in third countries, by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15.7.2025 14.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Foundation to Battle</p>
<p xml:lang="fra">Injustice</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of creation: 23.3.2021</p>
<p xml:lang="nno">Website: fondfbr.ru</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">The Foundation to Battle Injustice (R-FBI) is a fake human-rights defence NGO created in March 2021 by Wagner group founder</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Yevgeny Prigozhin. The R-FBI has been involved in numerous information operations targeting</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">France and Ukraine, including a campaign accusing French soldiers of having kidnapped children from Niger just after the military coup d’état in 2023. Since the death of Yevgeny Prigozhin in 15.7.2025 44</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">August 2023, the R-FBI has been involved in the amplification of numerous Storm-1516’s information operations.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, the R-FBI is responsible for, implementing and supporting actions and policies attributable to the Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which undermine or threaten democracy, the rule of law, stability or security in the Union, or in one or several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States, or in third countries, by planning, directing, engaging in, directly or indirectly, supporting or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15.</p>
<p xml:lang="deu">Tigerweb</p>
<p xml:lang="sme">Website: Tigerweb.ru</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Place of registration: 295000, Krim Republic,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Simferopol City,</p>
<p xml:lang="nob">Oktyabirskaya Street, 3,</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Office 408</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Date of registration: 2019</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registration number: 1199112018973</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tigerweb is the Russian Crimea-based web-company that operates the informational manipulation project ‘Portal Kombat’, which disseminates pro-Russian content and targets several Western countries, including France, through various so-called ‘informational portals’.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Therefore, Tigerweb is involved in the implementation of actions and policies attributable to the</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Government of the Russian</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Federation which threaten the stability and security in the Union, or in one or several of its Member</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">States, or in third countries, through engaging in or otherwise facilitating the use of coordinated information manipulation and interference. 15.7.2025 ” 45</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 3 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="vep"><em type="bold">Skjal 1 B </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Listi við likamligum og løgfrøðiligum persónum, samsvarandi fylgiskjali I til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 2024/2642 </em></p>
<p>Samanskrivaði listin hjá Evropasamveldinum við likamligum og løgfrøðiligum persónum, sum eru fevnd av avmarkandi tiltøkunum sambært § 3 a, samsvarandi fylgiskjali I til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 2024/2642, sæst á heimasíðuni hjá Uttanríkis- og mentamálaráðnum, www.ummr.fo ” 46</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 4 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 2 </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Listi við vørum, sum loyvt er at útflyta til Russlands samsvarandi § 13 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">CN Code </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Description </em>02 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Meat and edible meat offal 03</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Fish and crustaceans, molluscs and other aquatic invertebrates 04</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dairy produce; birds’ eggs; natural honey; edible products of animal origin; not elsewhere specified or included 05</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products of animal origin, not elsewhere specified or included ex 06</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Live trees and other plants; bulbs, roots and the like; cut flowers and ornamental foliage, excluding CN 0601 (Bulbs, tubers, tuberous roots, corms, crowns and rhizomes, dormant, in growth or in flower, chicory plants and roots other than roots of heading 1212:), 0602 30 (Rhododendrons and azaleas, grafted or not), 0602 40 (Roses, grafted or not), 0602 90 (Other live plants (including their roots), cuttings and slips; mushroom spawn –</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other), and 0604 20 (Foliage, branches and other parts of plants, without flowers or flower buds, and grasses, mosses and lichens, being goods of a kind suitable for bouquets or for ornamental purposes, fresh, dried, dyed, bleached, impregnated or otherwise prepared – Fresh). ex 07</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Edible vegetables and certain roots and tubers, excluding CN 0709 56 00 (Truffles), 0710 80 69 (Other), 0711 59 00 (Other), 0712 39 00 (Other). 08</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Edible fruit and nuts; peel of citrus fruit and melons 09</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Coffee, tea, maté and spices 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cereals 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products of the milling industry; malt; starches; inulin, wheat gluten 12</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oil seeds and oleaginous fruits; miscellaneous grains, seeds and fruit; industrial or medicinal plants; straw and fodder 13</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lac; grums; resins and other vegetable saps and extracts 14</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Vegetable plaiting materials; vegetable products not elsewhere specified or included 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Animal or vegetable fats and oils and their cleavage products; prepared edible fats; animal or vegetable waxes ex 16</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of meat, of fish or of crustaceans, molluscs or other aquatic invertebrates, excluding CN 1604 31 00 (Caviar) and 1604 32 00 (Caviar substitutes) 17</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sugars and sugar confectionery 18</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cocoa and cocoa preparations 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of cereals, flour, starch or milk; pastrycooks’ products ex 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations of vegetables, fruit, nuts or other parts of plants, excluding 2001 90 97 (Other) and 2003 90 10 (Truffles) ex 21</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Miscellaneous edible preparations, excluding CN 2103 90 90 (Other), 2104 10 00 (Soups and broths and preparations therefor), 2104 20 00 (Homogenised composite food preparations), and 2106 00 00 (Food preparations not elsewhere specified or included) ex 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Beverages, spirits and vinegar, excluding CN 2203 00 00 (Beer made from malt), 2204 10 11 (Champagne), 2204 10 91 (Asti spurmante), 2204 10 93 (Other), 2204 10 94 (With a protected geographical indication (PGI)), 2204 10 96 (Other varietal wines), 472204 10 98 (Other), 2204 21 00 (In containers holding 2 litres or less), 2204 29 00 (Other), 2205 00 00 (Vermouth and other wine of fresh grapes flavoured with plants or aromatic substances), 2206 00 00 (Other fermented beverages (for example, cider, perry, mead, saké); mixtures of fermented beverages and mixtures of fermented beverages with non-alcoholic beverages, not elsewhere specified or included), 2207 10 00 (Undenatured ethyl alcohol of an alcoholic strength by volume of 80 % vol or higher), and 2208 00 00 (Undenatured ethyl alcohol of an alcoholic strength by volume of less than 80 % vol; spirits, liqueurs and other spirituous beverages) 23</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Residues and waste from the food industries; prepared animal fodder ex 24</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tobacco and manufactured tobacco substitutes, excluding CN 2402 10 00 (Cigars, cheroots and cigarillos, containing tobacco) and 2402 90 00 (Other) 2505</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural sands of all kinds, whether or not coloured, other than metal-bearing sands of Chapter 26 2707</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Oils and other products of the distillation of high temperature coal tar; similar products in which the weight of the aromatic constituents exceeds that of the non-aromatic constituents, excluding 2707 30 (Xylol (xylenes)) 2710 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Medium oils and preparations, of petroleum or bituminous minerals, not containing biodiesel, n.e.s. 2711</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Petroleum gases and other gaseous hydrocarbons 2716</p>
<p xml:lang="spa">Electrical energy 2853</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Phosphides, whether or not chemically defined, excluding ferrophosphorus; other inorganic compounds (including distilled or conductivity water and water of similar purity); liquid air (whether or not rare gases have been removed); compressed air; amalgams, other than amalgams of precious metals 2932</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Heterocyclic compounds with oxygen hetero-atom(s) only 3005</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wadding, gauze, bandages and the like, e.g. dressings, adhesive plasters, poultices, impregnated or covered with pharmaceutical substances or put up for retail sale for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes 3006</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pharmaceutical preparations and products of subheadings 3006 10 10 to 3006 93 00 3215 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Ink, whether or not concentrated or solid (excl. printing ink) 3401</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for use as soap, in the form of bars, cakes, moulded pieces or shapes, whether or not containing soap; organic surface-active products and preparations for washing the skin, in the form of liquid or cream and put up for retail sale, whether or not containing soap; paper, wadding, felt and nonwovens, impregnated, coated or covered with soap or detergent 3402</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Organic surface-active agents (other than soap); surface-active preparations, washing preparations (including auxiliary washing preparations) and cleaning preparations, whether or not containing soap, other than those of heading 3401 3503</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gelatin (including gelatin in rectangular (including square) sheets, whether or not surface-worked or coloured) and gelatin derivatives; isinglass; other glues of animal origin, excluding casein glues of heading 3501 3506 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Products suitable for use as glues or adhesives, put up for retail sale as glues or adhesives, not exceeding a net weight of 1 kg 3506 91</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Adhesives based on polymers of headings 3901 to 3913 or on rubber (excl. put up for retail sale with a net weight of &lt;= 1 kg) 3801</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Artificial graphite; colloidal or semi-colloidal graphite; preparations based on graphite or other carbon in the form of pastes, blocks, plates or other semi-manufactures, excluding CN 3801 20 (colloidal or semi-colloidal graphite) 483822</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Diagnostic or laboratory reagents on a backing, prepared diagnostic or laboratory reagents whether or not on a backing, other than those of heading 3002 or 3006; certified reference materials 3901</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Polymers of ethylene, in primary forms, excluding CN 3901 40 (ethylene-alpha-olefin copolymers, having a specific gravity of &lt; 0,94, in primary forms) and 3208 (solutions of products of headings 3901 to 3913 in volatile organic solvents, containing &gt; 50 % solvent by weight (excl. solutions of collodion)) 3907 30</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Epoxide resins, in primary forms 3919</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Self-adhesive plates, sheets, film, foil, tape, strip and other flat shapes, of plastics, whether or not in rolls 3923</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles for the conveyance or packing of goods, of plastics; stoppers, lids, caps and other closures, of plastics 3924</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tableware, kitchenware, other household articles and hygienic or toilet articles, of plastics 3926</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of plastics and articles of other materials of heading 3901 to 3914, n.e.s., excluding CN 3926 90 4001</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural rubber, balata, gutta-percha, guayule, chicle and similar natural gums, in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip 4003</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Reclaimed rubber in primary forms or in plates, sheets or strip 4004</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Waste, parings and scrap of rubber (other than hard rubber) and powders and granules obtained therefrom 4006</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other forms (for example, rods, tubes and profile shapes) and articles (for example, discs and rings), of unvulcanised rubber, excluding CN 4006 10 (‘camel-back’ strips of unvulcanised rubber, for retreading rubber tyres) 4009</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber other than hard rubber, with or without their fittings (for example, joints, elbows, flanges), excluding CN 4009 12 (tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber), not reinforced or otherwise) and 4009 41 (tubes, pipes and hoses, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber), reinforced or otherwise combined with materials other than metal or textile materials, without fittings) 4011</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, excluding CN 4011 20 (New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, of a kind used for buses and lorries) and 4011 80 (New pneumatic tyres, of rubber, of a kind used on construction, mining or industrial handling vehicles and machines) 4015 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gloves, mittens and mitts, of a kind used for medical, surgical, dental or veterinary purposes, of vulcanised rubber 4016</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other articles of vulcanised rubber other than hard rubber, excluding 4016 93 (gaskets, washers and other seals, of vulcanised rubber (excl. hard rubber and those of cellular rubber)) 4415</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Packing cases, boxes, crates, drums and similar packings, of wood; cable-drums of wood; pallets, box pallets and other load boards, of wood; pallet collars of wood (excl. containers specially designed and equipped for one or more modes of transport) 4802 56</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Packing cases, boxes, crates, drums and similar packings, of wood; cable-drums of wood; pallets, box pallets and other load boards, of wood; pallet collars of wood (excl. containers specially designed and equipped for one or more modes of transport) 4802 62</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Uncoated paper and paperboard, of a kind used for writing, printing or other graphic purposes, and non-perforated punchcards and punch-tape paper, in square or rectangular sheets with one side &lt;= 435 mm and the other side &lt;= 297 mm in the unfolded state, of which &gt; 10% by weight of the total fibre content consists of fibres obtained by a mechanical or chemi-mechanical process, n.e.s. 4818</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Toilet paper and similar paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres, of a kind used for household or sanitary purposes, in rolls of a width &lt;= 36 cm, or cut to size or shape; handkerchiefs, cleansing tissues, towels, tablecloths, serviettes, bedsheets and similar household, sanitary or hospital articles, articles of apparel and clothing accessories, of paper pulp, paper, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres 494819</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Cartons, boxes, cases, bags and other packing containers, of paper, paperboard, cellulose wadding or webs of cellulose fibres; box files, letter trays, and similar articles, of paper or paperboard of a kind used in offices, shops or the like, excluding 4819 20 (folding cartons, boxes and cases, of non-corrugated paper or paperboard) 4820</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Registers, account books, notebooks, order books, receipt books, letter pads, memorandum pads, diaries and similar articles, exercise books, blotting pads, binders, folders, file covers, manifold business forms, interleaved carbon sets and other articles of stationery, of paper or paperboard; albums for samples or for collections and book covers, of paper and paperboard 4821</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Paper or paperboard labels of all kinds, whether or not printed 5602</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Felt, whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or laminated, n.e.s. 5603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nonwovens, whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or laminated, n.e.s. 5607</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Twine, cordage, ropes and cables, whether or not plaited or braided and whether or not impregnated, coated, covered or sheathed with rubber or plastics, excluding CN 5607 41 (binder or baler twine, of polyethylene or polypropylene) 5608</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Knotted netting of twine, cordage or rope, by the piece or metre; made-up fishing nets and other made-up nets, of textile materials (excl. hairnets, nets for sporting purposes, incl. landing nets, butterfly nets and the like) 5902</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tyre cord fabric of high-tenacity yarn of nylon or other polyamides, polyesters or viscose rayon, whether or not dipped or impregnated with rubber or plastic 5909</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Textile hosepiping and similar textile tubing, whether or not impregnated or coated, with or without lining, armour or accessories of other materials 5911 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Textile products and articles, for technical purposes, specified in Note 7 to chapter 59, n.e.s. 6302</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Bedlinen, table linen, toilet linen and kitchen linen of all types of textile materials (excl. floorcloths, polishing cloths, dishcloths and dusters) 6305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Sacks and bags, of a kind used for the packing of goods, of all types of textile materials 6306</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Tarpaulins, awnings and sunblinds; tents; sails for boats, sailboards or landcraft; camping goods of all types of textile materials (excl. flat protective coverings of light woven fabrics; umbrella and play tents; rucksacks, napsacks and similar containers; sleeping bags, mattresses and pillows, incl. their fillings) 6307</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Made-up articles of textile materials, incl. dress patterns, n.e.s. 6310</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Used or new rags, scrap twine, cordage, rope and cables and worn-out articles thereof, of textile materials 6406</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts of footwear, incl. uppers whether or not attached to soles other than outer soles; removable in-soles, heel cushions and similar articles; gaiters, leggings and similar articles, and parts thereof (excl. articles of asbestos) 6505</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hats and other headgear, knitted or crocheted, or made up from lace, felt or other textile fabric, in the piece (but not in strips), whether or not lined or trimmed; hairnets of any material, whether or not lined or trimmed 6506 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Headgear, whether or not lined or trimmed, n.e.s. 6804 21</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Millstones, grindstones, grinding wheels and the like, without frameworks, for sharpening, polishing, trueing or cutting, of agglomerated synthetic or natural diamond (excl. hand sharpening or polishing stones, and grinding wheels etc. specifically for dental drill engines) 6804 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Millstones, grindstones, grinding wheels and the like, without frameworks, for sharpening, polishing, trueing or cutting, of agglomerated abrasives or ceramics (excl. of agglomerated synthetic or natural diamond, hand sharpening or polishing stones, perfumed pumice stones, and grinding wheels etc. specifically for dental drill engines) 6805</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Natural or artificial abrasive powder or grain, on a base of textile material, paper, paperboard or other materials, whether or not cut to shape or sewn or otherwise made up 6903</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Retorts, crucibles, mufflers, nozzles, plugs, supports, cupels, tubes, pipes, sheaths, rods, slide gates and other refractory ceramic goods (excl. those of siliceous fossil meals or of similar siliceous earths, and refractory bricks, blocks, tiles and similar refractory ceramic constructional goods) 507019</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Glass fibres, incl. glass wool, and articles thereof (excl. mineral wools and articles thereof, optical fibres, fibre bundles or cable, electrical insulators or parts thereof, brushes of glass fibres, dolls' wigs) 7312</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Stranded wire, ropes, cables, plaited bands, slings and the like, of iron or steel (excl. electrically insulated products and twisted fencing wire and barbed wire) 7315</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Chain and parts thereof, or iron or steel (excl. watch chains, necklace chains and the like, cutting and saw chain, skid chain, scraper chain for conveyors, toothed chain for textile machinery and the like, safety devices with chains for securing doors, measuring chains) 7317</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Nails, tacks, drawing pins, corrugated nails, staples and similar articles of iron or steel, whether or not with heads of other material (excl. such articles with heads of copper and staples in strips) 7318 15</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Threaded screws and bolts, of iron or steel, whether or not with their nuts and washers (excl. coach screws and other wood screws, screw hooks and screw rings, self-tapping screws, lag screws, stoppers, plugs and the like, threaded) 7318 19</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Threaded articles, of iron or steel, n.e.s. 7318 22</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Washers of iron or steel (excl. spring washers and other lock washers) 7318 29</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Non-threaded articles, of iron or steel 7326</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of iron or steel, n.e.s. (excl. cast articles) 7403</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Copper, refined, and copper alloys, unwrought (excl. copper alloys of heading 7405) 7415 33</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Screws, bolts, nuts and similar articles, threaded, of copper (other than screw hooks, ring- and eyebolts, lag screws, plugs, bungs and the like, with screw thread) 8202 31</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Circular saw blades, incl. slitting or slotting saw blades, of base metal, with working parts of steel 8202 91</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Straight saw blades, of base metal, for working metal 8203</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Files, rasps, pliers, incl. cutting pliers, pincers and tweezers for non-medical use, metal-cutting shears, pipe-cutters, bolt croppers, perforating punches and similar hand tools, of base metal 8204</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hand-operated spanners and wrenches, incl. torque meter wrenches (excl. tap wrenches), of base metal; interchangeable spanner sockets, with or without handles, of base metal 8205</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hand tools, incl. glaziers' diamonds, of base metal, n.e.s.; blowlamps and the like; vices, clamps and the like (other than accessories for and parts of machine-tools or water-jet cutting machines); anvils; portable forges; hand-operated or pedal-operated grinding wheels with frameworks 8211</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Knives with cutting blades, serrated or not, incl. pruning knives, and blades therefor, of base metal (excl. straw knives, machetes, knives and cutting blades for machines or mechanical appliances, fish knives, butter knives, razors and razor blades and knives of heading 8214) 8305</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Fittings for loose-leaf binders or files, letter clips, letter corners, paper clips, indexing tags and similar office articles, of base metal (excl. drawing pins and clasps for books or registers); staples in strips, e.g. for use in offices, upholstery and packaging, of base metal 8308</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Clasps, frames with clasps, buckles, buckle-clasps, hooks, eyes, eyelets and the like, of base metal, of a kind used for clothing, footwear, awnings, handbags, travel goods or other made-up articles, tubular or bifurcated rivets, of base metal; beads and spangles of base metal 8311</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Wire, rods, tubes, plates, electrodes and similar products, of base metal or of metal carbides, coated or cored with flux material, of a kind used for soldering, brazing, welding or deposition of metal or of metal carbides; wire and rods, of agglomerated base metal powder, used for metal spraying 8414</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Air or vacuum pumps, air or other gas compressors and fans; ventilating or recycling hoods incorporating a fan, whether or not fitted with filters; gas-tight biological safety cabinets, whether or not fitted with filters, excluding 8414 10 (vacuum pumps), 8418 10 81 (cryogenic pumps in the LNG-process) and 8414 90 (Parts) 8418</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Refrigerators, freezers and other refrigerating or freezing equipment, electric or other; heat pumps other than air conditioning machines of heading 84.15 and excluding 8418 69 00 (Process units for gas cooling in the LNG-process), excluding CN 8418 99 518422</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Dish washing machines; machinery for cleaning or drying bottles or other containers; machinery for filling, closing, sealing or labelling bottles, cans, boxes, bags or other containers; machinery for capsuling bottles, jars, tubes and similar containers; other packing or wrapping machinery (including heat-shrink wrapping machinery); machinery for aerating beverages, excluding CN 8422 20 and 8422 30 8438</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machinery, not specified or included elsewhere in this chapter, for the industrial preparation or manufacture of food or drink (other than machinery for the extraction or preparation of animal or fixed vegetable fats or oils); parts thereof 8443 11</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Offset printing machinery, reel-fed 8443 14</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Letterpress printing machinery, reel fed, excluding flexographic printing 8443 99</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other. 8516 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric instantaneous or storage water heaters and immersion heaters 8516 40</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric smoothing irons 8516 79</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Electric instantaneous or storage water heaters and immersion heaters 8907</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Rafts, tanks, coffer-dams, landing stages, buoys, beacons and other floating structures (excl. vessels of heading 8901 to 8906 and floating structures for breaking up) 9001 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lenses, prisms, mirrors and other optical elements, of any material, unmounted (excl. such elements of glass not optically worked, contact lenses and spectacle lenses) 9002 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Lenses, prisms, mirrors and other optical elements, mounted, of any material, being parts of or fittings for instruments or apparatus (excl. objective lenses for cameras, projectors or photographic enlargers or reducers, such elements of glass not optically worked, and filters) 9017</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Drawing, marking-out or mathematical calculating instruments, e.g. drafting machines, pantographs, protractors, drawing sets, slide rules, disc calculators; instruments for measuring length, for use in the hand, e.g. measuring rods and tapes, micrometres, callipers and other gauges, not elsewhere specified in chapter 90 9025</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hydrometers and similar floating instruments, thermometers, pyrometers, barometers, hygrometers and psychrometers, recording or not, and any combination of these instruments, excluding CN 9025 90 (Parts and accessories for hydrometers, areometers and similar floating instruments, thermometers, pyrometers, barometers, hygrometers and psychrometers, n.e.s.) 9405</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Luminaires and lighting fittings, incl. searchlights and spotlights, and parts thereof, n.e.s; illuminated signs, illuminated nameplates and the like having a permanently fixed light source, and parts thereof, n.e.s. 9603</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Brooms, brushes, incl. brushes constituting parts of machines, appliances or vehicles, hand-operated mechanical floor sweepers, not motorised, mops and leather dusters; prepared knots and tufts for broom or brush making; paint pads and rollers; squeegees of rubber or similar flexible materials 9608 20</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Felt-tipped and other porous-tipped pens and markers 9608 40</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Propelling or sliding pencils ” 52</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 5 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Skjal 2 A </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng"><em type="bold">Listi við marglætisvørum, sum eru loyvdar at útflyta til Russlands samsvarandi treytunum í § 13 a 1) Perfumes, toilet waters and cosmetics, including beauty and make-up products </em>ex 3303 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Perfumes and toilet waters ex 3304 00 00 Beauty or make-up preparations and preparations for the care of the skin (other than medicaments), including sunscreen or suntan preparations; manicure or pedicure preparations ex 3305 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Preparations for use on the hair ex 3307 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pre-shave, shaving or aftershave preparations, personal deodorants, bath preparations, depilatories and other perfumery, cosmetic or toilet preparations, not elsewhere specified or included; prepared room deodorisers, whether or not perfumed or having disinfectant properties <em type="bold">2) Articles and equipment for sports, including skiing, golf, diving and water sports </em>ex 4015 19 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other ex 4015 90 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other ex 9020 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other breathing appliances and gas masks, excluding protective masks having neither mechanical parts nor replaceable filters <em type="bold">3) Leather, saddlery and travel goods, handbags and similar articles </em>ex 4202 00 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Trunks, suitcases, vanity cases, executive-cases, briefcases, school satchels, spectacle cases, binocular cases, camera cases, musical instrument cases, gun cases, holsters and similar containers; travelling-bags, insulated food or beverage bags, toilet bags, rucksacks, handbags, shopping-bags, wallets, purses, map-cases, cigarette-cases, tobacco-pouches, tool bags, sports bags, bottle-cases, jewellery boxes, powder-boxes, cutlery cases and similar containers, of leather or of composition leather, of sheeting of plastics, of textile materials, of vulcanised fibre or of paperboard, or wholly or mainly covered with such materials or with paper. <em type="bold">4) Coats, or other garments, clothing accessories and shoes (regardless of their material) </em>ex 4203 00 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Articles of apparel and clothing accessories, of leather or composition leather ex 6101 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks (including ski jackets), windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles, knitted or crocheted, other than those of heading 6103 ex 6102 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Women’s or girls’ overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks (including ski jackets), windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles, knitted or crocheted, other than those of heading 6104 ex 6103 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (other than swimwear), knitted or crocheted ex 6107 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ underpants, briefs, nightshirts, pyjamas, bathrobes, dressing gowns and similar articles, knitted or crocheted ex 6109 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">T-shirts, singlets and other vests, knitted or crocheted ex 6111 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Babies’ garments and clothing accessories, knitted or crocheted ex 6115 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Pantyhose, tights, stockings, socks and other hosiery, incl. graduated compression hosiery (e.g., stockings for varicose veins) and footwear without applied soles, knitted or crocheted 53ex 6116 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Gloves, mittens and mitts, knitted or crocheted ex 6201 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ overcoats, car coats, capes, cloaks, anoraks (incl. ski jackets), windcheaters, wind-jackets and similar articles, other than those of heading 6203 ex 6203 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Men’s or boys’ suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (other than swimwear) ex 6204 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Women’s or girls. suits, ensembles, jackets, blazers, dresses, skirts, divided skirts, trousers, bib and brace overalls, breeches and shorts (other than swimwear) ex 6211 33 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of man-made fibres ex 6211 39 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of other textile materials ex 6401 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Waterproof footwear with outer soles and uppers of rubber or of plastics, the uppers of which are neither fixed to the sole nor assembled by stitching, riveting, nailing, screwing, plugging or similar processes ex 6402 91 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Covering the ankle ex 6403 40 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other footwear, incorporating a protective metal toecap ex 6405 00 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other footwear ex 6505 00 10</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of fur felt or of felt of wool and fur, made from the hat bodies, hoods or plateaux of heading 6501 00 00 ex 6505 00 30</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Peaked caps ex 6505 00 90</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other <em type="bold">5) Carpets, rugs and tapestries, hand-made or not </em>ex 5702 91 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Carpets and other textile floor coverings, woven, not tufted or flocked, whether or not made up, incl. Kelem, Schumacks, Karamanie and similar hand-woven rugs of wool or fine animal hair <em type="bold">6) Electronic items for domestic use of a value not exceeding EUR 750 each </em>ex 8414 51 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Table, floor, wall, window, ceiling or roof fans, with a self-contained electric motor of an output not exceeding 125 W ex 8414 59 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other ex 8414 60 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Hoods having a maximum horizontal side not exceeding 120 cm ex 8418 10 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Combined refrigerator-freezers, fitted with separate external door ex 8418 21 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Compression-type ex 8418 29 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other ex 8418 30 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Freezers of the chest type, not exceeding 800 litres capacity ex 8418 40 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Freezers of the upright type, not exceeding 900 litres capacity ex 8422 11 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of the household type ex 8443 12 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Offset printing machinery, sheet fed, office type (using sheets with one side not exceeding 22 cm and the other side not exceeding 36 cm in the unfolded state) ex 8443 31 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Machines which perform two or more of the functions of printing, copying or facsimile transmission, capable of connecting to an automatic data-processing machine or to a network ex 8443 32 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other, capable of connecting to an automatic data-processing machine or to a network ex 8443 39 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Other ex 8508 11 00</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Of a power not exceeding 1 500 W and having a dust bag or other receptacle capacity not exceeding 20 l 54 <em type="bold">7) Vehicles, for the transport of persons on earth, air or sea of a value not exceeding EUR 50 000 each, teleferics, chairlifts, ski-draglines, traction mechanisms for funiculars, motorbikes of a value not exceeding EUR 5 000 each, as well as their accessories and spare parts </em>ex 8708 00 00 </p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Parts and accessories of the motor vehicles of headings 8701 to 8705 ” 55</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 6 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="est"><em type="bold">Skjal 6 A </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Listi við skipum, sum eru fevnd av § 15a, samsvarandi fylgiskjali XLII til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 833/2014 </em></p>
<p>Samanskrivaði listin hjá Evropasamveldinum við skipum, sum eru fevnd av § 15 a, samsvarandi fylgiskjali XLII til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 833/2014, sæst á heimasíðuni hjá Uttanríkis- og vinnmálaráðnum. ” 56</p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 7 </em>“ </p>
<p xml:lang="olo"><em type="bold">Skjal 15 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="isl"><em type="bold">Ritbúnaður, nevndur í § 9, stk. 2, samsvarandi fylgiskjal XXVI til fyriskipan Ráðsins nr. 765/2006 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Software for the management of enterprises, i.e. systems that digitally represent and steer all processes happening in an enterprise, including: — enterprise resource planning (ERP), — customer relationship management (CRM), — business intelligence (BI), — supply chain management (SCM), — enterprise data warehouse (EDW), — computerized maintenance management system (CMMS), — project management software, — product lifecycle management (PLM), — typical components of the above-mentioned suites, including software for accounting, fleet management, logistics and human resources.</p>
<p xml:lang="eng">Design and Manufacturing Software used in the areas of architecture, engineering, construction, manufacturing, media, education and entertainment, including: — building information modelling (BIM), — computer aided design (CAD), — computer-aided manufacturing (CAM), — engineer to order (ETO), — typical components of above-mentioned suites.” 57</p>
</body></document>
