<document xml:lang="fao" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>9254</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual><language xml:lang="dan"/></multilingual><origFileName>2020.02 Tilmæli um náttúruvernd, fuglavernd og ferðavinnu í Mykinesi.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 187360 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision$; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="dan">NÁTTÚRUVERND,</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">FUGLAVERND</p>
<p>OG FERÐAVINNU</p>
<p>Í MYKINESI</p>
<p>TILMÆLI UM</p>
<p>VISIT FAROE ISLANDS - UMHVØRVISSTOVAN - SØRVÁGS KOMMUNA - TJÓÐSAVNIÐ - HAVSTOVAN - VISIT VÁGAR</p>
<p><em type="bold">Tilmæli um náttúruvernd, fuglavernd og ferðavinnu í Mykinesi </em><em type="bold"></em><em type="bold">04 </em></p>
<p>Fylgiskjal 1 <em type="bold">Baksýni: 2017–2020 – Mykines og gongdin út í Hólm </em><em type="bold">10 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Fylgiskjal 2 <em type="bold">Sustainable Tourism Management – Scoping Report – July 2019 </em><em type="bold">12 </em></p>
<p>Fylgiskjal 3 <em type="bold">Tórshavn, 8.11.2019 – Sildberin og órógv </em><em type="bold">34 </em></p>
<p>Fylgiskjal 4 <em type="bold">Aðrar gonguleiðir </em><em type="bold">36 </em></p>
<p>YVIRLIT</p>
<p>Tilmælini eru liður í langari tilgongd at skipa viðurskiftini í Mykinesi, m.a. í samsvari við tilmælini í Ramsar-ætlanini og við atliti at ferðavinnuni. Viðfest er ein stutt gjøgnumgongd av tilgongdini higartil (fylgiskjal 1).</p>
<p>Sum liður í arbeiðinum at finna fram til eina burðardyggari umsiting av økinum, hava vit fingið útlendskan serfrøðing at vitja økið og, við støði í sínum eygleiðingum, at orða nøkur tilmæli um innihaldið í eini burðardyggari umsitingarætlan (fylgiskjal 2).</p>
<p>Tilmælini niðanfyri eru fyri ein part grundað á nevndu tilmæli og á frágreiðing frá fuglafrøðingum á Tjóðsavninum og Havstovuni, ið hava verið við í hesum arbeiðinum (sí fylgiskjali 3).</p>
<p>Tað eru nógv ymisk átøk, ið eru neyðug at seta í verk í Mykinesi. Tilmælini niðanfyri eru serliga um gongdina ígjøgnum Lamba, har ið harðast leikar á at gera eitthvørt. Tilmælini eru send Ramsar-nevndini fyri Mykines til kunningar 10. januar 2020, tey vera løgd fram fyri bygdarfólkið og jarðareigarar í Mykinesi 7. februar, og á borgarafundi í Sørvági tann 13. februar 2020 verður almenn framløga.</p>
<p>Mælt verður til: <em type="bold">1) </em>At leiðin gjøgnum Lamba verður stongd í bútíðini, til avtala er gjørd um eina burðardygga umsiting av økinum (uppskotini í fylgiskjali 2 eru gott útgangsstøði). </p>
<p>Tó kann verða skipað fyri serligum túrum við ferðaleiðara fyri avmarkaðum skara í turrum veðri eftir fastari mannagongd, sum tryggjar, at fuglur og lendi ikki verður overvað. <em type="bold">a. </em>Kanningar hjá fuglafrøðingum hava staðfest, at lundin, serliga sildberin, verður nógv órógvaður og heldur seg burtur, tá ið fólk eru á gøtuni. Kanningar vísa eisini, at fleiri holur tætt við gøtuna eru tómar, og tess longri tú fert frá gøtuni, tess fleiri lundaholur eru, sum lív er í. (sí skjal 3) <em type="bold">2) </em>At kanningar verða settar í verk í Lamba í 2020, sum kunnu vera grundarlag undir, hvussu gongdin gjøgnum Lamba verður skipað undir umstøðum, ið nú eru. T.e., hvussu nógv fólk skulu sleppa túrin, nær á degnum gongdin órógvar minst, og nær eingin gongd eigur at vera loyvd (sí fylgiskjal 2 og 3) <em type="bold">3) </em>At farið verður undir at skipa Lamba og møguliga eisini </p>
<p>Mykineshólm sum eitt serligt verndarøki sambært løgtingslóg um náttúrufriðing. <em type="bold">4) </em>At farið verður undir at kanna, hvussu ein nýggj leið oman ímóti brúnni kann verða gjørd. Nýggja leiðin eigur at vera løgd uttan um búøkið hjá lunda og øðrum fugli soleiðis, at fuglurin fær frið. Eisini skal tryggjast, at hon fellur væl inn í lendið og verður gjørd eftir røttum forskriftum. </p>
<p>TILMÆLIverður orðað við ítøkiligum tilmælum um, hvørji átøk eiga at vera framd, so vit fáa eina væl skipaða og burðardygga ferðavinnu í oynni, sum flest øll kunnu liva við og liva av. Ætlanin skal gerast í tøttum samstarvi við borgarar í oynni (sí eisini tilmælini frá Nathan Reigner, fylgiskjal 2).verður staðfest, t.e., hvussu nógv ferðafólk Mykines kann bera við verandi hentleikum, tað veri seg við atliti at bygdini, lendinum og fuglinum. Alt bendir á, at ferðafólkatalið er væl oman fyri tað, oyggin, sum nú er, kann bera, men neyðugt er at kanna tað gjøllari. Hetta er avgerandi fyri eina burðardygga ferðavinnu í Mykinesi. hvørjar avmarkingarnar í ferðafólkatalinum eiga at vera.merkja alla farleiðina fram við Eggini soleiðis, at fólk kunnu ganga túrin út á Rógvuna at hyggja at fugli og síðani ganga eystur eftir eggini, til komið verður til hagamarkið eystan fyri bygdina. Øll farleiðin eigur at vera umvæld og, har tað ber til, at verða breiðkað so mikið, at tvey kunnu ganga lið um lið, so tað slepst undan gásagongd, ið slítur nógv. (Víst verður til hjálagda uppskot, sí fylgiskjal 4.) <em type="bold">a. </em>Neyðugt er at gera nýtt kunningartilfar, faldarar, skelti o.a., sum vísa á nýggju farleiðina, umframt skelti, ið vísa á rættan atburð, tá ið gingið verður. Hetta arbeiði kann Visit Faroe Islands standa fyri. <em type="bold">8) </em>Avgerandi fyri eina vælskipaða ferðavinnu í oynni er, at fólk fáa neyðugu kunningina, tá ið tey koma út í oynna, so vit tryggja okkum, at tey duga at bera seg at. Føst kunningarfólk eiga at verða sett í starv, sum hava ábyrgd av at taka ímóti fólki og kunna um Mykines. <em type="bold">a. </em>Tað er sjálvsagt at brúka tey starvsfólk, ið longu eru í oynni til miðvísa kunning (á ferjuni, á lendingini, á tyrlupallinum, á caféini og ferðaleiðarar). Tey eiga at verða skúlað til at geva neyva og samskipaða kunning um atburð í oynni. <em type="bold">9) </em>Viðvíkjandi gjaldinum eigur innkrevjingarhátturin at vera endurskoðaður. Eitt hugskot er at umskipa verandi <span type="quote" xml:lang="dan">“hiking-fee”</span> soleiðis, at tað frameftir verður eitt rímiligt og meiri alment vitjanargjald fyri at fara út um bøgarðarnar í Mykinesi, ið eisini var tað, ið upprunaliga varð samtykt á grannastevnuni í 2017. Sostatt keypa tey ferðandi ein pakka, ið gevur atgongd til ávís støð í Mykinesi. Gjaldið kann so fara í ein Mykines-grunn, ið verður umsitin eftir neyvari reglugerð. Inntøkurnar kunnu síðani brúkast til ymisk átøk, allari oynni at frama. Eisini til átøk, ið kunnu skipa ferðavinnuna betur og tryggja, at fleiri inntøkur frá ferðavinnuni liggja eftir á staðnum. Ein treyt er kortini, at gjald, hentleikar og fyriskipanir eru hvørt eftir øðrum, so tey vitjandi síggja greitt samband millum gjald og vernd, hentleikar, tænastu o.a. <em type="bold">a. </em>Eitt dømi er at brúka gamla skúlan í Mykinesi sum karm um nýtt Visitor-Centre, har ferðafólk kunnu fáa góða kunning um Mykines, um fuglin, søguna, veiðimentanina o.a., og har ferðafólk hava høvi at keypa tinganest og túrar í oynni, sum fólk á staðnum skipa fyri. <em type="bold">b. </em>Ein partur av inntøkunum eigur eisini at vera brúktur til at fíggja neyðugt kanningararbeiði, gøtur, kunningartilfar og annað, sum kann hava við sær, at ferðavinnan í oynni verður betur skipað og burðardyggari. Visit Faroe Islands er sinnað at rinda part av hesum kostnaði. <em type="bold">c. </em>Gjaldsinnkrevjing og avmarkingar hanga neyvt saman. Tað er neyðugt, umframt aðrar avmarkingar, at seta eitt mesta mark á, hvussu nógv fólk sleppa út í oynna um samdøgrið (sí tilmæli 6). Ferjan til Mykinesar hevur eina lyklastøðu og eina lyklaábyrgd hesum viðvíkjandi. Tað er við ferjuni til ber at avmarka ferðafólkastreymin út í oynna, og tað er á ferjuni, til ber at geva ferðafólki góða kunning um, hvussu tey bera seg at í oynni. Eyðsýndasta loysnin fyri Mykines er tí at samskipa innkrevjing, kunning og avmarkingar í sambandi við siglingina til oynna. </p>
<p>Hesi tilmæli eiga sjálvsagt at verða meiri viðgjørd, áðrenn endalig avgerð verður tikin. Ikki minst er tað umráðandi, at borgarar og jarðareigarar í Mykinesi verða við í tilgongdini at skipa ferðavinnuna í oynni. <em type="bold">10) </em>Til tess at tryggja, at øll verkætlanin verður kjølfest á staðnum, mæla vit til, at eitt ábyrgdarfólk verður útnevnt at hava ábyrgd av at ætlanini verður hildin og tryggja, at tilmælini verða sett í verk. Hvør, ið eigur at hava hesa ábyrgd, og hvør, ið fíggjar arbeiði, eigur eisini at vera gjøllari umrøtt við avvarðandi partar, áðrenn endalig avgerð verður tikin. </p>
<p>FYLGISKJØL</p>
<p>Mykinesi verður avmarkaður í tíðarskeiðinum frá 1. mai – 31. august. Avmarkingin er ikki galdandi fyri fólk, ið eru í arbeiðsørindum, t.d. í sambandi við rakstur og røkt og eftirlit við vatnverki, el- og samskiftisútgerð, vitanum. við góðkendum ferðaleiðara. Hesin góðkendi ferðaleiðarin skal sambært samtyktini hava ábyrgdina av, at gongdin er skipað, at ferðafólk halda seg á gøtum og steðgiplássum, at ferðafólk órógva fugl og djór sum minst o.a.soleiðis, at gongd bara er loyvd hesi tíðarskeið: mai, juni og juli mánað frá kl. 0700 -1000, 1200 – 1600 og 1800 – 2100. Í august mánað frá kl. 0900 – 1800.ár gjalda 50 kr. og yngri gjalda onki fyri at fara út um bøgarðarnar.</p>
<p type="listitem">Hetta fyrsta árið eftir grannastevnusamtyktina (summarið  2017) varð ein skipan roynd, har ferðafólk vóru biðin um at  flyta 100 krónur á eina felags bankakonto fyri hagapartarnar.  Annars vóru hinar ásetingarnar í grannastevnusamtyktini  ikki settar í verk. Henda innkrevingarskipan virkaði ikki  eftir ætlan, og sum skilst kom lítil peningur inn. 11. januar 2018 var felagið <span type="quote">“hagapartarnir Mykines”</span> sett á  stovn, ið hevur uppgávuna at umsita tann pening, ið kemur  inn frá gongugjaldinum. Í § 3 verður sagt, at endamál  felagsins er</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla tiltøkum, ið menna ferðavinnu í Mykinesi</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla átøkum, ið verja náttúru, fugla- og djóralív í</p>
<p type="listitem">Mykinesi</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla tiltøkum, ið menna landbúnaðin í Mykinesi</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla átøkum, ið endurbyggja fornminni o.a. í</p>
<p type="listitem">Mykinesi</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla einstøku hagapørtunum hvør sær ella í felag</p>
<p type="listitem">at stuðla Mykines bygd og oynni á ein og hvønn hátt</p>
<p>Fyri summarið 2018 var avtala gjørd við felagið hiking. fo um <span type="quote">“vaktarhald”</span> og innkrevjing. Fráboðan um hetta varð eins og árið frammanundan send út, beint áðrenn ferðavinnuháárstíðin byrjaði, t.e. í mai mánaði. Í hesi fráboðan boðaðu hagastýrisformennirnir í Mykinesi frá, at kravið um ferðaleiðara var slept. Eisini var boðað frá, at tíðarásetingin í grannastevnusamtyktini verður broytt soleiðis, at tað einans er loyvt at fara út um bøgarðarnar frá 11-17 hvønn dag.</p>
<p>Í 2019, triðja árið eftir grannastevusamtyktina, er enn eina ferð nýggj skipan sett í verk, ið minnir um skipanina frá 2018, tó at tað nú er sp/f Mykines, felagið, ið rekur bátin Jósup, ið stendur fyri innkrevjingini. Peningurin verður kravdur inn í Sørvági, áðrenn ferðafólk fara umborð á Jósup, og við minnisvarðan í Mykinesi er eftirlit við, um fólk hava goldið. Fráboðanin um nýggju skipanina varð send út dagin fyri, at hon var sett í verk, og eftir at ferjan var farin at sigla.</p>
<p>Í januar 2020, fjórða árið, skipanin hevur virkað, varð fráboðan send frá hagastýrunum um, at skipanin aftur verður tillagað fyri 2020. Nú er tað galdandi, at gongugjaldið er hækkað til 250 kr. fyri hvønn. Gjaldið í 2020 verður bara galdandi fyri útlendingar og fyri skipað vinnulig ferðaløg, men føroyingar sleppa ókeypis. Eisini er vanligi ferðaseðilin við ferjuni hækkaður frá 60 til 100 kr. hvønn vegin. Enn er ógreitt, hvussu gjaldið verður umsitið, og hvussu skipanin í praksis fer at gera mun á føroyingum og útlendingum.</p>
<p>Í fráboðanini verður sagt, at gjaldið verður kravt inn fyri at verja haga og fugl. Tó er enn ógreitt, hvørji verndarátøk æltandi verða sett í verk.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Vit kunnu út frá royndunum higartil staðfesta 1) </em>At grannastevusamtyktin frá apríl 2017 ongantíð er sett í verk, tá ið tað snýr seg um ásetingarnar um gongurætt, ferðaleiðara og tíðaravmarkingar. Einasta áseting, sum er sett í verk, er gjaldsinnkrevjingin, ið tó bara er galdandi fyri túrin út í Hólmin og ikki fyri aðrar túrar uttan fyri bøgarðarnar, sum annars er ásett í grannastevnusamtyktini. <em type="bold">2) </em>Hóast skipanin er broytt ár undan ári, er ongin nýggj granna- ella hagastevna hildin, ið heimilar pørtunum at broyta skipanina. Sýslumaðurin staðfestir annars í skrivi 6. juni 2018, at <span type="quote">”Grannastevnuviðtøkan áleggur, at tað skal nýtast góðkendur ferðaleiðari. Skal tað broytast, má tað gerast á grannastevnu”</span>. <em type="bold">3) </em>Skipanin er ikki nøktandi og lýkur ikki endamálið, sum í viðtøkunum fyri felagið <span type="quote">“Hagapartarnir Mykines”</span> er at verja djór og náttúru. Gongdin út um bøgarðararnar, serliga út í Lamba, heldur fram at kalla ódarvað, og peningurin, sum inn er komin, er ikki brúktur til náttúru- ella djóravernd. <em type="bold">4) </em>Verða avmarkingar, verndarátøk og skipað gongd ikki sett í verk skjótt, er vandi fyri, at stór náttúru-, umhvørvis-, djóra- og ferðavinnuvirði fara fyri skeyti. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Recreation &amp; Tourism Science </em>www.RecreationTourismScience.com 494 Broadway, Newport, Rhode Island, 02840, USA </p>
<p>Nathan@RecreationTourismScience.com +1.802.331.0311</p>
<p>August 1, 2019</p>
<p>Visit Faroe Islands</p>
<p>Gongin 9, PO Box 118</p>
<p>FO-110 Tórshavn, Faroe Islands</p>
<p>Dear Jóhan Pauli Helgason,</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Thank you for inviting me to visit the Faroe Islands (July 3rd – 8th, 2019) to meet with you, your staff, and colleagues, and to visit and view some of the Faroe Islands’ most prominent tourism destinations. During my visit, which I undertook as part of my research as a Fulbright Scholar in Iceland, it was an enjoyable and educational experience to learn about the tourism influences and issues facing the Faroe Islands.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The following document reviews the activities of my trip; details the tourism behaviors, destinations, and impacts that we observed on Mykines, as well as suggests a path forward to sustainable tourism management of the area; and presents some more general observations related to other tourism destinations in the Faroe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Islands. I hope that this information is helpful for you and your col eagues as you work to make tourism in the</p>
<p>Faroe Islands more environmentally, socially, and economically sustainable.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Research and data informed planning and management are vital components of sustainable tourism. Effective sustainable tourism management requires an understanding of the relationships among tourism types and amounts, tourist behavior, environmental resources, and destination communities. With this understanding, the positive and negative impacts of tourism can be known, alternative management approaches to maximize the positive impacts and mitigate the negative impacts can be analyzed, and the effectiveness of management actions can be assessed. Without it, there can be little certainty that management actions will address the issues against which they are targeted, and secondary problems may be unknowingly caused. Additional y, the objective nature and transparency of a data-drive, scientific approach to tourism management is a powerful to for gaining public support for management actions.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">These points are particularly relevant to current situation at Mykines where tourism pressures are heavy, the puffins and other resources are sensitive, negative impacts are accumulating, and existing management is inadequate to protect nature, ensure safe and high-quality tourism experiences, and help the local community realize the full and sustained benefits of tourism.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">It would be my pleasure to continue to support you and your colleagues in the Faroese tourism and environmental management community continue your good work to protect the Faroese environment, help visitors have excel ent experiences, and generate the benefits of tourism for Faroese residents.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sincerely,</p>
<p>Nathan Reigner, PhD</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Fulbright Scholar, Icelandic Tourism Research Center</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Principal, Recreation &amp; Tourism Science</p>
<p>SUSTAINABLE TOURISM MANAGEMENT SCOPING REPORT – JULY 2019 Nathan Reigner, PhD ` 1 | P a g e</p>
<p>ACTIVITIES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The following list the activities conducted during the July 2019 scoping trip, along with activity participants and a brief description of the purpose of each activity. §</p>
<p>Meeting with <em type="bold">Visit Faroe Islands </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Jóhan Pauli Helgason </em>A general meeting to review the trip’s agenda, develop familiarity with tourism and environmental governance and administration in the Faroe Islands, discuss specific concerns related to Mykines tourism, and review the overall state of tourism use and development in the Faroe Islands. § </p>
<p>Meeting with <em type="bold">Umhvørvisstovan </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Suni Petersen, Maria Gunnleivsdóttir Hansen, Jóhan Pauli Helgason, Alda Egilstrøð Magnussen </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A meeting with the environmental agency to discuss the connections between tourism management and environmental protection, review the current state of policy and action for environmental protection in the Faroe Islands, and share examples of nature-based tourism from Iceland and the United States. §</p>
<p>Meeting with <em type="bold">Búnaðarstovan </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Tróndur G. Leivsson, Jóhan Pauli Helgason, Alda Egilstrøð Magnussen </em>A meeting with the agriculture agency to discuss the connection between tourism and agricultural land use, specifical y as it relates to tourism access-related issues, and to share examples of naturebased tourism from Iceland and the United States. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Visit to <em type="bold">Mykines </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Jóhannis Danielsen, British PhD student, Oda Wilhelmsdóttir Andreasen, Heini Heinesen, Jóhan Pauli Helgason, Alda Egilstrøð Magnussen </em>A site-visit and meetings to Mykines and Mykineshólmur to develop familiarity with tourist activity, opportunities, and infrastructure in the area, discuss the relationship between tourism and environmental resources (i.e., puffins and other sea birds, vegetation, soils) and the current state of and potential futures for tourism with tourism administrators, bird experts, and local stakeholders. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Visit to <em type="bold">Trælanípa </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Jóhan Pauli Helgason, Alda Egilstrøð Magnussen </em>A site-visit to Trælanípa to develop familiarity with tourist activity, opportunities, and infrastructure in the area and to observe and critique the type and condition of recent infrastructure development and management activities. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Visits to <em type="bold">Saksun </em>, <em type="bold">Tjørnuvík </em>, <em type="bold">Gjógv </em>, <em type="bold">Mikladalur, </em>and <em type="bold">Trøl anes </em>and <em type="bold">Kal ur Lighthouse </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Site-visits to develop familiarity with tourist activity, opportunities, and infrastructure in the areas, observe the types and conditions of tourism infrastructure development and management activities. ` 2 | P a g e</p>
<p>Photo Credit: Nathan Reigner</p>
<p>Photo Credit: Nathan Reigner ` 3 |</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Page</p>
<p>YK</p>
<p>IN</p>
<p>ES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Locat ions marked on this map are referenc ed in the text below. <em type="bold">1 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Harbor where the ferry boat drops off <em type="bold">5 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Northwestern peninsula and ove rlook <em type="bold">2 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines vilage <em type="bold">6 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Path trave ling throu gh the middle of</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Lamba puf fin colony <em type="bold">3 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Ridge-top where puf fins becom e visible and lost sailor monument <em type="bold">7 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Bridge connecting</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines and Mykineshólmur <em type="bold">4 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Binocular instalation area <em type="bold">8 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykineshólmur lighthouse and lighthouse keeper’s quar ters 1 2 3 4 5 6</p>
<p>Lamba</p>
<p>Mykineshólmur7 8</p>
<p>Main</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Path ` 4 | P a g e</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines is one of the primary tourism destinations in the Faroe Islands. Mykines is accessed either by ferry boat (capacity approximately 80 persons) or helicopter (capacity approximately 12 persons). There is one scheduled public ferry trip each day. The ferry operator typically runs a second daily trip, and sometimes a third, to the island. Additionally, private boat and tour operators. On busy days during the peak tourism season (June through August) approximately 200 tourists may visit the island. The main tourist season closely aligns with the puffin nesting season.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Puffin viewing, hiking, and visiting the Mykineshólmur lighthouse are the primary activities for visitors. Visiting the vil age of Mykines and hiking to other destinations on Mykines are also common activities. There are limited services available for tourists on Mykines. They include a small café and giftshop and a small guesthouse.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A TYPICAL VISIT TO MYKINES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The typical visit to Mykines begins in Sørvágur by paying the hiking fee (100 DKK) imposed by the farmers controlling the land around Mykines vil age to the ferry boat operator and boarding the boat. After a ferry ride of 45-60 minutes, during which visitors view surrounding islands, their birdlife, and the Mykines coastline, the boat arrives at Mykines and visitors disembark [1]. Visitors ascend from the harbor, where those who have hired local guides meet their guides, and proceed toward Mykines vil age [2] and begin their hike toward the puffin colony at Lamba.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Visitors heading to Lamba depart the road toward Mykines village prior to reaching the vil age and ascend a moderately steep path following a fence line to the northwest through open sheep pasture. At the top of the pasture, the path turns southwest and follows the height of land along a relatively narrow ridge with the slope of Lamba to the south. Shortly after the turn, in the vicinity of the lost sailor monument, puffins are visible from the ridge-top path [3]. In this area, the puffins are clearly visible just below the crest of the ridge and down the slopes of Lamba. Visitors proceed southwest toward the sight of a planned binocular installation [4]. Puffins are easily and frequently visible throughout this part of the path.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">After the binocular installation, the path drops below the ridge on the north side via constructed stairs, sometimes with handrails, before rounding the end of the ridge and heading south onto the slope of Lamba. Here there is a smal peninsula extending to the northwest that is used by some visitors and local guides as an overlook to view the puffin colony as wel as the sea, Mykines island, and Mykineshólmur [5]. Continuing along the path leads visitors steeply down and southeast through a small valley in the middle of the Lamba puffin colony. Multiple paths are present in this area, the result of new path construction and the development of several user-created paths through the colony. Approximately halfway down the small valley the path turns southwest across Lamba, through a concentration of puffin burrows, toward Mykineshólmur [6].</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">After crossing Lamba, the path takes visitors to the footbridge connecting Mykines and Mykineshólmur, from which there are excel ent views of the sea between the two islands and sea cliffs inhabited by several types of birds [7]. From here the path proceed generally southwest across Mykineshólmur, climbing via multiple pathways toward the crest of Mykineshólmur’s ridge, finally reaching the Mykineshólmur lighthouse and its keeper’s quarters [8]. From this point, visitors return to Mykines vil age [2] by the same route. ` 5 | P a g e</p>
<p>IMPACTS RELATED TO TOURISM ON MYKINES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Many benefits are generated by tourism to Mykines. The community receives income from tourists and tourism provides them an opportunity to showcase their islands and vil age. Furthermore, tourists have exceptional experiences with the community, land- and seascapes, and puffins. However, tourism to Mykines is also causing negative impacts to environmental resources (e.g., puffins and other sea birds, soils, vegetation) the tourism experience at the destination (e.g., safety, enjoyability, crowding and conflict, value for money), and the experience of residents with tourism. The following table lists the range of observed and potential impacts:</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Observed and Potential Tourism-related Impacts at Mykines </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Impact </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Description </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Severity </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Environmental </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Puffins and other sea birds</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Disturbance caused by tourists passing close to and through the Lamba puffin colony, direct damage to puffin burrows and their inhabitants.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, potentially severe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Vegetation</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Completely devegetated paths, trampled vegetation at stopping and viewing locations along the path.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Severe along paths, moderate at stopping locations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Soils</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Muddiness and erosion along paths, multiple unnecessary paths.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Severe on steep sections of path, moderate elsewhere</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Litter and waste</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Trash, toilet paper, and improperly disposed of waste along the path.</p>
<p>Slight</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Tourist Experience </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Safety</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Excessive muddiness on steep slopes and among rocks causes fal hazards. Multiple paths and ambiguous markings cause confusion about which is the safest path.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among visitor populations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Naturalness</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Vegetation loss, excessive muddiness, soil erosion, multiple paths, excessive trail marking.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among visitor populations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Crowding and conflict</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Need to step aside and let other pass, lack of solitude, inability to observe undisturbed birds.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among visitor populations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Value for money</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Dissatisfaction with relationship between fee amount and level of service and facility provided, quality of experience.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among visitor populations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sense of place</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Visitor comfort with levels and forms of access, tourist-local relationships, and social sustainability of tourism.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among visitor populations</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Resident Experience </em>` 6 | P a g e </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Disturbance</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Disturbance of daily activities by tourists.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among residents</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Displacement</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Residents displaced from Mykines and its attraction sites by tourists.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unknown, likely mixed among residents</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">These impacts, or potential impacts, are related in many ways to tourism use levels. If the number of tourists to Mykines increases, it is likely that these impacts would become more severe. If the number of tourists to Mykines decreases, some impacts would likely become less severe (e.g., puffins and other sea birds, crowding and conflict, disturbance, displacement). Others, however, would likely persist (e.g., soils, safety, value for money) regardless of decreasing tourist numbers either because the impacts have already accrued to a point that they would remain or because they are somewhat insensitive to tourist numbers.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Acknowledging that these relationships are non-linear and dependent, it is important to identify which impacts are the limiting factors for the sustainability of tourism to Mykines. In other words, which impacts are most important, sensitive to changes in tourism level, and able to serve as indicators for the <span type="quote">“health”</span> of the island’s tourism system. Puffin disturbance is likely this limiting factor for Mykines. Puffins viewing is the most significant draw for tourists to Mykines, virtually all tourists go to see the puffin colony at Lamba, puffins are sensitive to disturbance by tourists, and actions taken to manage impacts to puffins will likely address many of the other negative impacts from tourism.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The occurrence and severity of all impacts is related to the amount and type of tourism management at Mykines. The relationship between these impacts and management actions is complex. Intensification of some management actions (e.g., infrastructure development) could help to lessen some impacts (e.g., soils) while making other worse (e.g., naturalness). When planning management to address negative impacts from tourism at Mykines, it is important to consider management actions as a coordinated and mutually reinforcing set, not as independent actions, and combine them in ways that best accomplish environmental, social, and economic objectives for tourism management on the island.</p>
<p>EXISTING MANAGEMENT FOR MYKINES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Existing management of Mykines for environmental protection (e.g., puffins and other birds, soils, vegetation) and tourist experiences (e.g., safety, education, quality of experience, value for money) is minimal, uncoordinated, and inadequate relative to the value of Mykines as a community and natural resource and the damaging pressures tourist use places on the island, environment, and community.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Existing tourism management for Mykines includes the fol owing elements: §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Access rationing and allocation </em>– Combined capacities and scheduling of ferry and helicopter arrivals. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">These limit the total number of tourists that arrive to the island each day and distributes them in time according to the ferry and helicopter arrival schedule. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Access fee </em>– Hiking fee. This has potential to limit the total number of tourists that visit Mykines based on tourists’ wil ingness to pay for their visits, it provides a supply of money to fund additional management actions, and it provides income for Mykines residents that may balance the negative impacts caused by tourists to their lives and island. ` 7 | P a g e § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Information and education </em>– Websites, guidebooks, on-site signage, etc. Many information sources of varying quality and extensiveness are available. Effective communication of conditions to expect and desired responsible behavior can be a powerful management tool, however it is nearly impossible to ensure information delivery off-site (i.e., prior to visit). Current on-site information and education delivery is virtually absent. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Infrastructure </em>– Paths, wayfinding, viewing platforms, signage, etc. Existing paths are largely user created and, when on sloping terrain, unsustainably aligned. Path construction is informal and incremental (i.e., not part of comprehensive planning and development). Wayfinding aids (i.e., stakes that mark the path) are excessive in number, confusing, and easily moved. Structures to protect sensitive natural resources (e.g., puffins and their burrows, vegetation, soils) are largely absent. Signage directing visitors in the right ways to behave in and around the puffin colony and providing information on the puffins and their habitat is largely absent. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Guiding </em>– Guides to escort visitors and provide information. Guiding service is available, however it is not compulsory and there are not enough trained and capable guides to service the full population of Mykines visitors. Additionally, the cost of guiding service is a disincentive for its use. Trained and capable guides can improve the quality of tourist experiences by providing information about Mykines and its resources as wel as improve the safety and comfort of tourists during their visits. Guides can also help to mitigate negative impacts by ensuring tourists behave in a responsible and low-impact way. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Zoning </em>– Spatial or temporal subdivision of Mykines for planning and management. Currently, </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines and its tourism resources are managed as a single zone (i.e., all Mykines and Mykineshólmur with no temporal division). <em type="italic">De facto </em>zones do exist, however, in space (e.g., geographical y distinct areas like the ridge above Lamba, Lamba itself, and Mykineshólmur) and in time (i.e., times between ferry arrivals and departures). </p>
<p>RECOMMENDATION FOR ACTION TO SUSTAINABLY MANAGE TOURISM AT MYKINES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Enhanced and coordinated management of tourism to Mykines is needed based on the observed levels of tourism-caused impacts in the area, the inadequacy of existing management actions, the level of tourist use, the value and sensitivity of the island’s natural and cultural resources, and the desire to foster a sustainable tourism industry on Mykines and in the Faroe Islands.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A range of alternatives for management of tourism to Mykines should be considered.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A <em type="italic">no action </em>alternative exists at one end of this range. Within this alternative no new actions would be taken to manage tourism. This applies to the intensity of action (i.e., building of infrastructure, provision of information) and the coordination of action (i.e., development of regulations). This is a <em type="italic">laissez faire </em>approach that would allow tourism to continue to operate at Mykines based on existing market forces. This alternative would likely increase tourism-related impacts on Mykines with potential for the island’s tourism resources and desirability being destroyed and, ultimately, tourism to the island ending. This alternative is unsustainable and should not be implemented. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A <em type="italic">no tourism </em>alternative exists at the other end of this range. Within this alternative tourism to Mykines would be stopped completely. The natural resources of Mykines would be protected from the impacts of tourists, ` 8 | P a g e however, no benefits from tourism would be realized. The benefits of tourism are valuable and desirable for tourists, Mykines residents, and Faroese society. Effective and efficient management of tourism to Mykines that generates benefits while avoiding unacceptable impacts is possible. Therefore, this alternative should not be taken. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Between the <em type="italic">no action </em>and <em type="italic">no tourism </em>alternatives, there are many alternatives that can be put together. These alternatives combine different types and levels of access control (i.e., tourist arrival amounts and distributions, permits), information and education (e.g., off-site and on-site communication programs), infrastructure development (e.g., paths, platforms, barriers), guiding programs, and zoning. Each combination of management actions wil have different levels effectiveness mitigating different impacts and have different administrative requirements in terms of cost, law and regulation, staffing, construction, etc. The most sustainable alternative wil result from the combination of management actions that best accomplishes the environmental, social, and economic objectives for tourism to Mykines. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Tourism management for Mykines should be an adaptive process of continual improvement. This process should begin by taking advantage of the information, assets, and structures that are already in place and deliberately toward a comprehensive, data-driven, and community engaged planning and management system. Each step in the process should inform future steps and empower community members and managers to think critically about what works, what does not work, and how to adjust prior actions to work better in the future.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The sub-sections below provide recommended immediate and longer-term actions that wil put this process into place.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">IMMEDIATE ACTIONS Immediate management action at Mykines is both possible and needed. There is a substantial amount of information available on which to make some immediate management decisions and there are a number of different resources, assets, and structures that can be used to implement these actions. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Community coordination </em>– Visit Faroe Islands and other tourism managers, community members in </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines, and tourism stakeholders should continue open dialogue about their visions for sustainable tourism at Mykines, desires for tourism benefits, perceptions of tourism impacts, and ability to contribute to sustainable tourism management. This communication should highlight shared interests, the benefits that flow from tourism, and ways to harmonize stakeholder interests. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Information and education </em>– The information provided to visitors should be coordinated, enhanced, and more effectively delivered. Visitation to Mykines is largely funneled through the ferry and helicopter. These concentrated points of entry allow for effective contact of visitors. A message about how to properly behave (i.e., stay on trail, minimize disturbance to puffins, use a guide, etc.) can be delivered to every visitor arriving by ferry or helicopter with relative ease. This message should be specific and affirmative, telling visitors exactly how best to behave to minimize impacts on puffins and other sensitive resources. The harbor and helipad workers, ferry workers, and fee enforcement staff should be trained and coordinated to deliver this message to al visitors at each <span type="quote" xml:lang="dan">“touch-point”</span> (e.g., when arriving at the ferry, when departing the ferry, when arriving at the helipad, etc.). To be most effective, this message would be not just about proper behavior, but also include information about the natural and cultural heritage of Mykines, including its puffins. Visit Faroe Islands and other stakeholders should also work with tourism-related press and information providers (e.g., websites, guidebooks) to make sure visitors have accurate expectations of their visit to Mykines and the ways they wil be expected to behave. ` 9 | P a g e § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Infrastructure </em>– Two immediate actions should be taken with respect to infrastructure. First, signage in the Mykines area should be improved in both amount and information quality. Clear, professionally made, and strategically located signage should be installed communicating the same proper behavior message delivered at visitor arrival locations. Second, guidelines for trail closure should be developed and implemented. These guidelines should be based on minimizing impacts to puffins, soils, and vegetation, as well as visitor safety. Visitors should be informed prior to their visits that trails may be closed for good reasons and trail closures should be monitored and enforced by fee-enforcement staff. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Guiding </em>– Visitors should be more strongly encouraged to use guides when visiting Mykines and resources to develop guiding services (e.g., training programs, mentoring, incubators) should be enhanced. Additional y, best practices for guiding visitors at Mykines should be developed though consultation with guides, community members, and subject matter experts. Properly trained guides following agreed upon best practices for guiding visitors can both exert a great deal of management control on visitation as well as enhance the overall experience of visitors. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">LONGER-TERM ACTIONS The above listed immediate actions represent a first step in sustainable management of tourism to Mykines. Immediate actions wil not, however, answer the question of how much tourism can Mykines handle environmentally or social y, nor wil they ensure that tourism use levels are kept within environmental and social constraints.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The information and structures required to answer these questions and construct a comprehensive sustainable management system do not currently exist. Long-term action at Mykines should be focused on the goal of identifying the optimum levels and types of tourism use and the most effective and feasible set of management actions. The following is a brief recommended list of tasks to accomplish this goal, focused on the disturbance puffins in the Lamba area. <em type="bold">1. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Determine the maximum acceptable level of disturbance that puffins in the Lamba area can tolerate. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Consult with bird experts to determine the maximum frequency, intensity, and distribution of disturbance that the puffin colony can tolerate before the sustainability of the colony becomes unacceptably endangered.1 Much of information required to make this determination may already exist and it should be synthesized for the specific purpose of tourism management for Mykines. <em type="bold">2. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Determine the relationship between tourism use and puffin disturbance. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Collect and analyze data to determine the relationship between tourist and other uses of the Lamba area (i.e., type, amount, and distribution of use) and the frequency, intensity, and distribution of puffin 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Skene (2013) provides an example of such a study focused on eider disturbance at Dryólaey Nature Reserve in southern Iceland. This study is referenced here as an example, methods and analysis for a study at Mykines would need to address the issues specific to puffins and the tourism in the area. [Skene, Afra. (2013). The impact of visitor disturbance on breeding Eider ( <em type="italic">Somateria mol issima </em>) populations at Dryólaey Nature Reserve: Implications for management. Ísafjörður, Iceland: University Center of the Westfjords. Available at: https://skemman.is/bitstream/1946/15900/1/Thesis.afra.skene.2013.pdf. Accessed August 1, 2019.] ` 10 | P a g e disturbance. Much of information required to make this determination may already exist and it should be synthesized for the specific purpose of tourism management for Mykines. <em type="bold">3. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Estimate the maximum capacity of the Lamba area for tourists. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Estimate the maximum tourist use level (i.e., type, amount, and distribution) that can visit the Lamba area without systematically exceeding the maximum acceptable level of disturbance of puffins. <em type="bold">4. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Recommend and implement a tourism management approach for the Lamba area that maximizes </em><em type="bold">tourist use within the area’s estimated maximum tourism capacity. </em>Consider and analyze a range of alternative management configurations and analyze them based on their relative efficacy and feasibility. These alternatives should include options that maintain tourist use in Lamaba, shift tourists use away from Lamba but maintain a similar tourists experiences to those available in Lamba, and prohibit al tourism use in and around Lamba. Recommend and implement the management approach that best maximizes tourist use of the Lamba area within puffin-related capacity constraints as well as other relevant environmental, social, and administrative management constraints. <em type="bold">5. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Design and make recommendations to implement a tourism monitoring program. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Design a program to monitor tourism-related conditions and impacts, including puffin disturbance patterns, tourist satisfaction, resident experiences of tourism, and economic impacts of tourism. Make recommendations for implementing the monitoring program and using its results for policymaking.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Accomplishing the above described tasks wil require a series of data collection, analysis, engagement, and related activities. The table below provides a timeline of these activities, along with comments on the necessary outside support Visit Faroe Islands would need to complete them, rough order of magnitude cost estimates, and relatively priority assessments. It is important to note that while this table lists these activities individual y, they should be thought of as a progression of integrated activities that lead from actions that can be taken now with relatively little funding to full implementation of a comprehensive sustainable tourism management structure for Mykines. Likewise, while cost estimates are provided individually, many of the activities are mutually supporting and share resources related to field data collection, analysis, and reporting. Conducting them through a coordinated, phased approach would both create substantial overall cost savings and ensure the highest level of quality for the results. If fully implemented, these activities will result in a welldocumented and scientifically sound management approach that accounts for the environmental, social, and economic aspects of tourism sustainability on Mykines. An example of such a management approach could include elements such as: §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Enhanced information and education program to better inform visitors about expectations for responsible behavior on Mykines and near puffins. §</p>
<p>Improved infrastructure to protect vegetation from trampling damage, soils from erosion, and tourists from safety hazards. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Zoning of Mykines into areas and times with customized access requirements and tourism levels (e.g., group size limits, restricted access times, guide requirements, etc.) to keep puffin disturbance within acceptable levels. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Development of additional tourism opportunities on Mykines to better distribute visitors and improve overall tourist and resident experiences. ` 11 | P a g e §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Ongoing basic tourism statistics tracking and periodic monitoring of tourism-related conditions to assess the effectiveness of management, track changes in use and tourism-related conditions, and information future policy, planning, and management.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">These elements are simply examples of the kind of integrated management actions that could be combined for sustainable management of tourism to Mykines. An actual management approach should only be developed fol owing additional research, analysis, and consultation with relevant stakeholders. `</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Ac </em><em type="bold">tivi </em><em type="bold">ties </em><em type="bold">&amp; </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">R </em><em type="bold">ec </em><em type="bold">om </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">ded </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Ti </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">g </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Nec </em><em type="bold">essa </em><em type="bold">ry </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">E </em><em type="bold">xter </em><em type="bold">na </em><em type="bold">l S </em><em type="bold">up </em><em type="bold">po </em><em type="bold">rt </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Ap </em><em type="bold">pro </em><em type="bold">x. </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Co </em><em type="bold">st </em><em type="bold">1 </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Prio </em><em type="bold">rit </em><em type="bold">y </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">W </em><em type="bold">ith </em><em type="bold">in </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">O </em><em type="bold">ne </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Year </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Co </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">pi </em><em type="bold">le </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">al </em><em type="bold">yz </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">ava </em><em type="bold">ila </em><em type="bold">bl </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">da </em><em type="bold">ta </em><em type="bold">a </em><em type="bold">bo </em><em type="bold">ut </em><em type="bold">vi </em><em type="bold">sit </em><em type="bold">or </em><em type="bold">u </em><em type="bold">se </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Work with ferry, helicopter, and tour operators and guides to gather data aboutcurrent visitor use (i.e., ferry and helicopter passengers, number of guided tours, group size, etc.). Analyze this data to understand thenumber and type of visitors to the island and their distribution in time.§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stakeholder participation§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Data management and analyticalsupport</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Co </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">pi </em><em type="bold">le </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">re </em><em type="bold">vi </em><em type="bold">ew </em><em type="bold">av </em><em type="bold">ai </em><em type="bold">lab </em><em type="bold">le </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">fo </em><em type="bold">rm </em><em type="bold">at </em><em type="bold">io </em><em type="bold">n </em><em type="bold">on </em><em type="bold">p </em><em type="bold">uf </em><em type="bold">fin </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">ist </em><em type="bold">ur </em><em type="bold">ban </em><em type="bold">ce </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Literature review and consultation with bird experts to about therelationships among tourism, bird disturbance, and puffin colony health/sustainability.§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Biological/ecological science expertise</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Do </em><em type="bold">cu </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t t </em><em type="bold">he </em><em type="bold">co </em><em type="bold">nd </em><em type="bold">iti </em><em type="bold">on </em><em type="bold">o </em><em type="bold">f t </em><em type="bold">he </em><em type="bold">tra </em><em type="bold">il </em><em type="bold">th </em><em type="bold">ro </em><em type="bold">ugh </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Lam </em><em type="bold">ba </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">to </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">M </em><em type="bold">yki </em><em type="bold">nes </em><em type="bold">hó </em><em type="bold">lm </em><em type="bold">ur </em><em type="bold">li </em><em type="bold">gh </em><em type="bold">th </em><em type="bold">ou </em><em type="bold">se </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Measure and assess the alignment, vegetation cover, width, depth, etc. of the existing trails leading from</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines to</p>
<p>Lamba. §</p>
<p>Trail science expert(s)</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 2</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">On </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">to </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Tw </em><em type="bold">o </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Year </em><em type="bold">s </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Sh </em><em type="bold">ift </em><em type="bold">st </em><em type="bold">aff </em><em type="bold">fo </em><em type="bold">cu </em><em type="bold">s fr </em><em type="bold">om </em><em type="bold">fee </em><em type="bold">-e </em><em type="bold">nf </em><em type="bold">or </em><em type="bold">ce </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">ent </em><em type="bold">to </em><em type="bold">educ </em><em type="bold">at </em><em type="bold">ion </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Train and empower fee-enforcement staff to engage visitor in informaleducational conversations with visitors about</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines, puffins, and responsible behavior while conducting their fee-enforcement activities. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Environmental interpretation expertise§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stakeholder participation</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Det </em><em type="bold">er </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">th </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">rel </em><em type="bold">at </em><em type="bold">io </em><em type="bold">ns </em><em type="bold">hi </em><em type="bold">p </em><em type="bold">bet </em><em type="bold">w </em><em type="bold">een </em><em type="bold">vi </em><em type="bold">sit </em><em type="bold">or </em><em type="bold">u </em><em type="bold">se </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">pu </em><em type="bold">ffi </em><em type="bold">n </em><em type="bold">di </em><em type="bold">st </em><em type="bold">ur </em><em type="bold">ba </em><em type="bold">nc </em><em type="bold">e </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Observe the disturbance patterns that result from a range ofvisitor use patterns throughout the puffin nesting season.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Instal and operate trail counters or other devices to gather continuous data on visitor use levels and distributions. Analyze the data to determine the relationship between visitor use level and distribution, and quantify the amount and patterns of puffin disturbance being caused by visitors. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">University or consultancy research§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Multi-disciplinary expertise</p>
<p>B 2</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Su </em><em type="bold">rve </em><em type="bold">y v </em><em type="bold">isi </em><em type="bold">to </em><em type="bold">rs </em><em type="bold">to </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">M </em><em type="bold">yk </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">es </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Survey visitors to Mykines to understand their motivations for visiting, activities and behaviors whilevisiting, perceptions of conditions in the area, and attitudes about and support for alternative management activities. <em type="bold"></em>§ </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">University or consultancy research §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Social science expertise</p>
<p>B 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Det </em><em type="bold">er </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">th </em><em type="bold">e </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">axi </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">um </em><em type="bold">ca </em><em type="bold">pa </em><em type="bold">cit </em><em type="bold">ies </em><em type="bold">fo </em><em type="bold">r vi </em><em type="bold">sit </em><em type="bold">or </em><em type="bold">u </em><em type="bold">nd </em><em type="bold">er </em><em type="bold">a </em><em type="bold">lter </em><em type="bold">na </em><em type="bold">tive </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">agem </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t s </em><em type="bold">cen </em><em type="bold">ar </em><em type="bold">io </em><em type="bold">s </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Analyze puffin disturbance, visitor use and survey, and other data to: a) determine and the maximum acceptable level of puffin disturbance; b) suggest alternative management approaches and analyze their feasibility; c) determine the maximum number of visitors that each management approach could accommodate within the maximum acceptable level of puffin disturbance.§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">University or consultancy research§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Multi-disciplinary expertise §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stakeholder participation</p>
<p>B 2</p>
<p><em type="bold">Tw </em><em type="bold">o </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Ye </em><em type="bold">ar </em><em type="bold">s or </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">M </em><em type="bold">or </em><em type="bold">e </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">En </em><em type="bold">gag </em><em type="bold">em </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t t </em><em type="bold">o </em><em type="bold">id </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">tif </em><em type="bold">y t </em><em type="bold">he </em><em type="bold">des </em><em type="bold">ired </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">ag </em><em type="bold">em </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t al </em><em type="bold">ter </em><em type="bold">nat </em><em type="bold">iv </em><em type="bold">e </em>– </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Conduct a thorough engagement effort with</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Mykines stakeholders, the</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Faroese public, and other interested parties to identify the desired management alternative.§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Public engagement facilitators§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stakeholder participation</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 3</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Im </em><em type="bold">pl </em><em type="bold">em </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t t </em><em type="bold">he </em><em type="bold">des </em><em type="bold">ired </em><em type="bold">m </em><em type="bold">an </em><em type="bold">agem </em><em type="bold">en </em><em type="bold">t a </em><em type="bold">lter </em><em type="bold">na </em><em type="bold">tive </em><em type="bold">– </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Create the regulation, zoning, infrastructure, and information/education programs, and hire the staff necessary to implement the desired management alternative identified through the engagement process. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government and stakeholderparticipation§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Consultancy and contractor project implementation</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">B - C3</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">On </em><em type="bold">go </em><em type="bold">in </em><em type="bold">g </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">M </em><em type="bold">on </em><em type="bold">ito </em><em type="bold">rin </em><em type="bold">g an </em><em type="bold">d </em><em type="bold">eval </em><em type="bold">uat </em><em type="bold">io </em><em type="bold">n </em><em type="bold">– </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan">On an <em type="bold"></em>ongoing basis, collect and analyze basic data, evaluate data to determine if the implemented management program is accomplishing its goals and/or unintended or unanticipated negative impacts are being created.§ </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">University or consultancy support§</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stakeholder participation</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">A 4 1</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Approximate cost provides categorized rough order of magnitude estimates for each activity.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Conducting research and analysis activities together (e.g., collecting puffin disturbance and visitor survey data at the same time) would result in both substantial cost savings and improved data quality.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Cost categories: A ≤ 100,000</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">DKK;</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">B = 100,000 to 500,000</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">DKK;</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">C ≥ 500,000.` 14 | P a g e</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TRÆLANÍPA is a major tourism destination on the island of Vágar. A typical visit to the area involves hiking from the road (Route 11) near Miðvágur along the southeastern shore of the lake to its outlet at the southern end (approximately 3 km roundtrip). The first part of this hike, which represents most of its distance, paral els the lake’s shoreline on a relatively sustainable alignment. Near the southern end of the lake, the trail forks with one leg turning east and climbing steeply upward to the sea cliffs and the other leg continuing southward toward the lake’s outlet.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The trail to the east climbs at a severely unsustainable grade to the height of land, where a dramatic view emerges with the lake and its outlet above the sea on one side and sea cliffs and ocean on the other. At the time of visit, work had recently been started, but not completed, to construct an improved path up the steep slope. The work is necessary because of the devegetation and related soil erosion that is the result of the trail’s use level and very unsustainable alignment, and that is extensive along this section of the trail. Often, these effects have resulted in multiple deep tracks and holes that cause additional, compounding erosion and are unattractive and unsafe. The current trail construction consists of installing geotextiles, gravel paving, and wooden steps. Recent construction had already begun to fail (i.e., travelers leaving the constructed path because it is too narrow, stairs were falling out, and gravel was eroding off the path exposing geotextiles). Furthermore, at the time of visit the incomplete worksite was left in an untidy and unsafe state. As it exists, the newly constructed trail is difficult to use, unattractive, and, because of its excessive steepness, wil have constant and unmanageable erosion problems leading to failure of the trail. Building a sustainable trail to the top of the sea cliffs would require one of two approaches, neither of which was taken in the existing construction effort. 1.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Design and construction of a long trail that winds its way up the slope at grades generally not exceeding 8% with frequent grade reversals to drain water. 2.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Design and construction of extensive rock stairs made from native material, large enough to resist water-caused erosion along the trail’s grade.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Either of these solutions wil require substantial planning and investment. However, they represent durable, sustainable, and attractive solutions to the existing trail problems.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The trail to the south travels toward the outlet of the lake. However, the distinct single route of the trail soon becomes obscure and multiple routes emerge. Some of these lead toward the lake, others lead toward the sea. The divergence of these trails causes excessive impacts with more paths, and associated devegetation and erosion, than are necessary and confusion among visitors. It is likely that sustainable trail alignments (i.e., at sustainable grades) are possible in this area of Trælanípa without extensive construction.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The landowners in the Trælanípa recently began charging a fee (200 DKK per person) to access the land and hike along the lake. This fee is purported to support environmental management and visitor facilities in the area. Some visitors expressed dissatisfaction with the environmental and facility quality relative to the fee charged.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Credit: IMBA Trail Solutions ` 15 | P a g e ` 16 | P a g e</p>
<p>SAKSUN, TJØRNUVÍK, GJÓGV, MIKLADALUR, TRØLLANES</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Saksun, Tjørnuvík, Gjógv, Mikladalur, and Trøllanes and the Kallur lighthouse are popular tourism destinations in the northern Faroe Islands. Each of these destinations is centered on a small vil age and has one or more small excursions possible from the vil age center (e.g., hikes to lighthouses, waterfalls, mountains, etc.).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Typical visits to these villages begin when tourists park their rental cars. These villages generally have some parking available at the entrance of the vil age and sometimes within the vil age itself. Visitors walk through the villages, admiring architecture and scenery, visiting the harbor, and sometimes a café, shop, or museum. These visitors often also take the excursion(s) available from the village (i.e., hikes or walks).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Common elements of tourist management in all these destinations, which were observed to be of relatively high-quality, include: §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Parking lots at or near the entrance to the vil age </em>. These parking lots allow villages to keep visitor vehicle traffic out of the vil age center and provide visitors with convenient and coordinated locations from which to begin theirs visits. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Orientation signs at the entrance of and key locations within vil ages </em>. Informative welcome signs featuring clear maps, highlighting vil age attractions and providing brief but adequate information on excursions vil age history. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Public toilets </em>. Clean and functional toilet facilities that are centrally located and provided a point for communicating information about the vil age and responsible tourist behavior. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Common emerging, and potentially troublesome, issues related to tourism were also observed in all these destinations. §</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Parking </em>– In each of the destinations, during the busier hours of the day, available public parking is occupied at or beyond capacity. This included the parking lots at the entrance to vil ages, which are ideal y suited for tourist use, and those within vil age centers. If parking demand increases, parking and roadway congestion may result in decreased quality of tourist experiences, increased environmental impacts from parking outside of designated areas, safety hazards as people walk along roadways from undesignated parking to destinations, and reduced resident support for tourism. Parking demand and supply studies followed by integrated transportation and tourism planning would help to address these immerging issues. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Conflict </em>– In each of the destinations, viewing and exploring small Faroese vil ages and their surrounding farms is a primary attraction for tourists. These vil ages are, however, quite small, compact, and intimate. Tourists within the villages are substantially noticeable and different than residents in their dress, motivations, activities, and behaviors. The combination of these differences and the physical and social closeness of the vil ages produces conditions that may result in conflict between tourists and residents, which itself wil damage the quality of tourist experiences and create negative attitudes among residents toward tourism. Public engagement with vil age residents and social science to understand their attitudes and the relationship between tourism and resident experiences would help to inform tourism management to maintain positive public support for tourism in the villages. § </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Trails </em>– Many of the excursions accessed from these vil ages, and a large part of the tourism draw to the Faroe Islands in general, are hikes or walks on trails in the Faroese mountains. These trails are ` 17 | P a g e mostly user-created and often climb open slopes at very steep angles. The level of use these trails are receiving, combined with their often near-vertical alignment and the generally wet climate of the Faroe Islands, has resulted in extensive erosion and related impacts to trails. These impacts are compounding, with visitors creating addition parallel trails to avoid muddy and eroded sections, which itself leads to addition trail impacts and an ongoing cycle of trail proliferation. The consequences of this are both environmental damage and lower quality experiences for tourists and residents alike. Comprehensive trail planning, design, construction, and maintenance would help to address these issues and provide sustainable and high-quality trail resources for use by visitors and residents. ` 18 | P a g e </p>
<p>PHOTOGRAPHIC APPENDIX</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Welcome sign for tourist</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Full parking lot in village center ` 19 | P a g e</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Full parking lot at village entrance</p>
<p>Trail access control and new stair construction at Gjógv. `</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Multiple, unnecessary trails.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Muddiness and trail widening.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Muddiness and multiple trails.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Stairs and trail impacts (i.e., devegetation, erosion) at Gjógv.</p>
<p>Talið av holum nær við gøtuna í Lamba er rímiliga høgt. Hetta merkir at lundin vil reiðrast júst har, men ein undankanning (Ramsar frágreiðing 2018) bendir á, at fleiri holur nær við gøtuna standa tómar og longri frá gøtuni eru fleiri lundaholur í brúk. Hetta er ábending um, at lundin ikki ynskir at reiðrast við gøtuna, helst orsaka av økta órógvinum.</p>
<p><em type="italic">Miðal tal av brúktum holum (holur/m2), 0 til 8 metrar frá gøtuni í Lamba. </em></p>
<p>Kanning frá Skúgvoy vísir, at tað eru ávisar tíðir á degnum, har størsti parturin av sildberunum kemur til lands við føði til pisuna. Møguliga verður hetta, í ávísan mun, stýrt av sjóvarfallinum. Ein líknandi <span type="quote">“sildbera tíðarætlan”</span> er væntandi galdandi í Mykinesi. Fyri at vita hvussu henda tíðarætlanin er í Mykinesi er neyðugt at gera eina kanning (sí niðanfyri).</p>
<p>Vert er at hava í huga, at sildberin er fuglur sum ber føði til pisuna og tí er ógvuliga umráðandi at júst hann verður órógvaður sum minst.</p>
<p>Fyri at minka sum mest um neiliga ávirkan av mannaávum á lundastovnin í Lamba hevði tí rættast verið, at eingin gongd var í økinum í bútíðini.</p>
<p><em type="bold">Kanning </em>Størsta neiliga ávirkanin av gongd í lundalandinum er tengd at hvussu nógv ferðsla talan er um, og eisini hvussu nógvur sildberi roynir at koma við føði til pisuna og her koma vit aftur til <span type="quote">“silbera tíðarætlanina”</span>. </p>
<p>Tær ávísu tíðirnar á degnum, har størsti parturin av sildberanum kemur til lands við føði, eru tær tíðirnar tá ferðsla hevur neiligastu ávirkanina. Í Skúgvoy tykjast tíðirnar, í ávísan mun, at vera stýrdar av sjóvarfallinum. Neyðugt er at kannað um hetta ger seg galdandi í Mykinesi, og í so fall, nær, hetta er, í mun til sjóvarfallið.</p>
<p>Tað verður gjørt við at skráseta tal av sildberum sum koma at landi ígjøgnum dagin, í eitt ávíst tíðarskeið. Hetta skal so endurtakast fleiri ferð ígjøgnum summarið, tí møguliga kann henda tíðarætlanin broytast ígjøgnum summarið m.a. orsaka av sjóvarfalli.</p>
<p>Fyri at kunna gera eina meting av <span type="quote">“lunda tíðarætlanini”</span> er neyðugt, at skráseta talið av sildberum frá morgni til myrkurs.</p>
<p>Fyri at fáa eina rætta natúrliga mynd av ferðamynstrinum og tíðarætlanunum hjá sildberanum, er neyðugt at avmarka menniskjaliga ávirkan á atburðin hjá honum. Størsta ávirkanin á lundan í hesum økinum er uttan iva ferðafólk í økinum. Tí er neyðugt at steðga allari ferðslu gjøgnum Lamba meðan kanninging verður gjørd.</p>
<p>Ein tílík kanning eigur at vera gjørd sum skjótast, t.v.s. longu komandi summar (2020) og eigur at fyriskipast saman við regluligu Ramsar kanningunum.</p>
<p><em type="bold">JÓHANNIS DANIELSEN </em>, HAVSTOVAN <em type="bold">LEIVUR JANUS HANSEN </em>, TJÓÐSAVNIÐ </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Anderson, D. W., and Keith, J. O. (1980). The human influence on seabird nesting success: conservation implications. <em type="italic">Biol. Conserv. </em>18: 65–8. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Yuri V. Albores-Barajas, Cecilia Soldatini, Robert W. Furness "Are Burrow Nesting Seabird Chicks Affected by Human Disturbance?," Waterbirds, 32(4), 572-578, (1 December 2009).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Morrison, K. W., Hipfner, J. M., Gjerdrum, C., and Green, D. J. (2009). Wing length and mass at fledging predict local juvenile survival and age at first return in Tufted Puffins. <em type="italic">Condor </em>111: 433–441. </p>
<p>McClung, M. R., Seddon, P. J., Massaro, M., and Setiawan A. N. (2004). Nature-based tourism impacts on yellow-eyed penguins <em type="italic">Megadyptes antipodes: </em>does unregulated visitor access affect fledging weight and juvenile survival? <em type="italic">Biol. Conserv. </em>119: 279–285. </p>
<p>Lundi <em type="italic">Fratercula arctica grabae. </em>Teljing í Mykinesi í 2015. Jóhannis Danielsen, Leivur Janus Hansen og Christina Joensen. Tjóðsavnið, Ramsar frágreiðing 2019. Lundi <em type="italic">Fratercula arctica grabae. </em>Teljing í Mykinesi í 2017. Jóhannis Danielsen, Ana Paula Cairneiro Bertoldi og Leivur Janus Hansen. Tjóðsavnið, Ramsar frágreiðing 2019. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Ellenberg, U., Mattern, T., Seddon, P. J., and Luna Jorquera, G. (2006). Physiological and reproductive consequences of human disturbance in Humboldt penguins: The need for speciesspecific visitor management. <em type="italic">Biol. Conserv. </em>133: 95–106. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Gill, J. A., Norris, K., and Sutherland, W. J. (2001). Why behavioural responses may not reflect the population consequences of human disturbance. <em type="italic">Biol. Conserv. </em>97: 265–268. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Martínez-Abraín, A., Oro, D., Conesa, D., and Jiménez, J. (2008). Compromise between seabird enjoyment and disturbance: the role of observed and observers. <em type="italic">Environ. Conserv. </em>35: 104–108. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">KELDUR <em type="bold">40% </em><em type="bold">0 </em><em type="bold">2 </em><em type="bold">4 </em><em type="bold">6 </em><em type="bold">8 </em><em type="bold">58% </em><em type="bold">73% </em><em type="bold">78% </em><em type="bold">70% </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Lutfall av brúktum holum </em></p>
<p><em type="italic">Uppskot til nýggja gonguleið, ið skal skipast, uppmerkjast og gerast eftir røttum forskriftum. </em></p>
<p>AÐRAR</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">GONGULEIÐIR</p>
<p>STEÐGUR Á LEIÐINI Á leiðini runt er hugsað, at møguleiki skal vera at staðfesta nøkur steðgistøð. Tað kann t.d. verða eitt útsýnisstað, eitt uppihaldsstað ella eitt kunningarskelti. Hesi støð skulu virka sum eitt slag av varðum, eitt stað gingið verður eftir, eitt stað her til ber at halda ein steðg.</p>
</body></document>
