<document xml:lang="fao" id="no_id"><header><title/><genre code="admin"/><author><unknown/></author><wordcount>3573</wordcount><conversion_status type="standard"/><availability><license type="standard"/></availability><multilingual><language xml:lang="dan"/></multilingual><origFileName>kanning-av-aljtóða-internetnýtslu.pdf</origFileName><metadata><uncomplete/></metadata><version>XSLtemplate $Revision: 187360 $; file-specific xsl  Revision; common.xsl  $Revision: 154948 $; </version></header><body><p xml:lang="dan">Government OnlineGovernment Online<em type="italic">an international perspectivean international perspective</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">ANNUAL GLOBAL REPORT </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Australia, Canada, Czech Republic, Denmark, Estonia, Faroe Islands, Finland, France, Germany, Great Britain, Hong Kong, Hungary, India, Ireland, Italy, Japan, Latvia, Lithuania, Malaysia, Netherlands, New Zealand, Norway, Poland, Singapore, Slovak Republic, South Korea, Spain, Sweden, Taiwan, Turkey, United States of America. </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Global ReportGlobal Report</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">NOVEMBER,  2002TNS CONSULTANTS:  W MELLOR, V PARR</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">In 2001, Taylor Nelson Sofres (TNS), the global market research company, benchmarked the use of Government Online by interviewing over 29,000 adults in 28 countries.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">This study is unique in that it examines the uptake of Government Online from a citizen demand perspective.  As more Government Agencies around the world make greater use of Information Communications Technology (ICT) to develop alternative channels to meet the needs of citizens, it is important to understand the extent to which citizens are changing their patterns of behaviour and embracing the new opportunities that the Internet can bring.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TNS recognises the significant benefits that Government Online can bring to both citizens and Government Agencies, and the importance of encouraging its adoption.  Since they were first published in November 2001, the results of Government Online have been extensively used by Government strategists and planners,  professionally interested organisations and consultants and the media.  The results have been discussed at a number of government, knowledge management and e-government conferences around the world.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">In 2002, TNS has continued to track Government Online usage.  Again approximately 29,000 adults were interviewed, with 31 countries involved.  This report examines the international implications.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">For more information about the Government Online study, please contact your local TNS office or email</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">gostudy@au.tnsofres.comfor a copy of y</em>our country report. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The key aim of this study is to understand the impact of the Internet on government globally and nationally.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">More specifically the study objectives are to...</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Monitor the growth and establish new benchmarks against which to measure future growth of Government Online, globally and nationally.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Measure the ‘adoption curve’ for the utilisation of government services online, from information seeking and citizen consultation, to engaging in some sort of transaction.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Understand whether Government Online is reaching the broader community in terms of demographics.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Determine any levels of fear associated with providing government with personal information over the Internet, and the extent to which this may be a barrier to Government Online uptake.</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Provide global and national benchmarks against which individual government departments can measure themselves against in terms of:</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">• reach;</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">• adoption;</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">• demographic characteristics; and</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">• concerns over safety of personal information.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">One identical question about the use of Government services online was placed on a substantial, nationally representative survey in 31 countries between July and September 2002*.  All field work was conducted by TNS offices.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">An optional second question, regarding perceptions of safety when providing personal information to Government was asked of everyone in 27 countries, and asked of Internet users in one countries.**</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sample size…</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">All country results have been weighted to be representative of their country population.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">This report was prepared by Wendy Mellor and Victoria Parr from TNS Australia.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">31 countries 28,952 people interviewed</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">31 countries 28,952 people interviewed</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">27 countries 29,077 people interviewed</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">27 countries 29,077 people interviewed</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Europe</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Asia Pacific...</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Australia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Hong Kong</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">India</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Japan</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Malaysia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">New Zealand</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Singapore</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">South Korea</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Taiwan</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">North America</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">United States</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Canada</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Čzech Republic</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Denmark</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Estonia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Faroe Islands</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Finland</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">France</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Germany</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Great Britain</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Hungary</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Ireland</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Italy</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Latvia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Lithuania</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Netherlands</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Norway</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Poland</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Slovakia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Spain</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Sweden</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Turkey</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Asia Pacific</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Government Online (GO) -</em>Assessing Government over the Internet. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Information Seekers </em>- Have used the Internet to get information from a Government website. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Downloaders</em>- Used the Internet to print off government forms that were then sent by post or fax (e.g. tax </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">form, form to claim Government rebates).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Consulters</em>- Used the internet to express a point of view or participate in community consultations with </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Providers </em>- Used the Internet to provide personal/household information to Government. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Transactors </em>- Used the Internet to pay for Government services or products through the use of a credit </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">card or bank account number (e.g. rates, driving licences, recycle bins, traffic fines).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Non-users </em>- Have not used the Internet to get or provide information or transact with Government. </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">were thewere the</em> </p>
<p>2002</p>
<p><em type="italic">Key ResultsKey Results</em> </p>
<p><em type="italic">inin</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Global Government Online usage increased significantly since it was first measured in 2001.  30% of the adult population surveyed had used Government Online in the last twelve months, compared with 26% in 2001.  There have been significant increases since 2001 in 14 countries, and only one country fell back (Japan dropping from 17% to 13%). Whilst the global average for Government Online usage has increased by 4%, in some countries the increase has been far greater.  The major gain in Government Online usage have been in Australia (+31% to 46%),Turkey (+10% to 13%), USA (+9% to 43%), India (+9% to 31% of Internet users), Spain (+9% to 26%), France (+7% to 25%) and Germany (+7% to 24%).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Information Seeking</em>continues to be the major use made of Government Online (24% of adults) and this </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">has risen significantly from 20% in 2001.  <em type="bold">Downloading</em>(forms, etc) is the second major use made of Government Online (11%) and this application has risen since 2001(9%). </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Providers</em>(who provide information to Government over the Internet) represent 8% of the global </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">population (7% in 2001) whilst <em type="bold">Transacting</em>(providing bank account or credit card details to Government over the internet in exchange for service, product or infringement or rebate) was 7% (compared with 6% in 2001).  Government Online transacting (15% of Internet users) equals the incidence of Online Product Shopping (15% Internet users). </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">For the first time, <em type="bold">Consulters </em>(who use the Internet to express a point of view) were measured, and globally this is currently a relatively low usage interaction (4%). </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Since 2001 there has been very little change to the shape of the Government Online adoption curve.  It is dominated by Information Seeking (24%) which demonstrates the value of this communication channel to Government.  As Government‘s around the world seeks to provide more interactive services to its citizens, it is clear that these usage types have not grown (Transactors 7%, Providers 8%).  This relatively slow  uptake of interactive services may be because not enough services are provided yet, because the public is slow to take advantage of them, or because inappropriate services (i.e. those not meeting community needs) are being made available.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The global average for Transacting is 7% but some countries (Sweden, Estonia, Denmark, Finland, Norway) are achieving around 20% which demonstrates that the demand for this interaction exists, if the supply/demand balance is right.  A similar comment can be made of Providing.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Of the 31 countries surveyed, Sweden has the highest level of Government Online (57% over the last twelve months), whilst New Zealand has the highest Internet usage (71% in last month).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">There is wide variation in the level of Government Online uptake across the countries measured (3% in Hungary to 57% in Sweden).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The high Government Online user countries are: Sweden (57%) , Norway (56%), Singapore (53%), Denmark (53%), Faroe Islands (52%), Finland (49%), Canada (48%), Australia (46%) and the USA (43%).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Countries with relatively low levels of Government Online usage include: Slovak Republic (14%), Turkey (13%), Great Britain (13%), Japan (13%), Malaysia (12%), Lithuania (8%), Latvia (8%), Poland (4%) and Hungary (3%).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Scandinavian countries dominate the top 5 countries for Information Seeking, Downloading, Consulting, Providing and Transacting.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">There is a wide range of variation amongst those who use the Internet (in the last month) and their uptake of Government Online.  This proportion ranges from 82% in the Faroe Islands to 16% in Hungary.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Whilst Internet penetration is strongly correlated with age (the younger you are the more likely you are to use the Internet), this is not the experience of Government Online.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government Online usage is strong among under 44 year olds and then it drops away.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The biggest increases have been in the 35-44 year old grouping (rising 14% from 22% in 2001 to 36% in 2002) and among older people.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">About one in five people (18%) aged 55-64 years old have used Government Online in the last twelve months which represents an increase of 16% amongst that age group.  However those aged 65+ years have yet to realise Government Online (5% 2002).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Men are more likely to use Government Online (33% in 2002 compared with 26% women).  This gender difference was noted in 2001 but has become more pronounced.  It does reflect the gender skew  observed for Internet usage.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">There has been an increase in perceptions of safety when interacting with Government Online concerning personal information such as credit card, bank account number or salary size, rising from 14% safe in 2001 to 23% safe in 2002.*  Rather than there being a decrease in those perceiving it to be ‘unsafe’, there are less citizens who are unsure (dropping from 22% to 14%).  These are positive trends for Government, however the challenge for ICT providers and Government is to raise the perception of safety upwards, so more than 1 in 4 citizens believe this to be so.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Countries with the highest levels of perceived safety are: Denmark (40%), Singapore (39%), Finland (35%), Hong Kong (33%), Norway (32%) and Sweden (32%).  These countries demonstrate that despite their citizens having relatively high Government Online use, the levels of safety are still quite modest.  Hong Kong stands out as having a relatively high level of safety (5th highest) compared with its Government Online usage (12th globally).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Countries that have raised the level of safety include: Malaysia (from 23% to 35%), Denmark (from 31% to 40%), Norway (from 26% to 32%), Slovak Republic (from 15% to 21%), France (from 11% to 15% and Poland (from 9% to 12%).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">However increases in countries tracked in 2001 and 2002 show significant increases overall.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Countries with the highest concerns about safety are: Japan (90%), Germany (82%), France (76%), Taiwan (75%) and Italy (72%).</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Men are more likely to think that Government Online is safe (27%), perhaps reflecting their higher usage of Internet and Government Online generally.  Similar to the 2001 results, the younger you are, the more trusting.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">More non-users consider Government Online to be unsafe (64%) rather than safe (16%), while a further fifth (19%) had no opinion. Comparing the different types of Government Online users, Information Seekers globally have the greatest concern about safety (58%). Transactors and Providers have lower levels of concern (51% and 50% respectively).  Citizens globally are giving clear notice to Government that high safety strategies should be in place and be adhered too.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Scandinavian countries are highly adoptive of Government Online, however there has been some leveling off in Norway and Finland in the reach of Government Online, although citizens there (</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Great Britain has not made much progress in reaching or interacting with citizens through Government Online,and it remains well below average.  Whilst there has been tremendous investment made by all levels of Government in Great Britain, this does not appear to have been rewarded yet by citizen uptake.  The citizen benefits of other delivery channels (telephone, face to face, kiosks) are currently outweighing those from the Internet.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Ireland, which has benefited from significant EU investment, was measured for the first time and its Government Online uptake was twice that of Great Britain.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">France and Germany experienced gains of a similar magnitude in the reach of Government Online.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Spain and the Netherlands also increased in Government Online usage, including Information Seeking. The Turkish Government has placed greater emphasis on electronic communication since 2001, particularly in making more information available to  citizens on the Internet. The result has been substantial increases in usage (from 3% to 13%). Recent developments have allowed citizens to be able to search for and receive personal information, such as university results and ID and tax number, via the Internet. Among  East European (Post-Communist) countries the level of  Government Online usage varies from 3% in Hungary and 4% in Poland to 31% in Estonia. The adoption of  Government Online is a continuing challenge for all these countries and is directly affected by government policy towards developing an <span type="quote" xml:lang="dan">“information society”</span>. In Poland Government Online is currently not a high priority in government policy and encouragement for using Internet generally  is low. A very different government policy in Estonia is reflected in the results. Latvia has only recently adopted an e-government project, and at the moment are at initial stage of development of GO communication. This policy will likely impact on incidence levels of GO in Lativia when  next measured.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Singapore stands out as an Asia Pacific country where citizens have strongly embraced Government Online. The policy of the Singapore Government  to transform Singapore into an intelligent island has involved initiatives including educating Singaporeans in Internet skills (National IT Literacy Programme), nationwide broadband network that delivers interactive multimedia applications and services (S-One) and a dedicated portal that allows  accessibility to a range of e-Government <em type="italic">services (www.ecitizen.gov.sg).  The d</em>ate of fieldwork in Singapore coincided with the dates for filing incomes and paying Income tax. Much have been done by the Government to encourage Singaporeans to file their income or pay their tax electronically (e-filing). </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Australia, with a history of being highly adoptive of new  technologies, has experienced the greatest increase in Government Online usage, from information seeking to transacting.  National and State Governments have made a wide range of services available over the Internet with a whole-of -Government portal. Hong Kong also increased its Government Online usage, with increases in information seeking and downloading Malaysia has low incidence of Government Online and is currently not experiencing an upward trend in usage (despite increases in the perception of safety). Whilst the Indian data is based only on internet users, there has been a significant increase in uptake and specifically information seeking. Japan has been the only country with reduced Government Online activity.  Interaction such as transacting  and providing has reduced.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">The USA benchmark in 2001 was undertaken prior to September 11.  It is well documented that Government Online took on a different meaning after this date and the high increase in Government Online is likely to be enhanced by this.  Information Seeking and Downloading has increased.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Canada did not experience a significant increase in the reach of Government Online but Downloading has increased.</p>
<p><em type="bold">HighestLowest </em></p>
<p><em type="bold">Globally…</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Internet usage Government Online usage</p>
<p>Hungary13% Hungary3%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Transactors Providers Consultors</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Downloaders</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Information Seekers</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Attitudes to GO safety…</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Nett safe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Nett unsafe</p>
<p>14</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unsure</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Hungary0% Poland0% South Korea 0% Turkey0% Hungary1%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Japan6% Latvia41% Germany1%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">New Zealand 71% Sweden57%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden22% Denmark25% Faroe Islands16% Sweden26% Sweden48%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark40% Japan90% Lithuania43%</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Global Average </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">%</em> <em type="bold">Global Average </em></p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">%</em> <em type="bold">Percentage (%) Change From 2001</em> </p>
<p>+ + + n/an/a + + + - -</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">PERCENTAGE OF POPULATION WHO USED GOVERNMENT ONLINE SERVICES IN THE PAST TWELVE MONTHS</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">%</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">40 4146 4852 53 5356 57</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Global Average (30%)</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">23 24 2530 31 31</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">18 20</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">312 13 13 13 14</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">GO Users as % of population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden*n/an/an/a NorwayNone SingaporeNone50 (Feb'02)n/a Denmark Faroe Islands*n/an/an/a FinlandNone CanadaNone Australia USA Netherlands</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">GO Users as % of population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">New Zealand*n/an/an/a Hong Kong Estonia n/aIndia#n/a TaiwanNone Spain Ireland*n/an/an/a France Germany South Korea</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">GO Users as % of population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Italy*n/an/an/a Czech RepublicNone Slovak Republic Turkey Great BritainNone Japan MalaysiaNone Lithuania LatviaNone PolandNone Hungary+n/an/an/a</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">PERCENTAGE OF POPULATION WHO HAVE PERSONALLY USED THE INTERNET IN THE PAST MONTH</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Country Average Internet Use (42%)</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">13</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">PERCENTAGE OF GOVERNMENT ONLINE USERS BASED ON INTERNET USE</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Internet Users GO Uptake - Country Average Use (61%)</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">16</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Medium PenetrationMedium PenetrationHigh PenetrationHigh Penetration</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Very High PenetrationVery High Penetration</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Low PenetrationLow Penetration</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">(16% to 35% are users)(36% to 50% are users)</em> </p>
<p><em type="italic">(more than 50% are users)</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Slovak Republic Turkey Great Britain Japan Malaysia Lithuania Latvia Poland Hungary</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Estonia India# Taiwan Spain Ireland France Germany South Korea Italy Czech Republic Finland Canada Australia USA Netherlands </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government Online?Government Online?</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">uses theuses thea n da n dInternetInternet</em> </p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">As was found in 2001, males are using the Internet more than females. Globally, younger people continue to have the highest incidence of Internet usage.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMaleFemaleUnder 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Males are using Government Online more than females are. Those aged under 44 years make good use of Government Online.  The biggest growth since 2001 has been amongst the 34-44 and 55-64 age groupings.  People aged 65+ continue to make little use of Government Online, reflecting their low Internet usage generally.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>26</p>
<p>TotalMaleFemaleUnder 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+ <em type="italic">dodou s e  u s e  citizenscitizens</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government Online?Government Online?</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TransactorsProvidersConsultersDownloadersInformation Seekers</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Non GO Users</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">There has been little change to the shape of the Government Online adoption curve since 2001. The major Government Online use continues to be Information Seeking.  This has risen significantly since 2001.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p>6</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Consulters were not measured</em> <em type="bold">in 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TransactorsProvidersDownloadersInformation Seekers</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Non GO Users 15% of Internet users have made an Government Online transaction in the last twelve months.  Given the increase in Internet usage, Government Online transacting has not grown proportionately.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">This compares equally with the purchase of goods over the Internet.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Examples of Online Product Shopping are buying books, CDs, sports equipment, tickets to the cinema and theatre, and travel online.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">ers</em>% </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government Online Transactors</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Online Product Shoppers</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>7</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Transactors can come from any gender but are more likely to be aged 25-44 years.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>8</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Providers are more likely to be under 44 years of age.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>4</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Consulters are a relatively small user of Government Online and are spread across genders and age groups.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>11</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Downloaders are more likely to be aged 25-44 years.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>24</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Information Seekers are more likely to be male and aged under 44 years.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em>% </p>
<p>71</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Non GO Users are more likely to be 55 years or more.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Information SeekingDownloading</em> </p>
<p>48%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden</p>
<p>26%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden</p>
<p>48%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Norway</p>
<p>24%</p>
<p>Canada</p>
<p>47%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark</p>
<p>24%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Singapore</p>
<p>46%</p>
<p>Faroe Islands</p>
<p>22%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Norway</p>
<p>42%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Finland</p>
<p>21%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">USA</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Consulting</em> </p>
<p>16%</p>
<p>Faroe Islands</p>
<p>10%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">USA</p>
<p>9%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Norway</p>
<p>7%</p>
<p>Canada</p>
<p>7%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Finland</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">ProvidingTransacting</em> </p>
<p>25%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark</p>
<p>22%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden</p>
<p>23%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Singapore</p>
<p>21%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Estonia</p>
<p>22%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Norway</p>
<p>20%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark</p>
<p>21%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Sweden</p>
<p>20%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Finland</p>
<p>17%</p>
<p>Canada</p>
<p>18%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Norway</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Government OnlineGovernment Online<em type="italic">as as SAFE SAFE to use?to use?</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">s e es e ecitizenscitizens</em> <em type="italic">How safe would you feel about using the Internet to provide the Government with this sort of personal information?</em><em type="bold">Q</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">GLOBAL NETT SAFE AND SPECIFICS, NETT UNSAFE AND SPECIFICS</em> </p>
<p>NETT SAFE</p>
<p>Very Safe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Safe</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>-34</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Despite an increase in the perception of safety, there remains substantial levels of concern among the total adult population when providing personal information to Government over the Internet.</p>
<p>-</p>
<p>NETT UNSAFE</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unsafe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Very Unsafe</p>
<p>%</p>
<p>----</p>
<p>100%</p>
<p>50 50 54</p>
<p>80%</p>
<p>57 52</p>
<p>58 58</p>
<p>66 64 61 6658 52</p>
<p>60%</p>
<p>15 10 6</p>
<p>40%</p>
<p>50</p>
<p>24 23 15</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Unsafe</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Don't Know</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Safe</p>
<p>20%</p>
<p>6 11 1112 12 13 15 15 1618 20 21 22 2226 27 2930 31 31 32 32 33 35 3539 40</p>
<p>0%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Nett Safe As % Of Population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark SingaporeNone (Feb '02)n/a FinlandNone Malaysia Hong KongNone Norway Sweden*n/an/an/a Ireland*n/an/an/a New Zealand*n/an/an/a AustraliaNone</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Nett Safe As % Of Population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">EstoniaNone CanadaNone Great Britain#n/an/an/a NetherlandsNone LatviaNone Slovak Republic TurkeyNone Faroe Islands*n/an/an/a</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Nett Safe As % Of Population</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">2002</em> <em type="bold">%%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Rank 2002CountrySignificant (Increase/ Decrease) From</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Rank 2001</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Italy*n/an/an/a GermanyNone France Hungary#n/an/an/a Poland Czech RepublicNone Lithuania TaiwanNone JapanNone India+Nonen/a</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">% Safe% Unsafe</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Denmark</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Japan</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Singapore</p>
<p>Germany</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Finland</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">France</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Malaysia</p>
<p>Taiwan</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Hong Kong</p>
<p>Italy</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMale Female Under 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">Males and those under 34 years are more likely to think Government Online is safe.</p>
<p>%</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">AgeGender</em> </p>
<p>63</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">TotalMaleFemaleUnder 2525-3435-4445-5455-6465+</p>
<p>Safety concerns are highest amongst women and those 45-64 years.</p>
<p><em type="bold">%</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Very safe</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Safe</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Unsafe</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">19</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Very unsafe</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Don't know</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">TransactorsProvidersConsultersDownloadersInformation</em> <em type="bold">Seekers</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Non GO Users</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="italic">Appendices</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan">In the last twelve months, have you yourself used the Internet to...</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Get information from a Government website?</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Used the Internet to print off Government forms (e.g. tax form, form to claim a government rebate) which you have then sent by post or fax?</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Used the Internet to provide personal/household information to Government (e.g. complete and lodge a tax form, apply for a service, change your address)?</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Used the Internet to pay for Government services or products (e.g. rates, driving license, recycle bins, traffic fine) involving the use of a credit card or your bank account number?</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– Used the internet to express a point of view or participate in community consultations with Government?</p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">– None of these?</p>
<p xml:lang="dan">How safe would you feel about using the internet to provide the Government with this sort of personal information?</p>
<p type="listitem">– Very safe, safe, unsafe, very unsafe, don’t know?</p>
<p type="listitem">– Yes, No, Don’t Know/Refused/No Response.</p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">Europe</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Asia Pacific...</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Australia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Hong Kong</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">India</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Indonesia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Japan</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Malaysia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">South Korea</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Taiwan</em> </p>
<p xml:lang="dan"><em type="bold">North America</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">United States</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Canada</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Čzech Republic</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Denmark</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Estonia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Finland</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">France</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Germany</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Great Britain</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Hungary</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Latvia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Lithuania</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Netherlands</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Norway</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Poland</em> </p>
<p type="listitem" xml:lang="dan">•<em type="bold">Russian Federation</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Slovakia</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Spain</em> </p>
<p type="listitem">•<em type="bold">Turkey</em> </p>
<p><em type="bold">Asia Pacific</em> </p>
</body></document>